John

The Gospel According to

John

I

1^1In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God.

^2The same was in the beginning with God.

^3All things were made by him; and without him was not any thing made that was made.

^4In him was life; and the life was the light of men.

^5And the light shineth in darkness; and the darkness comprehended it not.

^6There was a man sent from God, whose name was John.

^7The same came for a witness, to bear witness of the Light, that all men through him might believe.

^8He was not that Light, but was sent to bear witness of that Light.

^9That was the true Light, which lighteth every man that cometh into the world.

^10He was in the world, and the world was made by him, and the world knew him not.

^11He came unto his own, and his own received him not.

^12But as many as received him, to them gave he power to become the sons of God, even to them that believe on his name:

^13Which were born, not of blood, nor of the will of the flesh, nor of the will of man, but of God.

^14And the Word was made flesh, and dwelt among us, (and we beheld his glory, the glory as of the only begotten of the Father,) full of grace and truth.

^15John bare witness of him, and cried, saying, This was he of whom I spake, He that cometh after me is preferred before me: for he was before me.

^16And of his fulness have all we received, and grace for grace.

^17For the law was given by Moses, but grace and truth came by Jesus Christ.

^18No man hath seen God at any time, the only begotten Son, which is in the bosom of the Father, he hath declared him.

^19And this is the record of John, when the Jews sent priests and Levites from Jerusalem to ask him, Who art thou?

^20And he confessed, and denied not; but confessed, I am not the Christ.

^21And they asked him, What then? Art thou Elias? And he saith, I am not. Art thou that prophet? And he answered, No.

^22Then said they unto him, Who art thou? that we may give an answer to them that sent us. What sayest thou of thyself?

^23He said, I am the voice of one crying in the wilderness, Make straight the way of the Lord, as said the prophet Esaias.

^24And they which were sent were of the Pharisees.

^25And they asked him, and said unto him, Why baptizest thou then, if thou be not that Christ, nor Elias, neither that prophet?

^26John answered them, saying, I baptize with water: but there standeth one among you, whom ye know not;

^27He it is, who coming after me is preferred before me, whose shoe’s latchet I am not worthy to unloose.

^28These things were done in Bethabara beyond Jordan, where John was baptizing.

^29The next day John seeth Jesus coming unto him, and saith, Behold the Lamb of God, which taketh away the sin of the world.

^30This is he of whom I said, After me cometh a man which is preferred before me: for he was before me.

^31And I knew him not: but that he should be made manifest to Israel, therefore am I come baptizing with water.

^32And John bare record, saying, I saw the Spirit descending from heaven like a dove, and it abode upon him.

^33And I knew him not: but he that sent me to baptize with water, the same said unto me, Upon whom thou shalt see the Spirit descending, and remaining on him, the same is he which baptizeth with the Holy Ghost.

^34And I saw, and bare record that this is the Son of God.

^35Again the next day after John stood, and two of his disciples;

^36And looking upon Jesus as he walked, he saith, Behold the Lamb of God!

^37And the two disciples heard him speak, and they followed Jesus.

^38Then Jesus turned, and saw them following, and saith unto them, What seek ye? They said unto him, Rabbi, (which is to say, being interpreted, Master,) where dwellest thou?

^39He saith unto them, Come and see. They came and saw where he dwelt, and abode with him that day: for it was about the tenth hour.

^40One of the two which heard John speak, and followed him, was Andrew, Simon Peter’s brother.

^41He first findeth his own brother Simon, and saith unto him, We have found the Messias, which is, being interpreted, the Christ.

^42And he brought him to Jesus. And when Jesus beheld him, he said, Thou art Simon the son of Jona: thou shalt be called Cephas, which is by interpretation, A stone.

^43The day following Jesus would go forth into Galilee, and findeth Philip, and saith unto him, Follow me.

^44Now Philip was of Bethsaida, the city of Andrew and Peter.

^45Philip findeth Nathanael, and saith unto him, We have found him, of whom Moses in the law, and the prophets, did write, Jesus of Nazareth, the son of Joseph.

^46And Nathanael said unto him, Can there any good thing come out of Nazareth? Philip saith unto him, Come and see.

^47Jesus saw Nathanael coming to him, and saith of him, Behold an Israelite indeed, in whom is no guile!

^48Nathanael saith unto him, Whence knowest thou me? Jesus answered and said unto him, Before that Philip called thee, when thou wast under the fig tree, I saw thee.

^49Nathanael answered and saith unto him, Rabbi, thou art the Son of God; thou art the King of Israel.

^50Jesus answered and said unto him, Because I said unto thee, I saw thee under the fig tree, believest thou? thou shalt see greater things than these.

^51And he saith unto him, Verily, verily, I say unto you, Hereafter ye shall see heaven open, and the angels of God ascending and descending upon the Son of man.

II

2^1And the third day there was a marriage in Cana of Galilee; and the mother of Jesus was there:

^2And both Jesus was called, and his disciples, to the marriage.

^3And when they wanted wine, the mother of Jesus saith unto him, They have no wine.

^4Jesus saith unto her, Woman, what have I to do with thee? mine hour is not yet come.

^5His mother saith unto the servants, Whatsoever he saith unto you, do it.

^6And there were set there six waterpots of stone, after the manner of the purifying of the Jews, containing two or three firkins apiece.

^7Jesus saith unto them, Fill the waterpots with water. And they filled them up to the brim.

^8And he saith unto them, Draw out now, and bear unto the governor of the feast. And they bare it.

^9When the ruler of the feast had tasted the water that was made wine, and knew not whence it was: (but the servants which drew the water knew;) the governor of the feast called the bridegroom,

^10And saith unto him, Every man at the beginning doth set forth good wine; and when men have well drunk, then that which is worse: but thou hast kept the good wine until now.

^11This beginning of miracles did Jesus in Cana of Galilee, and manifested forth his glory; and his disciples believed on him.

^12After this he went down to Capernaum, he, and his mother, and his brethren, and his disciples: and they continued there not many days.

^13And the Jews’ passover was at hand, and Jesus went up to Jerusalem.

^14And found in the temple those that sold oxen and sheep and doves, and the changers of money sitting:

^15And when he had made a scourge of small cords, he drove them all out of the temple, and the sheep, and the oxen; and poured out the changers’ money, and overthrew the tables;

^16And said unto them that sold doves, Take these things hence; make not my Father’s house an house of merchandise.

^17And his disciples remembered that it was written, The zeal of thine house hath eaten me up.

^18Then answered the Jews and said unto him, What sign shewest thou unto us, seeing that thou doest these things?

^19Jesus answered and said unto them, Destroy this temple, and in three days I will raise it up.

^20Then said the Jews, Forty and six years was this temple in building, and wilt thou rear it up in three days?

^21But he spake of the temple of his body.

^22When therefore he was risen from the dead, his disciples remembered that he had said this unto them; and they believed the scripture, and the word which Jesus had said.

^23Now when he was in Jerusalem at the passover, in the feast day, many believed in his name, when they saw the miracles which he did.

^24But Jesus did not commit himself unto them, because he knew all men,

^25And needed not that any should testify of man: for he knew what was in man.

III

3^1There was a man of the Pharisees, named Nicodemus, a ruler of the Jews:

^2The same came to Jesus by night, and said unto him, Rabbi, we know that thou art a teacher come from God: for no man can do these miracles that thou doest, except God be with him.

^3Jesus answered and said unto him, Verily, verily, I say unto thee, Except a man be born again, he cannot see the kingdom of God.

^4Nicodemus saith unto him, How can a man be born when he is old? can he enter the second time into his mother’s womb, and be born?

^5Jesus answered, Verily, verily, I say unto thee, Except a man be born of water and of the Spirit, he cannot enter into the kingdom of God.

^6That which is born of the flesh is flesh; and that which is born of the Spirit is spirit.

^7Marvel not that I said unto thee, Ye must be born again.

^8The wind bloweth where it listeth, and thou hearest the sound thereof, but canst not tell whence it cometh, and whither it goeth: so is every one that is born of the Spirit.

^9Nicodemus answered and said unto him, How can these things be?

^10Jesus answered and said unto him, Art thou a master of Israel, and knowest not these things?

^11Verily, verily, I say unto thee, We speak that we do know, and testify that we have seen; and ye receive not our witness.

^12If I have told you earthly things, and ye believe not, how shall ye believe, if I tell you of heavenly things?

^13And no man hath ascended up to heaven, but he that came down from heaven, even the Son of man which is in heaven.

^14And as Moses lifted up the serpent in the wilderness, even so must the Son of man be lifted up:

^15That whosoever believeth in him should not perish, but have eternal life.

^16For God so loved the world, that he gave his only begotten Son, that whosoever believeth in him should not perish, but have everlasting life.

^17For God sent not his Son into the world to condemn the world; but that the world through him might be saved.

^18He that believeth on him is not condemned: but he that believeth not is condemned already, because he hath not believed in the name of the only begotten Son of God.

^19And this is the condemnation, that light is come into the world, and men loved darkness rather than light, because their deeds were evil.

^20For every one that doeth evil hateth the light, neither cometh to the light, lest his deeds should be reproved.

^21But he that doeth truth cometh to the light, that his deeds may be made manifest, that they are wrought in God.

^22After these things came Jesus and his disciples into the land of Judaea; and there he tarried with them, and baptized.

^23And John also was baptizing in Aenon near to Salim, because there was much water there: and they came, and were baptized.

^24For John was not yet cast into prison.

^25Then there arose a question between some of John’s disciples and the Jews about purifying.

^26And they came unto John, and said unto him, Rabbi, he that was with thee beyond Jordan, to whom thou barest witness, behold, the same baptizeth, and all men come to him.

^27John answered and said, A man can receive nothing, except it be given him from heaven.

^28Ye yourselves bear me witness, that I said, I am not the Christ, but that I am sent before him.

^29He that hath the bride is the bridegroom: but the friend of the bridegroom, which standeth and heareth him, rejoiceth greatly because of the bridegroom’s voice: this my joy therefore is fulfilled.

^30He must increase, but I must decrease.

^31He that cometh from above is above all: he that is of the earth is earthly, and speaketh of the earth: he that cometh from heaven is above all.

^32And what he hath seen and heard, that he testifieth; and no man receiveth his testimony.

^33He that hath received his testimony hath set to his seal that God is true.

^34For he whom God hath sent speaketh the words of God: for God giveth not the Spirit by measure unto him.

^35The Father loveth the Son, and hath given all things into his hand.

^36He that believeth on the Son hath everlasting life: and he that believeth not the Son shall not see life; but the wrath of God abideth on him.

IV

4^1When therefore the Lord knew how the Pharisees had heard that Jesus made and baptized more disciples than John,

^2(Though Jesus himself baptized not, but his disciples,)

^3He left Judaea, and departed again into Galilee.

^4And he must needs go through Samaria.

^5Then cometh he to a city of Samaria, which is called Sychar, near to the parcel of ground that Jacob gave to his son Joseph.

^6Now Jacob’s well was there. Jesus therefore, being wearied with his journey, sat thus on the well: and it was about the sixth hour.

^7There cometh a woman of Samaria to draw water: Jesus saith unto her, Give me to drink.

^8(For his disciples were gone away unto the city to buy meat.)

^9Then saith the woman of Samaria unto him, How is it that thou, being a Jew, askest drink of me, which am a woman of Samaria? for the Jews have no dealings with the Samaritans.

^10Jesus answered and said unto her, If thou knewest the gift of God, and who it is that saith to thee, Give me to drink; thou wouldest have asked of him, and he would have given thee living water.

^11The woman saith unto him, Sir, thou hast nothing to draw with, and the well is deep: from whence then hast thou that living water?

^12Art thou greater than our father Jacob, which gave us the well, and drank thereof himself, and his children, and his cattle?

^13Jesus answered and said unto her, Whosoever drinketh of this water shall thirst again:

^14But whosoever drinketh of the water that I shall give him shall never thirst; but the water that I shall give him shall be in him a well of water springing up into everlasting life.

^15The woman saith unto him, Sir, give me this water, that I thirst not, neither come hither to draw.

^16Jesus saith unto her, Go, call thy husband, and come hither.

^17The woman answered and said, I have no husband. Jesus said unto her, Thou hast well said, I have no husband:

^18For thou hast had five husbands; and he whom thou now hast is not thy husband: in that saidst thou truly.

^19The woman saith unto him, Sir, I perceive that thou art a prophet.

^20Our fathers worshipped in this mountain; and ye say, that in Jerusalem is the place where men ought to worship.

^21Jesus saith unto her, Woman, believe me, the hour cometh, when ye shall neither in this mountain, nor yet at Jerusalem, worship the Father.

^22Ye worship ye know not what: we know what we worship: for salvation is of the Jews.

^23But the hour cometh, and now is, when the true worshippers shall worship the Father in spirit and in truth: for the Father seeketh such to worship him.

^24God is a Spirit: and they that worship him must worship him in spirit and in truth.

^25The woman saith unto him, I know that Messias cometh, which is called Christ: when he is come, he will tell us all things.

^26Jesus saith unto her, I that speak unto thee am he.

^27And upon this came his disciples, and marvelled that he talked with the woman: yet no man said, What seekest thou? or, Why talkest thou with her?

^28The woman then left her waterpot, and went her way into the city, and saith to the men,

^29Come, see a man, which told me all things that ever I did: is not this the Christ?

^30Then they went out of the city, and came unto him.

^31In the mean while his disciples prayed him, saying, Master, eat.

^32But he said unto them, I have meat to eat that ye know not of.

^33Therefore said the disciples one to another, Hath any man brought him ought to eat?

^34Jesus saith unto them, My meat is to do the will of him that sent me, and to finish his work.

^35Say not ye, There are yet four months, and then cometh harvest? behold, I say unto you, Lift up your eyes, and look on the fields; for they are white already to harvest.

^36And he that reapeth receiveth wages, and gathereth fruit unto life eternal: that both he that soweth and he that reapeth may rejoice together.

^37And herein is that saying true, One soweth, and another reapeth.

^38I sent you to reap that whereon ye bestowed no labour: other men laboured, and ye are entered into their labours.

^39And many of the Samaritans of that city believed on him for the saying of the woman, which testified, He told me all that ever I did.

^40So when the Samaritans were come unto him, they besought him that he would tarry with them: and he abode there two days.

^41And many more believed because of his own word;

^42And said unto the woman, Now we believe, not because of thy saying: for we have heard him ourselves, and know that this is indeed the Christ, the Saviour of the world.

^43Now after two days he departed thence, and went into Galilee.

^44For Jesus himself testified, that a prophet hath no honour in his own country.

^45Then when he was come into Galilee, the Galilaeans received him, having seen all the things that he did at Jerusalem at the feast: for they also went unto the feast.

^46So Jesus came again into Cana of Galilee, where he made the water wine. And there was a certain nobleman, whose son was sick at Capernaum.

^47When he heard that Jesus was come out of Judaea into Galilee, he went unto him, and besought him that he would come down, and heal his son: for he was at the point of death.

^48Then said Jesus unto him, Except ye see signs and wonders, ye will not believe.

^49The nobleman saith unto him, Sir, come down ere my child die.

^50Jesus saith unto him, Go thy way; thy son liveth. And the man believed the word that Jesus had spoken unto him, and he went his way.

^51And as he was now going down, his servants met him, and told him, saying, Thy son liveth.

^52Then enquired he of them the hour when he began to amend. And they said unto him, Yesterday at the seventh hour the fever left him.

^53So the father knew that it was at the same hour, in the which Jesus said unto him, Thy son liveth: and himself believed, and his whole house.

^54This is again the second miracle that Jesus did, when he was come out of Judaea into Galilee.

V

5^1After this there was a feast of the Jews; and Jesus went up to Jerusalem.

^2Now there is at Jerusalem by the sheep market a pool, which is called in the Hebrew tongue Bethesda, having five porches.

^3In these lay a great multitude of impotent folk, of blind, halt, withered, waiting for the moving of the water.

^4For an angel went down at a certain season into the pool, and troubled the water: whosoever then first after the troubling of the water stepped in was made whole of whatsoever disease he had.

^5And a certain man was there, which had an infirmity thirty and eight years.

^6When Jesus saw him lie, and knew that he had been now a long time in that case, he saith unto him, Wilt thou be made whole?

^7The impotent man answered him, Sir, I have no man, when the water is troubled, to put me into the pool: but while I am coming, another steppeth down before me.

^8Jesus saith unto him, Rise, take up thy bed, and walk.

^9And immediately the man was made whole, and took up his bed, and walked: and on the same day was the sabbath.

^10The Jews therefore said unto him that was cured, It is the sabbath day: it is not lawful for thee to carry thy bed.

^11He answered them, He that made me whole, the same said unto me, Take up thy bed, and walk.

^12Then asked they him, What man is that which said unto thee, Take up thy bed, and walk?

^13And he that was healed wist not who it was: for Jesus had conveyed himself away, a multitude being in that place.

^14Afterward Jesus findeth him in the temple, and said unto him, Behold, thou art made whole: sin no more, lest a worse thing come unto thee.

^15The man departed, and told the Jews that it was Jesus, which had made him whole.

^16And therefore did the Jews persecute Jesus, and sought to slay him, because he had done these things on the sabbath day.

^17But Jesus answered them, My Father worketh hitherto, and I work.

^18Therefore the Jews sought the more to kill him, because he not only had broken the sabbath, but said also that God was his Father, making himself equal with God.

^19Then answered Jesus and said unto them, Verily, verily, I say unto you, The Son can do nothing of himself, but what he seeth the Father do: for what things soever he doeth, these also doeth the Son likewise.

^20For the Father loveth the Son, and sheweth him all things that himself doeth: and he will shew him greater works than these, that ye may marvel.

^21For as the Father raiseth up the dead, and quickeneth them; even so the Son quickeneth whom he will.

^22For the Father judgeth no man, but hath committed all judgment unto the Son:

^23That all men should honour the Son, even as they honour the Father. He that honoureth not the Son honoureth not the Father which hath sent him.

^24Verily, verily, I say unto you, He that heareth my word, and believeth on him that sent me, hath everlasting life, and shall not come into condemnation; but is passed from death unto life.

^25Verily, verily, I say unto you, The hour is coming, and now is, when the dead shall hear the voice of the Son of God: and they that hear shall live.

^26For as the Father hath life in himself; so hath he given to the Son to have life in himself;

^27And hath given him authority to execute judgment also, because he is the Son of man.

^28Marvel not at this: for the hour is coming, in the which all that are in the graves shall hear his voice,

^29And shall come forth; they that have done good, unto the resurrection of life; and they that have done evil, unto the resurrection of damnation.

^30I can of mine own self do nothing: as I hear, I judge: and my judgment is just; because I seek not mine own will, but the will of the Father which hath sent me.

^31If I bear witness of myself, my witness is not true.

^32There is another that beareth witness of me; and I know that the witness which he witnesseth of me is true.

^33Ye sent unto John, and he bare witness unto the truth.

^34But I receive not testimony from man: but these things I say, that ye might be saved.

^35He was a burning and a shining light: and ye were willing for a season to rejoice in his light.

^36But I have greater witness than that of John: for the works which the Father hath given me to finish, the same works that I do, bear witness of me, that the Father hath sent me.

^37And the Father himself, which hath sent me, hath borne witness of me. Ye have neither heard his voice at any time, nor seen his shape.

^38And ye have not his word abiding in you: for whom he hath sent, him ye believe not.

^39Search the scriptures; for in them ye think ye have eternal life: and they are they which testify of me.

^40And ye will not come to me, that ye might have life.

^41I receive not honour from men.

^42But I know you, that ye have not the love of God in you.

^43I am come in my Father’s name, and ye receive me not: if another shall come in his own name, him ye will receive.

^44How can ye believe, which receive honour one of another, and seek not the honour that cometh from God only?

^45Do not think that I will accuse you to the Father: there is one that accuseth you, even Moses, in whom ye trust.

^46For had ye believed Moses, ye would have believed me; for he wrote of me.

^47But if ye believe not his writings, how shall ye believe my words?

VI

6^1After these things Jesus went over the sea of Galilee, which is the sea of Tiberias.

^2And a great multitude followed him, because they saw his miracles which he did on them that were diseased.

^3And Jesus went up into a mountain, and there he sat with his disciples.

^4And the passover, a feast of the Jews, was nigh.

^5When Jesus then lifted up his eyes, and saw a great company come unto him, he saith unto Philip, Whence shall we buy bread, that these may eat?

^6And this he said to prove him: for he himself knew what he would do.

^7Philip answered him, Two hundred pennyworth of bread is not sufficient for them, that every one of them may take a little.

^8One of his disciples, Andrew, Simon Peter’s brother, saith unto him,

^9There is a lad here, which hath five barley loaves, and two small fishes: but what are they among so many?

^10And Jesus said, Make the men sit down. Now there was much grass in the place. So the men sat down, in number about five thousand.

^11And Jesus took the loaves; and when he had given thanks, he distributed to the disciples, and the disciples to them that were set down; and likewise of the fishes as much as they would.

^12When they were filled, he said unto his disciples, Gather up the fragments that remain, that nothing be lost.

^13Therefore they gathered them together, and filled twelve baskets with the fragments of the five barley loaves, which remained over and above unto them that had eaten.

^14Then those men, when they had seen the miracle that Jesus did, said, This is of a truth that prophet that should come into the world.

^15When Jesus therefore perceived that they would come and take him by force, to make him a king, he departed again into a mountain himself alone.

^16And when even was now come, his disciples went down unto the sea,

^17And entered into a ship, and went over the sea toward Capernaum. And it was now dark, and Jesus was not come to them.

^18And the sea arose by reason of a great wind that blew.

^19So when they had rowed about five and twenty or thirty furlongs, they see Jesus walking on the sea, and drawing nigh unto the ship: and they were afraid.

^20But he saith unto them, It is I; be not afraid.

^21Then they willingly received him into the ship: and immediately the ship was at the land whither they went.

^22The day following, when the people which stood on the other side of the sea saw that there was none other boat there, save that one whereinto his disciples were entered, and that Jesus went not with his disciples into the boat, but that his disciples were gone away alone;

^23(Howbeit there came other boats from Tiberias nigh unto the place where they did eat bread, after that the Lord had given thanks:)

^24When the people therefore saw that Jesus was not there, neither his disciples, they also took shipping, and came to Capernaum, seeking for Jesus.

^25And when they had found him on the other side of the sea, they said unto him, Rabbi, when camest thou hither?

^26Jesus answered them and said, Verily, verily, I say unto you, Ye seek me, not because ye saw the miracles, but because ye did eat of the loaves, and were filled.

^27Labour not for the meat which perisheth, but for that meat which endureth unto everlasting life, which the Son of man shall give unto you: for him hath God the Father sealed.

^28Then said they unto him, What shall we do, that we might work the works of God?

^29Jesus answered and said unto them, This is the work of God, that ye believe on him whom he hath sent.

^30They said therefore unto him, What sign shewest thou then, that we may see, and believe thee? what dost thou work?

^31Our fathers did eat manna in the desert; as it is written, He gave them bread from heaven to eat.

^32Then Jesus said unto them, Verily, verily, I say unto you, Moses gave you not that bread from heaven; but my Father giveth you the true bread from heaven.

^33For the bread of God is he which cometh down from heaven, and giveth life unto the world.

^34Then said they unto him, Lord, evermore give us this bread.

^35And Jesus said unto them, I am the bread of life: he that cometh to me shall never hunger; and he that believeth on me shall never thirst.

^36But I said unto you, That ye also have seen me, and believe not.

^37All that the Father giveth me shall come to me; and him that cometh to me I will in no wise cast out.

^38For I came down from heaven, not to do mine own will, but the will of him that sent me.

^39And this is the Father’s will which hath sent me, that of all which he hath given me I should lose nothing, but should raise it up again at the last day.

^40And this is the will of him that sent me, that every one which seeth the Son, and believeth on him, may have everlasting life: and I will raise him up at the last day.

^41The Jews then murmured at him, because he said, I am the bread which came down from heaven.

^42And they said, Is not this Jesus, the son of Joseph, whose father and mother we know? how is it then that he saith, I came down from heaven?

^43Jesus therefore answered and said unto them, Murmur not among yourselves.

^44No man can come to me, except the Father which hath sent me draw him: and I will raise him up at the last day.

^45It is written in the prophets, And they shall be all taught of God. Every man therefore that hath heard, and hath learned of the Father, cometh unto me.

^46Not that any man hath seen the Father, save he which is of God, he hath seen the Father.

^47Verily, verily, I say unto you, He that believeth on me hath everlasting life.

^48I am that bread of life.

^49Your fathers did eat manna in the wilderness, and are dead.

^50This is the bread which cometh down from heaven, that a man may eat thereof, and not die.

^51I am the living bread which came down from heaven: if any man eat of this bread, he shall live for ever: and the bread that I will give is my flesh, which I will give for the life of the world.

^52The Jews therefore strove among themselves, saying, How can this man give us his flesh to eat?

^53Then Jesus said unto them, Verily, verily, I say unto you, Except ye eat the flesh of the Son of man, and drink his blood, ye have no life in you.

^54Whoso eateth my flesh, and drinketh my blood, hath eternal life; and I will raise him up at the last day.

^55For my flesh is meat indeed, and my blood is drink indeed.

^56He that eateth my flesh, and drinketh my blood, dwelleth in me, and I in him.

^57As the living Father hath sent me, and I live by the Father: so he that eateth me, even he shall live by me.

^58This is that bread which came down from heaven: not as your fathers did eat manna, and are dead: he that eateth of this bread shall live for ever.

^59These things said he in the synagogue, as he taught in Capernaum.

^60Many therefore of his disciples, when they had heard this, said, This is an hard saying; who can hear it?

^61When Jesus knew in himself that his disciples murmured at it, he said unto them, Doth this offend you?

^62What and if ye shall see the Son of man ascend up where he was before?

^63It is the spirit that quickeneth; the flesh profiteth nothing: the words that I speak unto you, they are spirit, and they are life.

^64But there are some of you that believe not. For Jesus knew from the beginning who they were that believed not, and who should betray him.

^65And he said, Therefore said I unto you, that no man can come unto me, except it were given unto him of my Father.

^66From that time many of his disciples went back, and walked no more with him.

^67Then said Jesus unto the twelve, Will ye also go away?

^68Then Simon Peter answered him, Lord, to whom shall we go? thou hast the words of eternal life.

^69And we believe and are sure that thou art that Christ, the Son of the living God.

^70Jesus answered them, Have not I chosen you twelve, and one of you is a devil?

^71He spake of Judas Iscariot the son of Simon: for he it was that should betray him, being one of the twelve.

VII

7^1After these things Jesus walked in Galilee: for he would not walk in Jewry, because the Jews sought to kill him.

^2Now the Jew’s feast of tabernacles was at hand.

^3His brethren therefore said unto him, Depart hence, and go into Judaea, that thy disciples also may see the works that thou doest.

^4For there is no man that doeth any thing in secret, and he himself seeketh to be known openly. If thou do these things, shew thyself to the world.

^5For neither did his brethren believe in him.

^6Then Jesus said unto them, My time is not yet come: but your time is alway ready.

^7The world cannot hate you; but me it hateth, because I testify of it, that the works thereof are evil.

^8Go ye up unto this feast: I go not up yet unto this feast: for my time is not yet full come.

^9When he had said these words unto them, he abode still in Galilee.

^10But when his brethren were gone up, then went he also up unto the feast, not openly, but as it were in secret.

^11Then the Jews sought him at the feast, and said, Where is he?

^12And there was much murmuring among the people concerning him: for some said, He is a good man: others said, Nay; but he deceiveth the people.

^13Howbeit no man spake openly of him for fear of the Jews.

^14Now about the midst of the feast Jesus went up into the temple, and taught.

^15And the Jews marvelled, saying, How knoweth this man letters, having never learned?

^16Jesus answered them, and said, My doctrine is not mine, but his that sent me.

^17If any man will do his will, he shall know of the doctrine, whether it be of God, or whether I speak of myself.

^18He that speaketh of himself seeketh his own glory: but he that seeketh his glory that sent him, the same is true, and no unrighteousness is in him.

^19Did not Moses give you the law, and yet none of you keepeth the law? Why go ye about to kill me?

^20The people answered and said, Thou hast a devil: who goeth about to kill thee?

^21Jesus answered and said unto them, I have done one work, and ye all marvel.

^22Moses therefore gave unto you circumcision; (not because it is of Moses, but of the fathers;) and ye on the sabbath day circumcise a man.

^23If a man on the sabbath day receive circumcision, that the law of Moses should not be broken; are ye angry at me, because I have made a man every whit whole on the sabbath day?

^24Judge not according to the appearance, but judge righteous judgment.

^25Then said some of them of Jerusalem, Is not this he, whom they seek to kill?

^26But, lo, he speaketh boldly, and they say nothing unto him. Do the rulers know indeed that this is the very Christ?

^27Howbeit we know this man whence he is: but when Christ cometh, no man knoweth whence he is.

^28Then cried Jesus in the temple as he taught, saying, Ye both know me, and ye know whence I am: and I am not come of myself, but he that sent me is true, whom ye know not.

^29But I know him: for I am from him, and he hath sent me.

^30Then they sought to take him: but no man laid hands on him, because his hour was not yet come.

^31And many of the people believed on him, and said, When Christ cometh, will he do more miracles than these which this man hath done?

^32The Pharisees heard that the people murmured such things concerning him; and the Pharisees and the chief priests sent officers to take him.

^33Then said Jesus unto them, Yet a little while am I with you, and then I go unto him that sent me.

^34Ye shall seek me, and shall not find me: and where I am, thither ye cannot come.

^35Then said the Jews among themselves, Whither will he go, that we shall not find him? will he go unto the dispersed among the Gentiles, and teach the Gentiles?

^36What manner of saying is this that he said, Ye shall seek me, and shall not find me: and where I am, thither ye cannot come?

^37In the last day, that great day of the feast, Jesus stood and cried, saying, If any man thirst, let him come unto me, and drink.

^38He that believeth on me, as the scripture hath said, out of his belly shall flow rivers of living water.

^39(But this spake he of the Spirit, which they that believe on him should receive: for the Holy Ghost was not yet given; because that Jesus was not yet glorified.)

^40Many of the people therefore, when they heard this saying, said, Of a truth this is the Prophet.

^41Others said, This is the Christ. But some said, Shall Christ come out of Galilee?

^42Hath not the scripture said, That Christ cometh of the seed of David, and out of the town of Bethlehem, where David was?

^43So there was a division among the people because of him.

^44And some of them would have taken him; but no man laid hands on him.

^45Then came the officers to the chief priests and Pharisees; and they said unto them, Why have ye not brought him?

^46The officers answered, Never man spake like this man.

^47Then answered them the Pharisees, Are ye also deceived?

^48Have any of the rulers or of the Pharisees believed on him?

^49But this people who knoweth not the law are cursed.

^50Nicodemus saith unto them, (he that came to Jesus by night, being one of them,)

^51Doth our law judge any man, before it hear him, and know what he doeth?

^52They answered and said unto him, Art thou also of Galilee? Search, and look: for out of Galilee ariseth no prophet.

^53And every man went unto his own house.

VIII

8^1Jesus went unto the mount of Olives.

^2And early in the morning he came again into the temple, and all the people came unto him; and he sat down, and taught them.

^3And the scribes and Pharisees brought unto him a woman taken in adultery; and when they had set her in the midst,

^4They say unto him, Master, this woman was taken in adultery, in the very act.

^5Now Moses in the law commanded us, that such should be stoned: but what sayest thou?

^6This they said, tempting him, that they might have to accuse him. But Jesus stooped down, and with his finger wrote on the ground, as though he heard them not.

^7So when they continued asking him, he lifted up himself, and said unto them, He that is without sin among you, let him first cast a stone at her.

^8And again he stooped down, and wrote on the ground.

^9And they which heard it, being convicted by their own conscience, went out one by one, beginning at the eldest, even unto the last: and Jesus was left alone, and the woman standing in the midst.

^10When Jesus had lifted up himself, and saw none but the woman, he said unto her, Woman, where are those thine accusers? hath no man condemned thee?

^11She said, No man, Lord. And Jesus said unto her, Neither do I condemn thee: go, and sin no more.

^12Then spake Jesus again unto them, saying, I am the light of the world: he that followeth me shall not walk in darkness, but shall have the light of life.

^13The Pharisees therefore said unto him, Thou bearest record of thyself; thy record is not true.

^14Jesus answered and said unto them, Though I bear record of myself, yet my record is true: for I know whence I came, and whither I go; but ye cannot tell whence I come, and whither I go.

^15Ye judge after the flesh; I judge no man.

^16And yet if I judge, my judgment is true: for I am not alone, but I and the Father that sent me.

^17It is also written in your law, that the testimony of two men is true.

^18I am one that bear witness of myself, and the Father that sent me beareth witness of me.

^19Then said they unto him, Where is thy Father? Jesus answered, Ye neither know me, nor my Father: if ye had known me, ye should have known my Father also.

^20These words spake Jesus in the treasury, as he taught in the temple: and no man laid hands on him; for his hour was not yet come.

^21Then said Jesus again unto them, I go my way, and ye shall seek me, and shall die in your sins: whither I go, ye cannot come.

^22Then said the Jews, Will he kill himself? because he saith, Whither I go, ye cannot come.

^23And he said unto them, Ye are from beneath; I am from above: ye are of this world; I am not of this world.

^24I said therefore unto you, that ye shall die in your sins: for if ye believe not that I am he, ye shall die in your sins.

^25Then said they unto him, Who art thou? And Jesus saith unto them, Even the same that I said unto you from the beginning.

^26I have many things to say and to judge of you: but he that sent me is true; and I speak to the world those things which I have heard of him.

^27They understood not that he spake to them of the Father.

^28Then said Jesus unto them, When ye have lifted up the Son of man, then shall ye know that I am he, and that I do nothing of myself; but as my Father hath taught me, I speak these things.

^29And he that sent me is with me: the Father hath not left me alone; for I do always those things that please him.

^30As he spake these words, many believed on him.

^31Then said Jesus to those Jews which believed on him, If ye continue in my word, then are ye my disciples indeed;

^32And ye shall know the truth, and the truth shall make you free.

^33They answered him, We be Abraham’s seed, and were never in bondage to any man: how sayest thou, Ye shall be made free?

^34Jesus answered them, Verily, verily, I say unto you, Whosoever committeth sin is the servant of sin.

^35And the servant abideth not in the house for ever: but the Son abideth ever.

^36If the Son therefore shall make you free, ye shall be free indeed.

^37I know that ye are Abraham’s seed; but ye seek to kill me, because my word hath no place in you.

^38I speak that which I have seen with my Father: and ye do that which ye have seen with your father.

^39They answered and said unto him, Abraham is our father. Jesus saith unto them, If ye were Abraham’s children, ye would do the works of Abraham.

^40But now ye seek to kill me, a man that hath told you the truth, which I have heard of God: this did not Abraham.

^41Ye do the deeds of your father. Then said they to him, We be not born of fornication; we have one Father, even God.

^42Jesus said unto them, If God were your Father, ye would love me: for I proceeded forth and came from God; neither came I of myself, but he sent me.

^43Why do ye not understand my speech? even because ye cannot hear my word.

^44Ye are of your father the devil, and the lusts of your father ye will do. He was a murderer from the beginning, and abode not in the truth, because there is no truth in him. When he speaketh a lie, he speaketh of his own: for he is a liar, and the father of it.

^45And because I tell you the truth, ye believe me not.

^46Which of you convinceth me of sin? And if I say the truth, why do ye not believe me?

^47He that is of God heareth God’s words: ye therefore hear them not, because ye are not of God.

^48Then answered the Jews, and said unto him, Say we not well that thou art a Samaritan, and hast a devil?

^49Jesus answered, I have not a devil; but I honour my Father, and ye do dishonour me.

^50And I seek not mine own glory: there is one that seeketh and judgeth.

^51Verily, verily, I say unto you, If a man keep my saying, he shall never see death.

^52Then said the Jews unto him, Now we know that thou hast a devil. Abraham is dead, and the prophets; and thou sayest, If a man keep my saying, he shall never taste of death.

^53Art thou greater than our father Abraham, which is dead? and the prophets are dead: whom makest thou thyself?

^54Jesus answered, If I honour myself, my honour is nothing: it is my Father that honoureth me; of whom ye say, that he is your God:

^55Yet ye have not known him; but I know him: and if I should say, I know him not, I shall be a liar like unto you: but I know him, and keep his saying.

^56Your father Abraham rejoiced to see my day: and he saw it, and was glad.

^57Then said the Jews unto him, Thou art not yet fifty years old, and hast thou seen Abraham?

^58Jesus said unto them, Verily, verily, I say unto you, Before Abraham was, I am.

^59Then took they up stones to cast at him: but Jesus hid himself, and went out of the temple, going through the midst of them, and so passed by.

IX

9^1And as Jesus passed by, he saw a man which was blind from his birth.

^2And his disciples asked him, saying, Master, who did sin, this man, or his parents, that he was born blind?

^3Jesus answered, Neither hath this man sinned, nor his parents: but that the works of God should be made manifest in him.

^4I must work the works of him that sent me, while it is day: the night cometh, when no man can work.

^5As long as I am in the world, I am the light of the world.

^6When he had thus spoken, he spat on the ground, and made clay of the spittle, and he anointed the eyes of the blind man with the clay,

^7And said unto him, Go, wash in the pool of Siloam, (which is by interpretation, Sent.) He went his way therefore, and washed, and came seeing.

^8The neighbours therefore, and they which before had seen him that he was blind, said, Is not this he that sat and begged?

^9Some said, This is he: others said, He is like him: but he said, I am he.

^10Therefore said they unto him, How were thine eyes opened?

^11He answered and said, A man that is called Jesus made clay, and anointed mine eyes, and said unto me, Go to the pool of Siloam, and wash: and I went and washed, and I received sight.

^12Then said they unto him, Where is he? He said, I know not.

^13They brought to the Pharisees him that aforetime was blind.

^14And it was the sabbath day when Jesus made the clay, and opened his eyes.

^15Then again the Pharisees also asked him how he had received his sight. He said unto them, He put clay upon mine eyes, and I washed, and do see.

^16Therefore said some of the Pharisees, This man is not of God, because he keepeth not the sabbath day. Others said, How can a man that is a sinner do such miracles? And there was a division among them.

^17They say unto the blind man again, What sayest thou of him, that he hath opened thine eyes? He said, He is a prophet.

^18But the Jews did not believe concerning him, that he had been blind, and received his sight, until they called the parents of him that had received his sight.

^19And they asked them, saying, Is this your son, who ye say was born blind? how then doth he now see?

^20His parents answered them and said, We know that this is our son, and that he was born blind:

^21But by what means he now seeth, we know not; or who hath opened his eyes, we know not: he is of age; ask him: he shall speak for himself.

^22These words spake his parents, because they feared the Jews: for the Jews had agreed already, that if any man did confess that he was Christ, he should be put out of the synagogue.

^23Therefore said his parents, He is of age; ask him.

^24Then again called they the man that was blind, and said unto him, Give God the praise: we know that this man is a sinner.

^25He answered and said, Whether he be a sinner or no, I know not: one thing I know, that, whereas I was blind, now I see.

^26Then said they to him again, What did he to thee? how opened he thine eyes?

^27He answered them, I have told you already, and ye did not hear: wherefore would ye hear it again? will ye also be his disciples?

^28Then they reviled him, and said, Thou art his disciple; but we are Moses’ disciples.

^29We know that God spake unto Moses: as for this fellow, we know not from whence he is.

^30The man answered and said unto them, Why herein is a marvellous thing, that ye know not from whence he is, and yet he hath opened mine eyes.

^31Now we know that God heareth not sinners: but if any man be a worshipper of God, and doeth his will, him he heareth.

^32Since the world began was it not heard that any man opened the eyes of one that was born blind.

^33If this man were not of God, he could do nothing.

^34They answered and said unto him, Thou wast altogether born in sins, and dost thou teach us? And they cast him out.

^35Jesus heard that they had cast him out; and when he had found him, he said unto him, Dost thou believe on the Son of God?

^36He answered and said, Who is he, Lord, that I might believe on him?

^37And Jesus said unto him, Thou hast both seen him, and it is he that talketh with thee.

^38And he said, Lord, I believe. And he worshipped him.

^39And Jesus said, For judgment I am come into this world, that they which see not might see; and that they which see might be made blind.

^40And some of the Pharisees which were with him heard these words, and said unto him, Are we blind also?

^41Jesus said unto them, If ye were blind, ye should have no sin: but now ye say, We see; therefore your sin remaineth.

X

10^1Verily, verily, I say unto you, He that entereth not by the door into the sheepfold, but climbeth up some other way, the same is a thief and a robber.

^2But he that entereth in by the door is the shepherd of the sheep.

^3To him the porter openeth; and the sheep hear his voice: and he calleth his own sheep by name, and leadeth them out.

^4And when he putteth forth his own sheep, he goeth before them, and the sheep follow him: for they know his voice.

^5And a stranger will they not follow, but will flee from him: for they know not the voice of strangers.

^6This parable spake Jesus unto them: but they understood not what things they were which he spake unto them.

^7Then said Jesus unto them again, Verily, verily, I say unto you, I am the door of the sheep.

^8All that ever came before me are thieves and robbers: but the sheep did not hear them.

^9I am the door: by me if any man enter in, he shall be saved, and shall go in and out, and find pasture.

^10The thief cometh not, but for to steal, and to kill, and to destroy: I am come that they might have life, and that they might have it more abundantly.

^11I am the good shepherd: the good shepherd giveth his life for the sheep.

^12But he that is an hireling, and not the shepherd, whose own the sheep are not, seeth the wolf coming, and leaveth the sheep, and fleeth: and the wolf catcheth them, and scattereth the sheep.

^13The hireling fleeth, because he is an hireling, and careth not for the sheep.

^14I am the good shepherd, and know my sheep, and am known of mine.

^15As the Father knoweth me, even so know I the Father: and I lay down my life for the sheep.

^16And other sheep I have, which are not of this fold: them also I must bring, and they shall hear my voice; and there shall be one fold, and one shepherd.

^17Therefore doth my Father love me, because I lay down my life, that I might take it again.

^18No man taketh it from me, but I lay it down of myself. I have power to lay it down, and I have power to take it again. This commandment have I received of my Father.

^19There was a division therefore again among the Jews for these sayings.

^20And many of them said, He hath a devil, and is mad; why hear ye him?

^21Others said, These are not the words of him that hath a devil. Can a devil open the eyes of the blind?

^22And it was at Jerusalem the feast of the dedication, and it was winter.

^23And Jesus walked in the temple in Solomon’s porch.

^24Then came the Jews round about him, and said unto him, How long dost thou make us to doubt? If thou be the Christ, tell us plainly.

^25Jesus answered them, I told you, and ye believed not: the works that I do in my Father’s name, they bear witness of me.

^26But ye believe not, because ye are not of my sheep, as I said unto you.

^27My sheep hear my voice, and I know them, and they follow me:

^28And I give unto them eternal life; and they shall never perish, neither shall any man pluck them out of my hand.

^29My Father, which gave them me, is greater than all; and no man is able to pluck them out of my Father’s hand.

^30I and my Father are one.

^31Then the Jews took up stones again to stone him.

^32Jesus answered them, Many good works have I shewed you from my Father; for which of those works do ye stone me?

^33The Jews answered him, saying, For a good work we stone thee not; but for blasphemy; and because that thou, being a man, makest thyself God.

^34Jesus answered them, Is it not written in your law, I said, Ye are gods?

^35If he called them gods, unto whom the word of God came, and the scripture cannot be broken;

^36Say ye of him, whom the Father hath sanctified, and sent into the world, Thou blasphemest; because I said, I am the Son of God?

^37If I do not the works of my Father, believe me not.

^38But if I do, though ye believe not me, believe the works: that ye may know, and believe, that the Father is in me, and I in him.

^39Therefore they sought again to take him: but he escaped out of their hand,

^40And went away again beyond Jordan into the place where John at first baptized; and there he abode.

^41And many resorted unto him, and said, John did no miracle: but all things that John spake of this man were true.

^42And many believed on him there.

XI

11^1Now a certain man was sick, named Lazarus, of Bethany, the town of Mary and her sister Martha.

^2(It was that Mary which anointed the Lord with ointment, and wiped his feet with her hair, whose brother Lazarus was sick.)

^3Therefore his sisters sent unto him, saying, Lord, behold, he whom thou lovest is sick.

^4When Jesus heard that, he said, This sickness is not unto death, but for the glory of God, that the Son of God might be glorified thereby.

^5Now Jesus loved Martha, and her sister, and Lazarus.

^6When he had heard therefore that he was sick, he abode two days still in the same place where he was.

^7Then after that saith he to his disciples, Let us go into Judaea again.

^8His disciples say unto him, Master, the Jews of late sought to stone thee; and goest thou thither again?

^9Jesus answered, Are there not twelve hours in the day? If any man walk in the day, he stumbleth not, because he seeth the light of this world.

^10But if a man walk in the night, he stumbleth, because there is no light in him.

^11These things said he: and after that he saith unto them, Our friend Lazarus sleepeth; but I go, that I may awake him out of sleep.

^12Then said his disciples, Lord, if he sleep, he shall do well.

^13Howbeit Jesus spake of his death: but they thought that he had spoken of taking of rest in sleep.

^14Then said Jesus unto them plainly, Lazarus is dead.

^15And I am glad for your sakes that I was not there, to the intent ye may believe; nevertheless let us go unto him.

^16Then said Thomas, which is called Didymus, unto his fellowdisciples, Let us also go, that we may die with him.

^17Then when Jesus came, he found that he had lain in the grave four days already.

^18Now Bethany was nigh unto Jerusalem, about fifteen furlongs off:

^19And many of the Jews came to Martha and Mary, to comfort them concerning their brother.

^20Then Martha, as soon as she heard that Jesus was coming, went and met him: but Mary sat still in the house.

^21Then said Martha unto Jesus, Lord, if thou hadst been here, my brother had not died.

^22But I know, that even now, whatsoever thou wilt ask of God, God will give it thee.

^23Jesus saith unto her, Thy brother shall rise again.

^24Martha saith unto him, I know that he shall rise again in the resurrection at the last day.

^25Jesus said unto her, I am the resurrection, and the life: he that believeth in me, though he were dead, yet shall he live:

^26And whosoever liveth and believeth in me shall never die. Believest thou this?

^27She saith unto him, Yea, Lord: I believe that thou art the Christ, the Son of God, which should come into the world.

^28And when she had so said, she went her way, and called Mary her sister secretly, saying, The Master is come, and calleth for thee.

^29As soon as she heard that, she arose quickly, and came unto him.

^30Now Jesus was not yet come into the town, but was in that place where Martha met him.

^31The Jews then which were with her in the house, and comforted her, when they saw Mary, that she rose up hastily and went out, followed her, saying, She goeth unto the grave to weep there.

^32Then when Mary was come where Jesus was, and saw him, she fell down at his feet, saying unto him, Lord, if thou hadst been here, my brother had not died.

^33When Jesus therefore saw her weeping, and the Jews also weeping which came with her, he groaned in the spirit, and was troubled.

^34And said, Where have ye laid him? They said unto him, Lord, come and see.

^35Jesus wept.

^36Then said the Jews, Behold how he loved him!

^37And some of them said, Could not this man, which opened the eyes of the blind, have caused that even this man should not have died?

^38Jesus therefore again groaning in himself cometh to the grave. It was a cave, and a stone lay upon it.

^39Jesus said, Take ye away the stone. Martha, the sister of him that was dead, saith unto him, Lord, by this time he stinketh: for he hath been dead four days.

^40Jesus saith unto her, Said I not unto thee, that, if thou wouldest believe, thou shouldest see the glory of God?

^41Then they took away the stone from the place where the dead was laid. And Jesus lifted up his eyes, and said, Father, I thank thee that thou hast heard me.

^42And I knew that thou hearest me always: but because of the people which stand by I said it, that they may believe that thou hast sent me.

^43And when he thus had spoken, he cried with a loud voice, Lazarus, come forth.

^44And he that was dead came forth, bound hand and foot with graveclothes: and his face was bound about with a napkin. Jesus saith unto them, Loose him, and let him go.

^45Then many of the Jews which came to Mary, and had seen the things which Jesus did, believed on him.

^46But some of them went their ways to the Pharisees, and told them what things Jesus had done.

^47Then gathered the chief priests and the Pharisees a council, and said, What do we? for this man doeth many miracles.

^48If we let him thus alone, all men will believe on him: and the Romans shall come and take away both our place and nation.

^49And one of them, named Caiaphas, being the high priest that same year, said unto them, Ye know nothing at all,

^50Nor consider that it is expedient for us, that one man should die for the people, and that the whole nation perish not.

^51And this spake he not of himself: but being high priest that year, he prophesied that Jesus should die for that nation;

^52And not for that nation only, but that also he should gather together in one the children of God that were scattered abroad.

^53Then from that day forth they took counsel together for to put him to death.

^54Jesus therefore walked no more openly among the Jews; but went thence unto a country near to the wilderness, into a city called Ephraim, and there continued with his disciples.

^55And the Jews’ passover was nigh at hand: and many went out of the country up to Jerusalem before the passover, to purify themselves.

^56Then sought they for Jesus, and spake among themselves, as they stood in the temple, What think ye, that he will not come to the feast?

^57Now both the chief priests and the Pharisees had given a commandment, that, if any man knew where he were, he should shew it, that they might take him.

XII

12^1Then Jesus six days before the passover came to Bethany, where Lazarus was, which had been dead, whom he raised from the dead.

^2There they made him a supper; and Martha served: but Lazarus was one of them that sat at the table with him.

^3Then took Mary a pound of ointment of spikenard, very costly, and anointed the feet of Jesus, and wiped his feet with her hair: and the house was filled with the odour of the ointment.

^4Then saith one of his disciples, Judas Iscariot, Simon’s son, which should betray him,

^5Why was not this ointment sold for three hundred pence, and given to the poor?

^6This he said, not that he cared for the poor; but because he was a thief, and had the bag, and bare what was put therein.

^7Then said Jesus, Let her alone: against the day of my burying hath she kept this.

^8For the poor always ye have with you; but me ye have not always.

^9Much people of the Jews therefore knew that he was there: and they came not for Jesus’ sake only, but that they might see Lazarus also, whom he had raised from the dead.

^10But the chief priests consulted that they might put Lazarus also to death;

^11Because that by reason of him many of the Jews went away, and believed on Jesus.

^12On the next day much people that were come to the feast, when they heard that Jesus was coming to Jerusalem,

^13Took branches of palm trees, and went forth to meet him, and cried, Hosanna: Blessed is the King of Israel that cometh in the name of the Lord.

^14And Jesus, when he had found a young ass, sat thereon; as it is written,

^15Fear not, daughter of Sion: behold, thy King cometh, sitting on an ass’s colt.

^16These things understood not his disciples at the first: but when Jesus was glorified, then remembered they that these things were written of him, and that they had done these things unto him.

^17The people therefore that was with him when he called Lazarus out of his grave, and raised him from the dead, bare record.

^18For this cause the people also met him, for that they heard that he had done this miracle.

^19The Pharisees therefore said among themselves, Perceive ye how ye prevail nothing? behold, the world is gone after him.

^20And there were certain Greeks among them that came up to worship at the feast:

^21The same came therefore to Philip, which was of Bethsaida of Galilee, and desired him, saying, Sir, we would see Jesus.

^22Philip cometh and telleth Andrew: and again Andrew and Philip tell Jesus.

^23And Jesus answered them, saying, The hour is come, that the Son of man should be glorified.

^24Verily, verily, I say unto you, Except a corn of wheat fall into the ground and die, it abideth alone: but if it die, it bringeth forth much fruit.

^25He that loveth his life shall lose it; and he that hateth his life in this world shall keep it unto life eternal.

^26If any man serve me, let him follow me; and where I am, there shall also my servant be: if any man serve me, him will my Father honour.

^27Now is my soul troubled; and what shall I say? Father, save me from this hour: but for this cause came I unto this hour.

^28Father, glorify thy name. Then came there a voice from heaven, saying, I have both glorified it, and will glorify it again.

^29The people therefore, that stood by, and heard it, said that it thundered: others said, An angel spake to him.

^30Jesus answered and said, This voice came not because of me, but for your sakes.

^31Now is the judgment of this world: now shall the prince of this world be cast out.

^32And I, if I be lifted up from the earth, will draw all men unto me.

^33This he said, signifying what death he should die.

^34The people answered him, We have heard out of the law that Christ abideth for ever: and how sayest thou, The Son of man must be lifted up? who is this Son of man?

^35Then Jesus said unto them, Yet a little while is the light with you. Walk while ye have the light, lest darkness come upon you: for he that walketh in darkness knoweth not whither he goeth.

^36While ye have light, believe in the light, that ye may be the children of light. These things spake Jesus, and departed, and did hide himself from them.

^37But though he had done so many miracles before them, yet they believed not on him:

^38That the saying of Esaias the prophet might be fulfilled, which he spake, Lord, who hath believed our report? and to whom hath the arm of the Lord been revealed?

^39Therefore they could not believe, because that Esaias said again,

^40He hath blinded their eyes, and hardened their heart; that they should not see with their eyes, nor understand with their heart, and be converted, and I should heal them.

^41These things said Esaias, when he saw his glory, and spake of him.

^42Nevertheless among the chief rulers also many believed on him; but because of the Pharisees they did not confess him, lest they should be put out of the synagogue:

^43For they loved the praise of men more than the praise of God.

^44Jesus cried and said, He that believeth on me, believeth not on me, but on him that sent me.

^45And he that seeth me seeth him that sent me.

^46I am come a light into the world, that whosoever believeth on me should not abide in darkness.

^47And if any man hear my words, and believe not, I judge him not: for I came not to judge the world, but to save the world.

^48He that rejecteth me, and receiveth not my words, hath one that judgeth him: the word that I have spoken, the same shall judge him in the last day.

^49For I have not spoken of myself; but the Father which sent me, he gave me a commandment, what I should say, and what I should speak.

^50And I know that his commandment is life everlasting: whatsoever I speak therefore, even as the Father said unto me, so I speak.

XIII

13^1Now before the feast of the passover, when Jesus knew that his hour was come that he should depart out of this world unto the Father, having loved his own which were in the world, he loved them unto the end.

^2And supper being ended, the devil having now put into the heart of Judas Iscariot, Simon’s son, to betray him;

^3Jesus knowing that the Father had given all things into his hands, and that he was come from God, and went to God;

^4He riseth from supper, and laid aside his garments; and took a towel, and girded himself.

^5After that he poureth water into a bason, and began to wash the disciples’ feet, and to wipe them with the towel wherewith he was girded.

^6Then cometh he to Simon Peter: and Peter saith unto him, Lord, dost thou wash my feet?

^7Jesus answered and said unto him, What I do thou knowest not now; but thou shalt know hereafter.

^8Peter saith unto him, Thou shalt never wash my feet. Jesus answered him, If I wash thee not, thou hast no part with me.

^9Simon Peter saith unto him, Lord, not my feet only, but also my hands and my head.

^10Jesus saith to him, He that is washed needeth not save to wash his feet, but is clean every whit: and ye are clean, but not all.

^11For he knew who should betray him; therefore said he, Ye are not all clean.

^12So after he had washed their feet, and had taken his garments, and was set down again, he said unto them, Know ye what I have done to you?

^13Ye call me Master and Lord: and ye say well; for so I am.

^14If I then, your Lord and Master, have washed your feet; ye also ought to wash one another’s feet.

^15For I have given you an example, that ye should do as I have done to you.

^16Verily, verily, I say unto you, The servant is not greater than his lord; neither he that is sent greater than he that sent him.

^17If ye know these things, happy are ye if ye do them.

^18I speak not of you all: I know whom I have chosen: but that the scripture may be fulfilled, He that eateth bread with me hath lifted up his heel against me.

^19Now I tell you before it come, that, when it is come to pass, ye may believe that I am he.

^20Verily, verily, I say unto you, He that receiveth whomsoever I send receiveth me; and he that receiveth me receiveth him that sent me.

^21When Jesus had thus said, he was troubled in spirit, and testified, and said, Verily, verily, I say unto you, that one of you shall betray me.

^22Then the disciples looked one on another, doubting of whom he spake.

^23Now there was leaning on Jesus’ bosom one of his disciples, whom Jesus loved.

^24Simon Peter therefore beckoned to him, that he should ask who it should be of whom he spake.

^25He then lying on Jesus’ breast saith unto him, Lord, who is it?

^26Jesus answered, He it is, to whom I shall give a sop, when I have dipped it. And when he had dipped the sop, he gave it to Judas Iscariot, the son of Simon.

^27And after the sop Satan entered into him. Then said Jesus unto him, That thou doest, do quickly.

^28Now no man at the table knew for what intent he spake this unto him.

^29For some of them thought, because Judas had the bag, that Jesus had said unto him, Buy those things that we have need of against the feast; or, that he should give something to the poor.

^30He then having received the sop went immediately out: and it was night.

^31Therefore, when he was gone out, Jesus said, Now is the Son of man glorified, and God is glorified in him.

^32If God be glorified in him, God shall also glorify him in himself, and shall straightway glorify him.

^33Little children, yet a little while I am with you. Ye shall seek me: and as I said unto the Jews, Whither I go, ye cannot come; so now I say to you.

^34A new commandment I give unto you, That ye love one another; as I have loved you, that ye also love one another.

^35By this shall all men know that ye are my disciples, if ye have love one to another.

^36Simon Peter said unto him, Lord, whither goest thou? Jesus answered him, Whither I go, thou canst not follow me now; but thou shalt follow me afterwards.

^37Peter said unto him, Lord, why cannot I follow thee now? I will lay down my life for thy sake.

^38Jesus answered him, Wilt thou lay down thy life for my sake? Verily, verily, I say unto thee, The cock shall not crow, till thou hast denied me thrice.

XIV

14^1Let not your heart be troubled: ye believe in God, believe also in me.

^2In my Father’s house are many mansions: if it were not so, I would have told you. I go to prepare a place for you.

^3And if I go and prepare a place for you, I will come again, and receive you unto myself; that where I am, there ye may be also.

^4And whither I go ye know, and the way ye know.

^5Thomas saith unto him, Lord, we know not whither thou goest; and how can we know the way?

^6Jesus saith unto him, I am the way, the truth, and the life: no man cometh unto the Father, but by me.

^7If ye had known me, ye should have known my Father also: and from henceforth ye know him, and have seen him.

^8Philip saith unto him, Lord, shew us the Father, and it sufficeth us.

^9Jesus saith unto him, Have I been so long time with you, and yet hast thou not known me, Philip? he that hath seen me hath seen the Father; and how sayest thou then, Shew us the Father?

^10Believest thou not that I am in the Father, and the Father in me? the words that I speak unto you I speak not of myself: but the Father that dwelleth in me, he doeth the works.

^11Believe me that I am in the Father, and the Father in me: or else believe me for the very works’ sake.

^12Verily, verily, I say unto you, He that believeth on me, the works that I do shall he do also; and greater works than these shall he do; because I go unto my Father.

^13And whatsoever ye shall ask in my name, that will I do, that the Father may be glorified in the Son.

^14If ye shall ask any thing in my name, I will do it.

^15If ye love me, keep my commandments.

^16And I will pray the Father, and he shall give you another Comforter, that he may abide with you for ever;

^17Even the Spirit of truth; whom the world cannot receive, because it seeth him not, neither knoweth him: but ye know him; for he dwelleth with you, and shall be in you.

^18I will not leave you comfortless: I will come to you.

^19Yet a little while, and the world seeth me no more; but ye see me: because I live, ye shall live also.

^20At that day ye shall know that I am in my Father, and ye in me, and I in you.

^21He that hath my commandments, and keepeth them, he it is that loveth me: and he that loveth me shall be loved of my Father, and I will love him, and will manifest myself to him.

^22Judas saith unto him, not Iscariot, Lord, how is it that thou wilt manifest thyself unto us, and not unto the world?

^23Jesus answered and said unto him, If a man love me, he will keep my words: and my Father will love him, and we will come unto him, and make our abode with him.

^24He that loveth me not keepeth not my sayings: and the word which ye hear is not mine, but the Father’s which sent me.

^25These things have I spoken unto you, being yet present with you.

^26But the Comforter, which is the Holy Ghost, whom the Father will send in my name, he shall teach you all things, and bring all things to your remembrance, whatsoever I have said unto you.

^27Peace I leave with you, my peace I give unto you: not as the world giveth, give I unto you. Let not your heart be troubled, neither let it be afraid.

^28Ye have heard how I said unto you, I go away, and come again unto you. If ye loved me, ye would rejoice, because I said, I go unto the Father: for my Father is greater than I.

^29And now I have told you before it come to pass, that, when it is come to pass, ye might believe.

^30Hereafter I will not talk much with you: for the prince of this world cometh, and hath nothing in me.

^31But that the world may know that I love the Father; and as the Father gave me commandment, even so I do. Arise, let us go hence.

XV

15^1I am the true vine, and my Father is the husbandman.

^2Every branch in me that beareth not fruit he taketh away: and every branch that beareth fruit, he purgeth it, that it may bring forth more fruit.

^3Now ye are clean through the word which I have spoken unto you.

^4Abide in me, and I in you. As the branch cannot bear fruit of itself, except it abide in the vine; no more can ye, except ye abide in me.

^5I am the vine, ye are the branches: He that abideth in me, and I in him, the same bringeth forth much fruit: for without me ye can do nothing.

^6If a man abide not in me, he is cast forth as a branch, and is withered; and men gather them, and cast them into the fire, and they are burned.

^7If ye abide in me, and my words abide in you, ye shall ask what ye will, and it shall be done unto you.

^8Herein is my Father glorified, that ye bear much fruit; so shall ye be my disciples.

^9As the Father hath loved me, so have I loved you: continue ye in my love.

^10If ye keep my commandments, ye shall abide in my love; even as I have kept my Father’s commandments, and abide in his love.

^11These things have I spoken unto you, that my joy might remain in you, and that your joy might be full.

^12This is my commandment, That ye love one another, as I have loved you.

^13Greater love hath no man than this, that a man lay down his life for his friends.

^14Ye are my friends, if ye do whatsoever I command you.

^15Henceforth I call you not servants; for the servant knoweth not what his lord doeth: but I have called you friends; for all things that I have heard of my Father I have made known unto you.

^16Ye have not chosen me, but I have chosen you, and ordained you, that ye should go and bring forth fruit, and that your fruit should remain: that whatsoever ye shall ask of the Father in my name, he may give it you.

^17These things I command you, that ye love one another.

^18If the world hate you, ye know that it hated me before it hated you.

^19If ye were of the world, the world would love his own: but because ye are not of the world, but I have chosen you out of the world, therefore the world hateth you.

^20Remember the word that I said unto you, The servant is not greater than his lord. If they have persecuted me, they will also persecute you; if they have kept my saying, they will keep yours also.

^21But all these things will they do unto you for my name’s sake, because they know not him that sent me.

^22If I had not come and spoken unto them, they had not had sin: but now they have no cloak for their sin.

^23He that hateth me hateth my Father also.

^24If I had not done among them the works which none other man did, they had not had sin: but now have they both seen and hated both me and my Father.

^25But this cometh to pass, that the word might be fulfilled that is written in their law, They hated me without a cause.

^26But when the Comforter is come, whom I will send unto you from the Father, even the Spirit of truth, which proceedeth from the Father, he shall testify of me:

^27And ye also shall bear witness, because ye have been with me from the beginning.

XVI

16^1These things have I spoken unto you, that ye should not be offended.

^2They shall put you out of the synagogues: yea, the time cometh, that whosoever killeth you will think that he doeth God service.

^3And these things will they do unto you, because they have not known the Father, nor me.

^4But these things have I told you, that when the time shall come, ye may remember that I told you of them. And these things I said not unto you at the beginning, because I was with you.

^5But now I go my way to him that sent me; and none of you asketh me, Whither goest thou?

^6But because I have said these things unto you, sorrow hath filled your heart.

^7Nevertheless I tell you the truth; It is expedient for you that I go away: for if I go not away, the Comforter will not come unto you; but if I depart, I will send him unto you.

^8And when he is come, he will reprove the world of sin, and of righteousness, and of judgment:

^9Of sin, because they believe not on me;

^10Of righteousness, because I go to my Father, and ye see me no more;

^11Of judgment, because the prince of this world is judged.

^12I have yet many things to say unto you, but ye cannot bear them now.

^13Howbeit when he, the Spirit of truth, is come, he will guide you into all truth: for he shall not speak of himself; but whatsoever he shall hear, that shall he speak: and he will shew you things to come.

^14He shall glorify me: for he shall receive of mine, and shall shew it unto you.

^15All things that the Father hath are mine: therefore said I, that he shall take of mine, and shall shew it unto you.

^16A little while, and ye shall not see me: and again, a little while, and ye shall see me, because I go to the Father.

^17Then said some of his disciples among themselves, What is this that he saith unto us, A little while, and ye shall not see me: and again, a little while, and ye shall see me: and, Because I go to the Father?

^18They said therefore, What is this that he saith, A little while? we cannot tell what he saith.

^19Now Jesus knew that they were desirous to ask him, and said unto them, Do ye enquire among yourselves of that I said, A little while, and ye shall not see me: and again, a little while, and ye shall see me?

^20Verily, verily, I say unto you, That ye shall weep and lament, but the world shall rejoice: and ye shall be sorrowful, but your sorrow shall be turned into joy.

^21A woman when she is in travail hath sorrow, because her hour is come: but as soon as she is delivered of the child, she remembereth no more the anguish, for joy that a man is born into the world.

^22And ye now therefore have sorrow: but I will see you again, and your heart shall rejoice, and your joy no man taketh from you.

^23And in that day ye shall ask me nothing. Verily, verily, I say unto you, Whatsoever ye shall ask the Father in my name, he will give it you.

^24Hitherto have ye asked nothing in my name: ask, and ye shall receive, that your joy may be full.

^25These things have I spoken unto you in proverbs: but the time cometh, when I shall no more speak unto you in proverbs, but I shall shew you plainly of the Father.

^26At that day ye shall ask in my name: and I say not unto you, that I will pray the Father for you:

^27For the Father himself loveth you, because ye have loved me, and have believed that I came out from God.

^28I came forth from the Father, and am come into the world: again, I leave the world, and go to the Father.

^29His disciples said unto him, Lo, now speakest thou plainly, and speakest no proverb.

^30Now are we sure that thou knowest all things, and needest not that any man should ask thee: by this we believe that thou camest forth from God.

^31Jesus answered them, Do ye now believe?

^32Behold, the hour cometh, yea, is now come, that ye shall be scattered, every man to his own, and shall leave me alone: and yet I am not alone, because the Father is with me.

^33These things I have spoken unto you, that in me ye might have peace. In the world ye shall have tribulation: but be of good cheer; I have overcome the world.

XVII

17^1These words spake Jesus, and lifted up his eyes to heaven, and said, Father, the hour is come; glorify thy Son, that thy Son also may glorify thee:

^2As thou hast given him power over all flesh, that he should give eternal life to as many as thou hast given him.

^3And this is life eternal, that they might know thee the only true God, and Jesus Christ, whom thou hast sent.

^4I have glorified thee on the earth: I have finished the work which thou gavest me to do.

^5And now, O Father, glorify thou me with thine own self with the glory which I had with thee before the world was.

^6I have manifested thy name unto the men which thou gavest me out of the world: thine they were, and thou gavest them me; and they have kept thy word.

^7Now they have known that all things whatsoever thou hast given me are of thee.

^8For I have given unto them the words which thou gavest me; and they have received them, and have known surely that I came out from thee, and they have believed that thou didst send me.

^9I pray for them: I pray not for the world, but for them which thou hast given me; for they are thine.

^10And all mine are thine, and thine are mine; and I am glorified in them.

^11And now I am no more in the world, but these are in the world, and I come to thee. Holy Father, keep through thine own name those whom thou hast given me, that they may be one, as we are.

^12While I was with them in the world, I kept them in thy name: those that thou gavest me I have kept, and none of them is lost, but the son of perdition; that the scripture might be fulfilled.

^13And now come I to thee; and these things I speak in the world, that they might have my joy fulfilled in themselves.

^14I have given them thy word; and the world hath hated them, because they are not of the world, even as I am not of the world.

^15I pray not that thou shouldest take them out of the world, but that thou shouldest keep them from the evil.

^16They are not of the world, even as I am not of the world.

^17Sanctify them through thy truth: thy word is truth.

^18As thou hast sent me into the world, even so have I also sent them into the world.

^19And for their sakes I sanctify myself, that they also might be sanctified through the truth.

^20Neither pray I for these alone, but for them also which shall believe on me through their word;

^21That they all may be one; as thou, Father, art in me, and I in thee, that they also may be one in us: that the world may believe that thou hast sent me.

^22And the glory which thou gavest me I have given them; that they may be one, even as we are one:

^23I in them, and thou in me, that they may be made perfect in one; and that the world may know that thou hast sent me, and hast loved them, as thou hast loved me.

^24Father, I will that they also, whom thou hast given me, be with me where I am; that they may behold my glory, which thou hast given me: for thou lovedst me before the foundation of the world.

^25O righteous Father, the world hath not known thee: but I have known thee, and these have known that thou hast sent me.

^26And I have declared unto them thy name, and will declare it: that the love wherewith thou hast loved me may be in them, and I in them.

XVIII

18^1When Jesus had spoken these words, he went forth with his disciples over the brook Cedron, where was a garden, into the which he entered, and his disciples.

^2And Judas also, which betrayed him, knew the place: for Jesus ofttimes resorted thither with his disciples.

^3Judas then, having received a band of men and officers from the chief priests and Pharisees, cometh thither with lanterns and torches and weapons.

^4Jesus therefore, knowing all things that should come upon him, went forth, and said unto them, Whom seek ye?

^5They answered him, Jesus of Nazareth. Jesus saith unto them, I am he. And Judas also, which betrayed him, stood with them.

^6As soon then as he had said unto them, I am he, they went backward, and fell to the ground.

^7Then asked he them again, Whom seek ye? And they said, Jesus of Nazareth.

^8Jesus answered, I have told you that I am he: if therefore ye seek me, let these go their way:

^9That the saying might be fulfilled, which he spake, Of them which thou gavest me have I lost none.

^10Then Simon Peter having a sword drew it, and smote the high priest’s servant, and cut off his right ear. The servant’s name was Malchus.

^11Then said Jesus unto Peter, Put up thy sword into the sheath: the cup which my Father hath given me, shall I not drink it?

^12Then the band and the captain and officers of the Jews took Jesus, and bound him,

^13And led him away to Annas first; for he was father in law to Caiaphas, which was the high priest that same year.

^14Now Caiaphas was he, which gave counsel to the Jews, that it was expedient that one man should die for the people.

^15And Simon Peter followed Jesus, and so did another disciple: that disciple was known unto the high priest, and went in with Jesus into the palace of the high priest.

^16But Peter stood at the door without. Then went out that other disciple, which was known unto the high priest, and spake unto her that kept the door, and brought in Peter.

^17Then saith the damsel that kept the door unto Peter, Art not thou also one of this man’s disciples? He saith, I am not.

^18And the servants and officers stood there, who had made a fire of coals; for it was cold: and they warmed themselves: and Peter stood with them, and warmed himself.

^19The high priest then asked Jesus of his disciples, and of his doctrine.

^20Jesus answered him, I spake openly to the world; I ever taught in the synagogue, and in the temple, whither the Jews always resort; and in secret have I said nothing.

^21Why askest thou me? ask them which heard me, what I have said unto them: behold, they know what I said.

^22And when he had thus spoken, one of the officers which stood by struck Jesus with the palm of his hand, saying, Answerest thou the high priest so?

^23Jesus answered him, If I have spoken evil, bear witness of the evil: but if well, why smitest thou me?

^24Now Annas had sent him bound unto Caiaphas the high priest.

^25And Simon Peter stood and warmed himself. They said therefore unto him, Art not thou also one of his disciples? He denied it, and said, I am not.

^26One of the servants of the high priest, being his kinsman whose ear Peter cut off, saith, Did not I see thee in the garden with him?

^27Peter then denied again: and immediately the cock crew.

^28Then led they Jesus from Caiaphas unto the hall of judgment: and it was early; and they themselves went not into the judgment hall, lest they should be defiled; but that they might eat the passover.

^29Pilate then went out unto them, and said, What accusation bring ye against this man?

^30They answered and said unto him, If he were not a malefactor, we would not have delivered him up unto thee.

^31Then said Pilate unto them, Take ye him, and judge him according to your law. The Jews therefore said unto him, It is not lawful for us to put any man to death:

^32That the saying of Jesus might be fulfilled, which he spake, signifying what death he should die.

^33Then Pilate entered into the judgment hall again, and called Jesus, and said unto him, Art thou the King of the Jews?

^34Jesus answered him, Sayest thou this thing of thyself, or did others tell it thee of me?

^35Pilate answered, Am I a Jew? Thine own nation and the chief priests have delivered thee unto me: what hast thou done?

^36Jesus answered, My kingdom is not of this world: if my kingdom were of this world, then would my servants fight, that I should not be delivered to the Jews: but now is my kingdom not from hence.

^37Pilate therefore said unto him, Art thou a king then? Jesus answered, Thou sayest that I am a king. To this end was I born, and for this cause came I into the world, that I should bear witness unto the truth. Every one that is of the truth heareth my voice.

^38Pilate saith unto him, What is truth? And when he had said this, he went out again unto the Jews, and saith unto them, I find in him no fault at all.

^39But ye have a custom, that I should release unto you one at the passover: will ye therefore that I release unto you the King of the Jews?

^40Then cried they all again, saying, Not this man, but Barabbas. Now Barabbas was a robber.

XIX

19^1Then Pilate therefore took Jesus, and scourged him.

^2And the soldiers platted a crown of thorns, and put it on his head, and they put on him a purple robe,

^3And said, Hail, King of the Jews! and they smote him with their hands.

^4Pilate therefore went forth again, and saith unto them, Behold, I bring him forth to you, that ye may know that I find no fault in him.

^5Then came Jesus forth, wearing the crown of thorns, and the purple robe. And Pilate saith unto them, Behold the man!

^6When the chief priests therefore and officers saw him, they cried out, saying, Crucify him, crucify him. Pilate saith unto them, Take ye him, and crucify him: for I find no fault in him.

^7The Jews answered him, We have a law, and by our law he ought to die, because he made himself the Son of God.

^8When Pilate therefore heard that saying, he was the more afraid;

^9And went again into the judgment hall, and saith unto Jesus, Whence art thou? But Jesus gave him no answer.

^10Then saith Pilate unto him, Speakest thou not unto me? knowest thou not that I have power to crucify thee, and have power to release thee?

^11Jesus answered, Thou couldest have no power at all against me, except it were given thee from above: therefore he that delivered me unto thee hath the greater sin.

^12And from thenceforth Pilate sought to release him: but the Jews cried out, saying, If thou let this man go, thou art not Caesar’s friend: whosoever maketh himself a king speaketh against Caesar.

^13When Pilate therefore heard that saying, he brought Jesus forth, and sat down in the judgment seat in a place that is called the Pavement, but in the Hebrew, Gabbatha.

^14And it was the preparation of the passover, and about the sixth hour: and he saith unto the Jews, Behold your King!

^15But they cried out, Away with him, away with him, crucify him. Pilate saith unto them, Shall I crucify your King? The chief priests answered, We have no king but Caesar.

^16Then delivered he him therefore unto them to be crucified. And they took Jesus, and led him away.

^17And he bearing his cross went forth into a place called the place of a skull, which is called in the Hebrew Golgotha:

^18Where they crucified him, and two other with him, on either side one, and Jesus in the midst.

^19And Pilate wrote a title, and put it on the cross. And the writing was Jesus of Nazareth the King of the Jews.

^20This title then read many of the Jews: for the place where Jesus was crucified was nigh to the city: and it was written in Hebrew, and Greek, and Latin.

^21Then said the chief priests of the Jews to Pilate, Write not, The King of the Jews; but that he said, I am King of the Jews.

^22Pilate answered, What I have written I have written.

^23Then the soldiers, when they had crucified Jesus, took his garments, and made four parts, to every soldier a part; and also his coat: now the coat was without seam, woven from the top throughout.

^24They said therefore among themselves, Let us not rend it, but cast lots for it, whose it shall be: that the scripture might be fulfilled, which saith, They parted my raiment among them, and for my vesture they did cast lots. These things therefore the soldiers did.

^25Now there stood by the cross of Jesus his mother, and his mother’s sister, Mary the wife of Cleophas, and Mary Magdalene.

^26When Jesus therefore saw his mother, and the disciple standing by, whom he loved, he saith unto his mother, Woman, behold thy son!

^27Then saith he to the disciple, Behold thy mother! And from that hour that disciple took her unto his own home.

^28After this, Jesus knowing that all things were now accomplished, that the scripture might be fulfilled, saith, I thirst.

^29Now there was set a vessel full of vinegar: and they filled a spunge with vinegar, and put it upon hyssop, and put it to his mouth.

^30When Jesus therefore had received the vinegar, he said, It is finished: and he bowed his head, and gave up the ghost.

^31The Jews therefore, because it was the preparation, that the bodies should not remain upon the cross on the sabbath day, (for that sabbath day was an high day,) besought Pilate that their legs might be broken, and that they might be taken away.

^32Then came the soldiers, and brake the legs of the first, and of the other which was crucified with him.

^33But when they came to Jesus, and saw that he was dead already, they brake not his legs:

^34But one of the soldiers with a spear pierced his side, and forthwith came there out blood and water.

^35And he that saw it bare record, and his record is true: and he knoweth that he saith true, that ye might believe.

^36For these things were done, that the scripture should be fulfilled, A bone of him shall not be broken.

^37And again another scripture saith, They shall look on him whom they pierced.

^38And after this Joseph of Arimathaea, being a disciple of Jesus, but secretly for fear of the Jews, besought Pilate that he might take away the body of Jesus: and Pilate gave him leave. He came therefore, and took the body of Jesus.

^39And there came also Nicodemus, which at the first came to Jesus by night, and brought a mixture of myrrh and aloes, about an hundred pound weight.

^40Then took they the body of Jesus, and wound it in linen clothes with the spices, as the manner of the Jews is to bury.

^41Now in the place where he was crucified there was a garden; and in the garden a new sepulchre, wherein was never man yet laid.

^42There laid they Jesus therefore because of the Jews’ preparation day; for the sepulchre was nigh at hand.

XX

20^1The first day of the week cometh Mary Magdalene early, when it was yet dark, unto the sepulchre, and seeth the stone taken away from the sepulchre.

^2Then she runneth, and cometh to Simon Peter, and to the other disciple, whom Jesus loved, and saith unto them, They have taken away the Lord out of the sepulchre, and we know not where they have laid him.

^3Peter therefore went forth, and that other disciple, and came to the sepulchre.

^4So they ran both together: and the other disciple did outrun Peter, and came first to the sepulchre.

^5And he stooping down, and looking in, saw the linen clothes lying; yet went he not in.

^6Then cometh Simon Peter following him, and went into the sepulchre, and seeth the linen clothes lie,

^7And the napkin, that was about his head, not lying with the linen clothes, but wrapped together in a place by itself.

^8Then went in also that other disciple, which came first to the sepulchre, and he saw, and believed.

^9For as yet they knew not the scripture, that he must rise again from the dead.

^10Then the disciples went away again unto their own home.

^11But Mary stood without at the sepulchre weeping: and as she wept, she stooped down, and looked into the sepulchre,

^12And seeth two angels in white sitting, the one at the head, and the other at the feet, where the body of Jesus had lain.

^13And they say unto her, Woman, why weepest thou? She saith unto them, Because they have taken away my Lord, and I know not where they have laid him.

^14And when she had thus said, she turned herself back, and saw Jesus standing, and knew not that it was Jesus.

^15Jesus saith unto her, Woman, why weepest thou? whom seekest thou? She, supposing him to be the gardener, saith unto him, Sir, if thou have borne him hence, tell me where thou hast laid him, and I will take him away.

^16Jesus saith unto her, Mary. She turned herself, and saith unto him, Rabboni; which is to say, Master.

^17Jesus saith unto her, Touch me not; for I am not yet ascended to my Father: but go to my brethren, and say unto them, I ascend unto my Father, and your Father; and to my God, and your God.

^18Mary Magdalene came and told the disciples that she had seen the Lord, and that he had spoken these things unto her.

^19Then the same day at evening, being the first day of the week, when the doors were shut where the disciples were assembled for fear of the Jews, came Jesus and stood in the midst, and saith unto them, Peace be unto you.

^20And when he had so said, he shewed unto them his hands and his side. Then were the disciples glad, when they saw the Lord.

^21Then said Jesus to them again, Peace be unto you: as my Father hath sent me, even so send I you.

^22And when he had said this, he breathed on them, and saith unto them, Receive ye the Holy Ghost:

^23Whose soever sins ye remit, they are remitted unto them; and whose soever sins ye retain, they are retained.

^24But Thomas, one of the twelve, called Didymus, was not with them when Jesus came.

^25The other disciples therefore said unto him, We have seen the Lord. But he said unto them, Except I shall see in his hands the print of the nails, and put my finger into the print of the nails, and thrust my hand into his side, I will not believe.

^26And after eight days again his disciples were within, and Thomas with them: then came Jesus, the doors being shut, and stood in the midst, and said, Peace be unto you.

^27Then saith he to Thomas, Reach hither thy finger, and behold my hands; and reach hither thy hand, and thrust it into my side: and be not faithless, but believing.

^28And Thomas answered and said unto him, My Lord and my God.

^29Jesus saith unto him, Thomas, because thou hast seen me, thou hast believed: blessed are they that have not seen, and yet have believed.

^30And many other signs truly did Jesus in the presence of his disciples, which are not written in this book:

^31But these are written, that ye might believe that Jesus is the Christ, the Son of God; and that believing ye might have life through his name.

XXI

21^1After these things Jesus shewed himself again to the disciples at the sea of Tiberias; and on this wise shewed he himself.

^2There were together Simon Peter, and Thomas called Didymus, and Nathanael of Cana in Galilee, and the sons of Zebedee, and two other of his disciples.

^3Simon Peter saith unto them, I go a fishing. They say unto him, We also go with thee. They went forth, and entered into a ship immediately; and that night they caught nothing.

^4But when the morning was now come, Jesus stood on the shore: but the disciples knew not that it was Jesus.

^5Then Jesus saith unto them, Children, have ye any meat? They answered him, No.

^6And he said unto them, Cast the net on the right side of the ship, and ye shall find. They cast therefore, and now they were not able to draw it for the multitude of fishes.

^7Therefore that disciple whom Jesus loved saith unto Peter, It is the Lord. Now when Simon Peter heard that it was the Lord, he girt his fisher’s coat unto him, (for he was naked,) and did cast himself into the sea.

^8And the other disciples came in a little ship; (for they were not far from land, but as it were two hundred cubits,) dragging the net with fishes.

^9As soon then as they were come to land, they saw a fire of coals there, and fish laid thereon, and bread.

^10Jesus saith unto them, Bring of the fish which ye have now caught.

^11Simon Peter went up, and drew the net to land full of great fishes, an hundred and fifty and three: and for all there were so many, yet was not the net broken.

^12Jesus saith unto them, Come and dine. And none of the disciples durst ask him, Who art thou? knowing that it was the Lord.

^13Jesus then cometh, and taketh bread, and giveth them, and fish likewise.

^14This is now the third time that Jesus shewed himself to his disciples, after that he was risen from the dead.

^15So when they had dined, Jesus saith to Simon Peter, Simon, son of Jonas, lovest thou me more than these? He saith unto him, Yea, Lord; thou knowest that I love thee. He saith unto him, Feed my lambs.

^16He saith to him again the second time, Simon, son of Jonas, lovest thou me? He saith unto him, Yea, Lord; thou knowest that I love thee. He saith unto him, Feed my sheep.

^17He saith unto him the third time, Simon, son of Jonas, lovest thou me? Peter was grieved because he said unto him the third time, Lovest thou me? And he said unto him, Lord, thou knowest all things; thou knowest that I love thee. Jesus saith unto him, Feed my sheep.

^18Verily, verily, I say unto thee, When thou wast young, thou girdest thyself, and walkedst whither thou wouldest: but when thou shalt be old, thou shalt stretch forth thy hands, and another shall gird thee, and carry thee whither thou wouldest not.

^19This spake he, signifying by what death he should glorify God. And when he had spoken this, he saith unto him, Follow me.

^20Then Peter, turning about, seeth the disciple whom Jesus loved following; which also leaned on his breast at supper, and said, Lord, which is he that betrayeth thee?

^21Peter seeing him saith to Jesus, Lord, and what shall this man do?

^22Jesus saith unto him, If I will that he tarry till I come, what is that to thee? follow thou me.

^23Then went this saying abroad among the brethren, that that disciple should not die: yet Jesus said not unto him, He shall not die; but, If I will that he tarry till I come, what is that to thee?

^24This is the disciple which testifieth of these things, and wrote these things: and we know that his testimony is true.

^25And there are also many other things which Jesus did, the which, if they should be written every one, I suppose that even the world itself could not contain the books that should be written. Amen.

Acts 1

1^1The former treatise have I made, O Theophilus, of all that Jesus began both to do and teach,

^2Until the day in which he was taken up, after that he through the Holy Ghost had given commandments unto the apostles whom he had chosen:

^3To whom also he shewed himself alive after his passion by many infallible proofs, being seen of them forty days, and speaking of the things pertaining to the kingdom of God:

^4And, being assembled together with them, commanded them that they should not depart from Jerusalem, but wait for the promise of the Father, which, saith he, ye have heard of me.

^5For John truly baptized with water; but ye shall be baptized with the Holy Ghost not many days hence.

^6When they therefore were come together, they asked of him, saying, Lord, wilt thou at this time restore again the kingdom to Israel?

^7And he said unto them, It is not for you to know the times or the seasons, which the Father hath put in his own power.

^8But ye shall receive power, after that the Holy Ghost is come upon you: and ye shall be witnesses unto me both in Jerusalem, and in all Judaea, and in Samaria, and unto the uttermost part of the earth.

^9And when he had spoken these things, while they beheld, he was taken up; and a cloud received him out of their sight.

^10And while they looked stedfastly toward heaven as he went up, behold, two men stood by them in white apparel;

^11Which also said, Ye men of Galilee, why stand ye gazing up into heaven? this same Jesus, which is taken up from you into heaven, shall so come in like manner as ye have seen him go into heaven.

^12Then returned they unto Jerusalem from the mount called Olivet, which is from Jerusalem a sabbath day’s journey.

^13And when they were come in, they went up into an upper room, where abode both Peter, and James, and John, and Andrew, Philip, and Thomas, Bartholomew, and Matthew, James the son of Alphaeus, and Simon Zelotes, and Judas the brother of James.

^14These all continued with one accord in prayer and supplication, with the women, and Mary the mother of Jesus, and with his brethren.

^15And in those days Peter stood up in the midst of the disciples, and said, (the number of names together were about an hundred and twenty,)

^16Men and brethren, this scripture must needs have been fulfilled, which the Holy Ghost by the mouth of David spake before concerning Judas, which was guide to them that took Jesus.

^17For he was numbered with us, and had obtained part of this ministry.

^18Now this man purchased a field with the reward of iniquity; and falling headlong, he burst asunder in the midst, and all his bowels gushed out.

^19And it was known unto all the dwellers at Jerusalem; insomuch as that field is called in their proper tongue, Aceldama, that is to say, The field of blood.

^20For it is written in the book of Psalms, Let his habitation be desolate, and let no man dwell therein: and his bishoprick let another take.

^21Wherefore of these men which have companied with us all the time that the Lord Jesus went in and out among us,

^22Beginning from the baptism of John, unto that same day that he was taken up from us, must one be ordained to be a witness with us of his resurrection.

^23And they appointed two, Joseph called Barsabas, who was surnamed Justus, and Matthias.

^24And they prayed, and said, Thou, Lord, which knowest the hearts of all men, shew whether of these two thou hast chosen,

^25That he may take part of this ministry and apostleship, from which Judas by transgression fell, that he might go to his own place.

^26And they gave forth their lots; and the lot fell upon Matthias; and he was numbered with the eleven apostles.

Acts 2

2^1And when the day of Pentecost was fully come, they were all with one accord in one place.

^2And suddenly there came a sound from heaven as of a rushing mighty wind, and it filled all the house where they were sitting.

^3And there appeared unto them cloven tongues like as of fire, and it sat upon each of them.

^4And they were all filled with the Holy Ghost, and began to speak with other tongues, as the Spirit gave them utterance.

^5And there were dwelling at Jerusalem Jews, devout men, out of every nation under heaven.

^6Now when this was noised abroad, the multitude came together, and were confounded, because that every man heard them speak in his own language.

^7And they were all amazed and marvelled, saying one to another, Behold, are not all these which speak Galilaeans?

^8And how hear we every man in our own tongue, wherein we were born?

^9Parthians, and Medes, and Elamites, and the dwellers in Mesopotamia, and in Judaea, and Cappadocia, in Pontus, and Asia,

^10Phrygia, and Pamphylia, in Egypt, and in the parts of Libya about Cyrene, and strangers of Rome, Jews and proselytes,

^11Cretes and Arabians, we do hear them speak in our tongues the wonderful works of God.

^12And they were all amazed, and were in doubt, saying one to another, What meaneth this?

^13Others mocking said, These men are full of new wine.

^14But Peter, standing up with the eleven, lifted up his voice, and said unto them, Ye men of Judaea, and all ye that dwell at Jerusalem, be this known unto you, and hearken to my words:

^15For these are not drunken, as ye suppose, seeing it is but the third hour of the day.

^16But this is that which was spoken by the prophet Joel;

^17And it shall come to pass in the last days, saith God, I will pour out of my Spirit upon all flesh: and your sons and your daughters shall prophesy, and your young men shall see visions, and your old men shall dream dreams:

^18And on my servants and on my handmaidens I will pour out in those days of my Spirit; and they shall prophesy:

^19And I will shew wonders in heaven above, and signs in the earth beneath; blood, and fire, and vapour of smoke:

^20The sun shall be turned into darkness, and the moon into blood, before the great and notable day of the Lord come:

^21And it shall come to pass, that whosoever shall call on the name of the Lord shall be saved.

^22Ye men of Israel, hear these words; Jesus of Nazareth, a man approved of God among you by miracles and wonders and signs, which God did by him in the midst of you, as ye yourselves also know:

^23Him, being delivered by the determinate counsel and foreknowledge of God, ye have taken, and by wicked hands have crucified and slain:

^24Whom God hath raised up, having loosed the pains of death: because it was not possible that he should be holden of it.

^25For David speaketh concerning him, I foresaw the Lord always before my face, for he is on my right hand, that I should not be moved:

^26Therefore did my heart rejoice, and my tongue was glad; moreover also my flesh shall rest in hope:

^27Because thou wilt not leave my soul in hell, neither wilt thou suffer thine Holy One to see corruption.

^28Thou hast made known to me the ways of life; thou shalt make me full of joy with thy countenance.

^29Men and brethren, let me freely speak unto you of the patriarch David, that he is both dead and buried, and his sepulchre is with us unto this day.

^30Therefore being a prophet, and knowing that God had sworn with an oath to him, that of the fruit of his loins, according to the flesh, he would raise up Christ to sit on his throne;

^31He seeing this before spake of the resurrection of Christ, that his soul was not left in hell, neither his flesh did see corruption.

^32This Jesus hath God raised up, whereof we all are witnesses.

^33Therefore being by the right hand of God exalted, and having received of the Father the promise of the Holy Ghost, he hath shed forth this, which ye now see and hear.

^34For David is not ascended into the heavens: but he saith himself, The Lord said unto my Lord, Sit thou on my right hand,

^35Until I make thy foes thy footstool.

^36Therefore let all the house of Israel know assuredly, that God hath made the same Jesus, whom ye have crucified, both Lord and Christ.

^37Now when they heard this, they were pricked in their heart, and said unto Peter and to the rest of the apostles, Men and brethren, what shall we do?

^38Then Peter said unto them, Repent, and be baptized every one of you in the name of Jesus Christ for the remission of sins, and ye shall receive the gift of the Holy Ghost.

^39For the promise is unto you, and to your children, and to all that are afar off, even as many as the Lord our God shall call.

^40And with many other words did he testify and exhort, saying, Save yourselves from this untoward generation.

^41Then they that gladly received his word were baptized: and the same day there were added unto them about three thousand souls.

^42And they continued stedfastly in the apostles’ doctrine and fellowship, and in breaking of bread, and in prayers.

^43And fear came upon every soul: and many wonders and signs were done by the apostles.

^44And all that believed were together, and had all things common;

^45And sold their possessions and goods, and parted them to all men, as every man had need.

^46And they, continuing daily with one accord in the temple, and breaking bread from house to house, did eat their meat with gladness and singleness of heart,

^47Praising God, and having favour with all the people. And the Lord added to the church daily such as should be saved.

Acts 3

3^1Now Peter and John went up together into the temple at the hour of prayer, being the ninth hour.

^2And a certain man lame from his mother’s womb was carried, whom they laid daily at the gate of the temple which is called Beautiful, to ask alms of them that entered into the temple;

^3Who seeing Peter and John about to go into the temple asked an alms.

^4And Peter, fastening his eyes upon him with John, said, Look on us.

^5And he gave heed unto them, expecting to receive something of them.

^6Then Peter said, Silver and gold have I none; but such as I have give I thee: In the name of Jesus Christ of Nazareth rise up and walk.

^7And he took him by the right hand, and lifted him up: and immediately his feet and ankle bones received strength.

^8And he leaping up stood, and walked, and entered with them into the temple, walking, and leaping, and praising God.

^9And all the people saw him walking and praising God:

^10And they knew that it was he which sat for alms at the Beautiful gate of the temple: and they were filled with wonder and amazement at that which had happened unto him.

^11And as the lame man which was healed held Peter and John, all the people ran together unto them in the porch that is called Solomon’s, greatly wondering.

^12And when Peter saw it, he answered unto the people, Ye men of Israel, why marvel ye at this? or why look ye so earnestly on us, as though by our own power or holiness we had made this man to walk?

^13The God of Abraham, and of Isaac, and of Jacob, the God of our fathers, hath glorified his Son Jesus; whom ye delivered up, and denied him in the presence of Pilate, when he was determined to let him go.

^14But ye denied the Holy One and the Just, and desired a murderer to be granted unto you;

^15And killed the Prince of life, whom God hath raised from the dead; whereof we are witnesses.

^16And his name through faith in his name hath made this man strong, whom ye see and know: yea, the faith which is by him hath given him this perfect soundness in the presence of you all.

^17And now, brethren, I wot that through ignorance ye did it, as did also your rulers.

^18But those things, which God before had shewed by the mouth of all his prophets, that Christ should suffer, he hath so fulfilled.

^19Repent ye therefore, and be converted, that your sins may be blotted out, when the times of refreshing shall come from the presence of the Lord.

^20And he shall send Jesus Christ, which before was preached unto you:

^21Whom the heaven must receive until the times of restitution of all things, which God hath spoken by the mouth of all his holy prophets since the world began.

^22For Moses truly said unto the fathers, A prophet shall the Lord your God raise up unto you of your brethren, like unto me; him shall ye hear in all things whatsoever he shall say unto you.

^23And it shall come to pass, that every soul, which will not hear that prophet, shall be destroyed from among the people.

^24Yea, and all the prophets from Samuel and those that follow after, as many as have spoken, have likewise foretold of these days.

^25Ye are the children of the prophets, and of the covenant which God made with our fathers, saying unto Abraham, And in thy seed shall all the kindreds of the earth be blessed.

^26Unto you first God, having raised up his Son Jesus, sent him to bless you, in turning away every one of you from his iniquities.

Acts 4

4^1And as they spake unto the people, the priests, and the captain of the temple, and the Sadducees, came upon them,

^2Being grieved that they taught the people, and preached through Jesus the resurrection from the dead.

^3And they laid hands on them, and put them in hold unto the next day: for it was now eventide.

^4Howbeit many of them which heard the word believed; and the number of the men was about five thousand.

^5And it came to pass on the morrow, that their rulers, and elders, and scribes,

^6And Annas the high priest, and Caiaphas, and John, and Alexander, and as many as were of the kindred of the high priest, were gathered together at Jerusalem.

^7And when they had set them in the midst, they asked, By what power, or by what name, have ye done this?

^8Then Peter, filled with the Holy Ghost, said unto them, Ye rulers of the people, and elders of Israel,

^9If we this day be examined of the good deed done to the impotent man, by what means he is made whole;

^10Be it known unto you all, and to all the people of Israel, that by the name of Jesus Christ of Nazareth, whom ye crucified, whom God raised from the dead, even by him doth this man stand here before you whole.

^11This is the stone which was set at nought of you builders, which is become the head of the corner.

^12Neither is there salvation in any other: for there is none other name under heaven given among men, whereby we must be saved.

^13Now when they saw the boldness of Peter and John, and perceived that they were unlearned and ignorant men, they marvelled; and they took knowledge of them, that they had been with Jesus.

^14And beholding the man which was healed standing with them, they could say nothing against it.

^15But when they had commanded them to go aside out of the council, they conferred among themselves,

^16Saying, What shall we do to these men? for that indeed a notable miracle hath been done by them is manifest to all them that dwell in Jerusalem; and we cannot deny it.

^17But that it spread no further among the people, let us straitly threaten them, that they speak henceforth to no man in this name.

^18And they called them, and commanded them not to speak at all nor teach in the name of Jesus.

^19But Peter and John answered and said unto them, Whether it be right in the sight of God to hearken unto you more than unto God, judge ye.

^20For we cannot but speak the things which we have seen and heard.

^21So when they had further threatened them, they let them go, finding nothing how they might punish them, because of the people: for all men glorified God for that which was done.

^22For the man was above forty years old, on whom this miracle of healing was shewed.

^23And being let go, they went to their own company, and reported all that the chief priests and elders had said unto them.

^24And when they heard that, they lifted up their voice to God with one accord, and said, Lord, thou art God, which hast made heaven, and earth, and the sea, and all that in them is:

^25Who by the mouth of thy servant David hast said, Why did the heathen rage, and the people imagine vain things?

^26The kings of the earth stood up, and the rulers were gathered together against the Lord, and against his Christ.

^27For of a truth against thy holy child Jesus, whom thou hast anointed, both Herod, and Pontius Pilate, with the Gentiles, and the people of Israel, were gathered together,

^28For to do whatsoever thy hand and thy counsel determined before to be done.

^29And now, Lord, behold their threatenings: and grant unto thy servants, that with all boldness they may speak thy word,

^30By stretching forth thine hand to heal; and that signs and wonders may be done by the name of thy holy child Jesus.

^31And when they had prayed, the place was shaken where they were assembled together; and they were all filled with the Holy Ghost, and they spake the word of God with boldness.

^32And the multitude of them that believed were of one heart and of one soul: neither said any of them that ought of the things which he possessed was his own; but they had all things common.

^33And with great power gave the apostles witness of the resurrection of the Lord Jesus: and great grace was upon them all.

^34Neither was there any among them that lacked: for as many as were possessors of lands or houses sold them, and brought the prices of the things that were sold,

^35And laid them down at the apostles’ feet: and distribution was made unto every man according as he had need.

^36And Joses, who by the apostles was surnamed Barnabas, (which is, being interpreted, The son of consolation,) a Levite, and of the country of Cyprus,

^37Having land, sold it, and brought the money, and laid it at the apostles’ feet.

Acts 5

5^1But a certain man named Ananias, with Sapphira his wife, sold a possession,

^2And kept back part of the price, his wife also being privy to it, and brought a certain part, and laid it at the apostles’ feet.

^3But Peter said, Ananias, why hath Satan filled thine heart to lie to the Holy Ghost, and to keep back part of the price of the land?

^4Whiles it remained, was it not thine own? and after it was sold, was it not in thine own power? why hast thou conceived this thing in thine heart? thou hast not lied unto men, but unto God.

^5And Ananias hearing these words fell down, and gave up the ghost: and great fear came on all them that heard these things.

^6And the young men arose, wound him up, and carried him out, and buried him.

^7And it was about the space of three hours after, when his wife, not knowing what was done, came in.

^8And Peter answered unto her, Tell me whether ye sold the land for so much? And she said, Yea, for so much.

^9Then Peter said unto her, How is it that ye have agreed together to tempt the Spirit of the Lord? behold, the feet of them which have buried thy husband are at the door, and shall carry thee out.

^10Then fell she down straightway at his feet, and yielded up the ghost: and the young men came in, and found her dead, and, carrying her forth, buried her by her husband.

^11And great fear came upon all the church, and upon as many as heard these things.

^12And by the hands of the apostles were many signs and wonders wrought among the people; (and they were all with one accord in Solomon’s porch.

^13And of the rest durst no man join himself to them: but the people magnified them.

^14And believers were the more added to the Lord, multitudes both of men and women.)

^15Insomuch that they brought forth the sick into the streets, and laid them on beds and couches, that at the least the shadow of Peter passing by might overshadow some of them.

^16There came also a multitude out of the cities round about unto Jerusalem, bringing sick folks, and them which were vexed with unclean spirits: and they were healed every one.

^17Then the high priest rose up, and all they that were with him, (which is the sect of the Sadducees,) and were filled with indignation,

^18And laid their hands on the apostles, and put them in the common prison.

^19But the angel of the Lord by night opened the prison doors, and brought them forth, and said,

^20Go, stand and speak in the temple to the people all the words of this life.

^21And when they heard that, they entered into the temple early in the morning, and taught. But the high priest came, and they that were with him, and called the council together, and all the senate of the children of Israel, and sent to the prison to have them brought.

^22But when the officers came, and found them not in the prison, they returned and told,

^23Saying, The prison truly found we shut with all safety, and the keepers standing without before the doors: but when we had opened, we found no man within.

^24Now when the high priest and the captain of the temple and the chief priests heard these things, they doubted of them whereunto this would grow.

^25Then came one and told them, saying, Behold, the men whom ye put in prison are standing in the temple, and teaching the people.

^26Then went the captain with the officers, and brought them without violence: for they feared the people, lest they should have been stoned.

^27And when they had brought them, they set them before the council: and the high priest asked them,

^28Saying, Did not we straitly command you that ye should not teach in this name? and, behold, ye have filled Jerusalem with your doctrine, and intend to bring this man’s blood upon us.

^29Then Peter and the other apostles answered and said, We ought to obey God rather than men.

^30The God of our fathers raised up Jesus, whom ye slew and hanged on a tree.

^31Him hath God exalted with his right hand to be a Prince and a Saviour, for to give repentance to Israel, and forgiveness of sins.

^32And we are his witnesses of these things; and so is also the Holy Ghost, whom God hath given to them that obey him.

^33When they heard that, they were cut to the heart, and took counsel to slay them.

^34Then stood there up one in the council, a Pharisee, named Gamaliel, a doctor of the law, had in reputation among all the people, and commanded to put the apostles forth a little space;

^35And said unto them, Ye men of Israel, take heed to yourselves what ye intend to do as touching these men.

^36For before these days rose up Theudas, boasting himself to be somebody; to whom a number of men, about four hundred, joined themselves: who was slain; and all, as many as obeyed him, were scattered, and brought to nought.

^37After this man rose up Judas of Galilee in the days of the taxing, and drew away much people after him: he also perished; and all, even as many as obeyed him, were dispersed.

^38And now I say unto you, Refrain from these men, and let them alone: for if this counsel or this work be of men, it will come to nought:

^39But if it be of God, ye cannot overthrow it; lest haply ye be found even to fight against God.

^40And to him they agreed: and when they had called the apostles, and beaten them, they commanded that they should not speak in the name of Jesus, and let them go.

^41And they departed from the presence of the council, rejoicing that they were counted worthy to suffer shame for his name.

^42And daily in the temple, and in every house, they ceased not to teach and preach Jesus Christ.

Acts 6

6^1And in those days, when the number of the disciples was multiplied, there arose a murmuring of the Grecians against the Hebrews, because their widows were neglected in the daily ministration.

^2Then the twelve called the multitude of the disciples unto them, and said, It is not reason that we should leave the word of God, and serve tables.

^3Wherefore, brethren, look ye out among you seven men of honest report, full of the Holy Ghost and wisdom, whom we may appoint over this business.

^4But we will give ourselves continually to prayer, and to the ministry of the word.

^5And the saying pleased the whole multitude: and they chose Stephen, a man full of faith and of the Holy Ghost, and Philip, and Prochorus, and Nicanor, and Timon, and Parmenas, and Nicolas a proselyte of Antioch:

^6Whom they set before the apostles: and when they had prayed, they laid their hands on them.

^7And the word of God increased; and the number of the disciples multiplied in Jerusalem greatly; and a great company of the priests were obedient to the faith.

^8And Stephen, full of faith and power, did great wonders and miracles among the people.

^9Then there arose certain of the synagogue, which is called the synagogue of the Libertines, and Cyrenians, and Alexandrians, and of them of Cilicia and of Asia, disputing with Stephen.

^10And they were not able to resist the wisdom and the spirit by which he spake.

^11Then they suborned men, which said, We have heard him speak blasphemous words against Moses, and against God.

^12And they stirred up the people, and the elders, and the scribes, and came upon him, and caught him, and brought him to the council,

^13And set up false witnesses, which said, This man ceaseth not to speak blasphemous words against this holy place, and the law:

^14For we have heard him say, that this Jesus of Nazareth shall destroy this place, and shall change the customs which Moses delivered us.

^15And all that sat in the council, looking stedfastly on him, saw his face as it had been the face of an angel.

Acts 7

7^1Then said the high priest, Are these things so?

^2And he said, Men, brethren, and fathers, hearken; The God of glory appeared unto our father Abraham, when he was in Mesopotamia, before he dwelt in Charran,

^3And said unto him, Get thee out of thy country, and from thy kindred, and come into the land which I shall shew thee.

^4Then came he out of the land of the Chaldaeans, and dwelt in Charran: and from thence, when his father was dead, he removed him into this land, wherein ye now dwell.

^5And he gave him none inheritance in it, no, not so much as to set his foot on: yet he promised that he would give it to him for a possession, and to his seed after him, when as yet he had no child.

^6And God spake on this wise, That his seed should sojourn in a strange land; and that they should bring them into bondage, and entreat them evil four hundred years.

^7And the nation to whom they shall be in bondage will I judge, said God: and after that shall they come forth, and serve me in this place.

^8And he gave him the covenant of circumcision: and so Abraham begat Isaac, and circumcised him the eighth day; and Isaac begat Jacob; and Jacob begat the twelve patriarchs.

^9And the patriarchs, moved with envy, sold Joseph into Egypt: but God was with him,

^10And delivered him out of all his afflictions, and gave him favour and wisdom in the sight of Pharaoh king of Egypt; and he made him governor over Egypt and all his house.

^11Now there came a dearth over all the land of Egypt and Chanaan, and great affliction: and our fathers found no sustenance.

^12But when Jacob heard that there was corn in Egypt, he sent out our fathers first.

^13And at the second time Joseph was made known to his brethren; and Joseph’s kindred was made known unto Pharaoh.

^14Then sent Joseph, and called his father Jacob to him, and all his kindred, threescore and fifteen souls.

^15So Jacob went down into Egypt, and died, he, and our fathers,

^16And were carried over into Sychem, and laid in the sepulchre that Abraham bought for a sum of money of the sons of Emmor the father of Sychem.

^17But when the time of the promise drew nigh, which God had sworn to Abraham, the people grew and multiplied in Egypt,

^18Till another king arose, which knew not Joseph.

^19The same dealt subtilly with our kindred, and evil entreated our fathers, so that they cast out their young children, to the end they might not live.

^20In which time Moses was born, and was exceeding fair, and nourished up in his father’s house three months:

^21And when he was cast out, Pharaoh’s daughter took him up, and nourished him for her own son.

^22And Moses was learned in all the wisdom of the Egyptians, and was mighty in words and in deeds.

^23And when he was full forty years old, it came into his heart to visit his brethren the children of Israel.

^24And seeing one of them suffer wrong, he defended him, and avenged him that was oppressed, and smote the Egyptian:

^25For he supposed his brethren would have understood how that God by his hand would deliver them: but they understood not.

^26And the next day he shewed himself unto them as they strove, and would have set them at one again, saying, Sirs, ye are brethren; why do ye wrong one to another?

^27But he that did his neighbour wrong thrust him away, saying, Who made thee a ruler and a judge over us?

^28Wilt thou kill me, as thou diddest the Egyptian yesterday?

^29Then fled Moses at this saying, and was a stranger in the land of Madian, where he begat two sons.

^30And when forty years were expired, there appeared to him in the wilderness of mount Sina an angel of the Lord in a flame of fire in a bush.

^31When Moses saw it, he wondered at the sight: and as he drew near to behold it, the voice of the Lord came unto him,

^32Saying, I am the God of thy fathers, the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob. Then Moses trembled, and durst not behold.

^33Then said the Lord to him, Put off thy shoes from thy feet: for the place where thou standest is holy ground.

^34I have seen, I have seen the affliction of my people which is in Egypt, and I have heard their groaning, and am come down to deliver them. And now come, I will send thee into Egypt.

^35This Moses whom they refused, saying, Who made thee a ruler and a judge? the same did God send to be a ruler and a deliverer by the hand of the angel which appeared to him in the bush.

^36He brought them out, after that he had shewed wonders and signs in the land of Egypt, and in the Red sea, and in the wilderness forty years.

^37This is that Moses, which said unto the children of Israel, A prophet shall the Lord your God raise up unto you of your brethren, like unto me; him shall ye hear.

^38This is he, that was in the church in the wilderness with the angel which spake to him in the mount Sina, and with our fathers: who received the lively oracles to give unto us:

^39To whom our fathers would not obey, but thrust him from them, and in their hearts turned back again into Egypt,

^40Saying unto Aaron, Make us gods to go before us: for as for this Moses, which brought us out of the land of Egypt, we wot not what is become of him.

^41And they made a calf in those days, and offered sacrifice unto the idol, and rejoiced in the works of their own hands.

^42Then God turned, and gave them up to worship the host of heaven; as it is written in the book of the prophets, O ye house of Israel, have ye offered to me slain beasts and sacrifices by the space of forty years in the wilderness?

^43Yea, ye took up the tabernacle of Moloch, and the star of your god Remphan, figures which ye made to worship them: and I will carry you away beyond Babylon.

^44Our fathers had the tabernacle of witness in the wilderness, as he had appointed, speaking unto Moses, that he should make it according to the fashion that he had seen.

^45Which also our fathers that came after brought in with Jesus into the possession of the Gentiles, whom God drave out before the face of our fathers, unto the days of David;

^46Who found favour before God, and desired to find a tabernacle for the God of Jacob.

^47But Solomon built him an house.

^48Howbeit the most High dwelleth not in temples made with hands; as saith the prophet,

^49Heaven is my throne, and earth is my footstool: what house will ye build me? saith the Lord: or what is the place of my rest?

^50Hath not my hand made all these things?

^51Ye stiffnecked and uncircumcised in heart and ears, ye do always resist the Holy Ghost: as your fathers did, so do ye.

^52Which of the prophets have not your fathers persecuted? and they have slain them which shewed before of the coming of the Just One; of whom ye have been now the betrayers and murderers:

^53Who have received the law by the disposition of angels, and have not kept it.

^54When they heard these things, they were cut to the heart, and they gnashed on him with their teeth.

^55But he, being full of the Holy Ghost, looked up stedfastly into heaven, and saw the glory of God, and Jesus standing on the right hand of God,

^56And said, Behold, I see the heavens opened, and the Son of man standing on the right hand of God.

^57Then they cried out with a loud voice, and stopped their ears, and ran upon him with one accord,

^58And cast him out of the city, and stoned him: and the witnesses laid down their clothes at a young man’s feet, whose name was Saul.

^59And they stoned Stephen, calling upon God, and saying, Lord Jesus, receive my spirit.

^60And he kneeled down, and cried with a loud voice, Lord, lay not this sin to their charge. And when he had said this, he fell asleep.

Acts 8

8^1And Saul was consenting unto his death. And at that time there was a great persecution against the church which was at Jerusalem; and they were all scattered abroad throughout the regions of Judaea and Samaria, except the apostles.

^2And devout men carried Stephen to his burial, and made great lamentation over him.

^3As for Saul, he made havock of the church, entering into every house, and haling men and women committed them to prison.

^4Therefore they that were scattered abroad went every where preaching the word.

^5Then Philip went down to the city of Samaria, and preached Christ unto them.

^6And the people with one accord gave heed unto those things which Philip spake, hearing and seeing the miracles which he did.

^7For unclean spirits, crying with loud voice, came out of many that were possessed with them: and many taken with palsies, and that were lame, were healed.

^8And there was great joy in that city.

^9But there was a certain man, called Simon, which beforetime in the same city used sorcery, and bewitched the people of Samaria, giving out that himself was some great one:

^10To whom they all gave heed, from the least to the greatest, saying, This man is the great power of God.

^11And to him they had regard, because that of long time he had bewitched them with sorceries.

^12But when they believed Philip preaching the things concerning the kingdom of God, and the name of Jesus Christ, they were baptized, both men and women.

^13Then Simon himself believed also: and when he was baptized, he continued with Philip, and wondered, beholding the miracles and signs which were done.

^14Now when the apostles which were at Jerusalem heard that Samaria had received the word of God, they sent unto them Peter and John:

^15Who, when they were come down, prayed for them, that they might receive the Holy Ghost:

^16(For as yet he was fallen upon none of them: only they were baptized in the name of the Lord Jesus.)

^17Then laid they their hands on them, and they received the Holy Ghost.

^18And when Simon saw that through laying on of the apostles’ hands the Holy Ghost was given, he offered them money,

^19Saying, Give me also this power, that on whomsoever I lay hands, he may receive the Holy Ghost.

^20But Peter said unto him, Thy money perish with thee, because thou hast thought that the gift of God may be purchased with money.

^21Thou hast neither part nor lot in this matter: for thy heart is not right in the sight of God.

^22Repent therefore of this thy wickedness, and pray God, if perhaps the thought of thine heart may be forgiven thee.

^23For I perceive that thou art in the gall of bitterness, and in the bond of iniquity.

^24Then answered Simon, and said, Pray ye to the Lord for me, that none of these things which ye have spoken come upon me.

^25And they, when they had testified and preached the word of the Lord, returned to Jerusalem, and preached the gospel in many villages of the Samaritans.

^26And the angel of the Lord spake unto Philip, saying, Arise, and go toward the south unto the way that goeth down from Jerusalem unto Gaza, which is desert.

^27And he arose and went: and, behold, a man of Ethiopia, an eunuch of great authority under Candace queen of the Ethiopians, who had the charge of all her treasure, and had come to Jerusalem for to worship,

^28Was returning, and sitting in his chariot read Esaias the prophet.

^29Then the Spirit said unto Philip, Go near, and join thyself to this chariot.

^30And Philip ran thither to him, and heard him read the prophet Esaias, and said, Understandest thou what thou readest?

^31And he said, How can I, except some man should guide me? And he desired Philip that he would come up and sit with him.

^32The place of the scripture which he read was this, He was led as a sheep to the slaughter; and like a lamb dumb before his shearer, so opened he not his mouth:

^33In his humiliation his judgment was taken away: and who shall declare his generation? for his life is taken from the earth.

^34And the eunuch answered Philip, and said, I pray thee, of whom speaketh the prophet this? of himself, or of some other man?

^35Then Philip opened his mouth, and began at the same scripture, and preached unto him Jesus.

^36And as they went on their way, they came unto a certain water: and the eunuch said, See, here is water; what doth hinder me to be baptized?

^37And Philip said, If thou believest with all thine heart, thou mayest. And he answered and said, I believe that Jesus Christ is the Son of God.

^38And he commanded the chariot to stand still: and they went down both into the water, both Philip and the eunuch; and he baptized him.

^39And when they were come up out of the water, the Spirit of the Lord caught away Philip, that the eunuch saw him no more: and he went on his way rejoicing.

^40But Philip was found at Azotus: and passing through he preached in all the cities, till he came to Caesarea.

Acts 9

9^1And Saul, yet breathing out threatenings and slaughter against the disciples of the Lord, went unto the high priest,

^2And desired of him letters to Damascus to the synagogues, that if he found any of this way, whether they were men or women, he might bring them bound unto Jerusalem.

^3And as he journeyed, he came near Damascus: and suddenly there shined round about him a light from heaven:

^4And he fell to the earth, and heard a voice saying unto him, Saul, Saul, why persecutest thou me?

^5And he said, Who art thou, Lord? And the Lord said, I am Jesus whom thou persecutest: it is hard for thee to kick against the pricks.

^6And he trembling and astonished said, Lord, what wilt thou have me to do? And the Lord said unto him, Arise, and go into the city, and it shall be told thee what thou must do.

^7And the men which journeyed with him stood speechless, hearing a voice, but seeing no man.

^8And Saul arose from the earth; and when his eyes were opened, he saw no man: but they led him by the hand, and brought him into Damascus.

^9And he was three days without sight, and neither did eat nor drink.

^10And there was a certain disciple at Damascus, named Ananias; and to him said the Lord in a vision, Ananias. And he said, Behold, I am here, Lord.

^11And the Lord said unto him, Arise, and go into the street which is called Straight, and enquire in the house of Judas for one called Saul, of Tarsus: for, behold, he prayeth,

^12And hath seen in a vision a man named Ananias coming in, and putting his hand on him, that he might receive his sight.

^13Then Ananias answered, Lord, I have heard by many of this man, how much evil he hath done to thy saints at Jerusalem:

^14And here he hath authority from the chief priests to bind all that call on thy name.

^15But the Lord said unto him, Go thy way: for he is a chosen vessel unto me, to bear my name before the Gentiles, and kings, and the children of Israel:

^16For I will shew him how great things he must suffer for my name’s sake.

^17And Ananias went his way, and entered into the house; and putting his hands on him said, Brother Saul, the Lord, even Jesus, that appeared unto thee in the way as thou camest, hath sent me, that thou mightest receive thy sight, and be filled with the Holy Ghost.

^18And immediately there fell from his eyes as it had been scales: and he received sight forthwith, and arose, and was baptized.

^19And when he had received meat, he was strengthened. Then was Saul certain days with the disciples which were at Damascus.

^20And straightway he preached Christ in the synagogues, that he is the Son of God.

^21But all that heard him were amazed, and said; Is not this he that destroyed them which called on this name in Jerusalem, and came hither for that intent, that he might bring them bound unto the chief priests?

^22But Saul increased the more in strength, and confounded the Jews which dwelt at Damascus, proving that this is very Christ.

^23And after that many days were fulfilled, the Jews took counsel to kill him:

^24But their laying await was known of Saul. And they watched the gates day and night to kill him.

^25Then the disciples took him by night, and let him down by the wall in a basket.

^26And when Saul was come to Jerusalem, he assayed to join himself to the disciples: but they were all afraid of him, and believed not that he was a disciple.

^27But Barnabas took him, and brought him to the apostles, and declared unto them how he had seen the Lord in the way, and that he had spoken to him, and how he had preached boldly at Damascus in the name of Jesus.

^28And he was with them coming in and going out at Jerusalem.

^29And he spake boldly in the name of the Lord Jesus, and disputed against the Grecians: but they went about to slay him.

^30Which when the brethren knew, they brought him down to Caesarea, and sent him forth to Tarsus.

^31Then had the churches rest throughout all Judaea and Galilee and Samaria, and were edified; and walking in the fear of the Lord, and in the comfort of the Holy Ghost, were multiplied.

^32And it came to pass, as Peter passed throughout all quarters, he came down also to the saints which dwelt at Lydda.

^33And there he found a certain man named Aeneas, which had kept his bed eight years, and was sick of the palsy.

^34And Peter said unto him, Aeneas, Jesus Christ maketh thee whole: arise, and make thy bed. And he arose immediately.

^35And all that dwelt at Lydda and Saron saw him, and turned to the Lord.

^36Now there was at Joppa a certain disciple named Tabitha, which by interpretation is called Dorcas: this woman was full of good works and almsdeeds which she did.

^37And it came to pass in those days, that she was sick, and died: whom when they had washed, they laid her in an upper chamber.

^38And forasmuch as Lydda was nigh to Joppa, and the disciples had heard that Peter was there, they sent unto him two men, desiring him that he would not delay to come to them.

^39Then Peter arose and went with them. When he was come, they brought him into the upper chamber: and all the widows stood by him weeping, and shewing the coats and garments which Dorcas made, while she was with them.

^40But Peter put them all forth, and kneeled down, and prayed; and turning him to the body said, Tabitha, arise. And she opened her eyes: and when she saw Peter, she sat up.

^41And he gave her his hand, and lifted her up, and when he had called the saints and widows, presented her alive.

^42And it was known throughout all Joppa; and many believed in the Lord.

^43And it came to pass, that he tarried many days in Joppa with one Simon a tanner.

Acts 10

10^1There was a certain man in Caesarea called Cornelius, a centurion of the band called the Italian band,

^2A devout man, and one that feared God with all his house, which gave much alms to the people, and prayed to God alway.

^3He saw in a vision evidently about the ninth hour of the day an angel of God coming in to him, and saying unto him, Cornelius.

^4And when he looked on him, he was afraid, and said, What is it, Lord? And he said unto him, Thy prayers and thine alms are come up for a memorial before God.

^5And now send men to Joppa, and call for one Simon, whose surname is Peter:

^6He lodgeth with one Simon a tanner, whose house is by the sea side: he shall tell thee what thou oughtest to do.

^7And when the angel which spake unto Cornelius was departed, he called two of his household servants, and a devout soldier of them that waited on him continually;

^8And when he had declared all these things unto them, he sent them to Joppa.

^9On the morrow, as they went on their journey, and drew nigh unto the city, Peter went up upon the housetop to pray about the sixth hour:

^10And he became very hungry, and would have eaten: but while they made ready, he fell into a trance,

^11And saw heaven opened, and a certain vessel descending upon him, as it had been a great sheet knit at the four corners, and let down to the earth:

^12Wherein were all manner of fourfooted beasts of the earth, and wild beasts, and creeping things, and fowls of the air.

^13And there came a voice to him, Rise, Peter; kill, and eat.

^14But Peter said, Not so, Lord; for I have never eaten any thing that is common or unclean.

^15And the voice spake unto him again the second time, What God hath cleansed, that call not thou common.

^16This was done thrice: and the vessel was received up again into heaven.

^17Now while Peter doubted in himself what this vision which he had seen should mean, behold, the men which were sent from Cornelius had made enquiry for Simon’s house, and stood before the gate,

^18And called, and asked whether Simon, which was surnamed Peter, were lodged there.

^19While Peter thought on the vision, the Spirit said unto him, Behold, three men seek thee.

^20Arise therefore, and get thee down, and go with them, doubting nothing: for I have sent them.

^21Then Peter went down to the men which were sent unto him from Cornelius; and said, Behold, I am he whom ye seek: what is the cause wherefore ye are come?

^22And they said, Cornelius the centurion, a just man, and one that feareth God, and of good report among all the nation of the Jews, was warned from God by an holy angel to send for thee into his house, and to hear words of thee.

^23Then called he them in, and lodged them. And on the morrow Peter went away with them, and certain brethren from Joppa accompanied him.

^24And the morrow after they entered into Caesarea. And Cornelius waited for them, and he had called together his kinsmen and near friends.

^25And as Peter was coming in, Cornelius met him, and fell down at his feet, and worshipped him.

^26But Peter took him up, saying, Stand up; I myself also am a man.

^27And as he talked with him, he went in, and found many that were come together.

^28And he said unto them, Ye know how that it is an unlawful thing for a man that is a Jew to keep company, or come unto one of another nation; but God hath shewed me that I should not call any man common or unclean.

^29Therefore came I unto you without gainsaying, as soon as I was sent for: I ask therefore for what intent ye have sent for me?

^30And Cornelius said, Four days ago I was fasting until this hour; and at the ninth hour I prayed in my house, and, behold, a man stood before me in bright clothing,

^31And said, Cornelius, thy prayer is heard, and thine alms are had in remembrance in the sight of God.

^32Send therefore to Joppa, and call hither Simon, whose surname is Peter; he is lodged in the house of one Simon a tanner by the sea side: who, when he cometh, shall speak unto thee.

^33Immediately therefore I sent to thee; and thou hast well done that thou art come. Now therefore are we all here present before God, to hear all things that are commanded thee of God.

^34Then Peter opened his mouth, and said, Of a truth I perceive that God is no respecter of persons:

^35But in every nation he that feareth him, and worketh righteousness, is accepted with him.

^36The word which God sent unto the children of Israel, preaching peace by Jesus Christ: (he is Lord of all:)

^37That word, I say, ye know, which was published throughout all Judaea, and began from Galilee, after the baptism which John preached;

^38How God anointed Jesus of Nazareth with the Holy Ghost and with power: who went about doing good, and healing all that were oppressed of the devil; for God was with him.

^39And we are witnesses of all things which he did both in the land of the Jews, and in Jerusalem; whom they slew and hanged on a tree:

^40Him God raised up the third day, and shewed him openly;

^41Not to all the people, but unto witnesses chosen before God, even to us, who did eat and drink with him after he rose from the dead.

^42And he commanded us to preach unto the people, and to testify that it is he which was ordained of God to be the Judge of quick and dead.

^43To him give all the prophets witness, that through his name whosoever believeth in him shall receive remission of sins.

^44While Peter yet spake these words, the Holy Ghost fell on all them which heard the word.

^45And they of the circumcision which believed were astonished, as many as came with Peter, because that on the Gentiles also was poured out the gift of the Holy Ghost.

^46For they heard them speak with tongues, and magnify God. Then answered Peter,

^47Can any man forbid water, that these should not be baptized, which have received the Holy Ghost as well as we?

^48And he commanded them to be baptized in the name of the Lord. Then prayed they him to tarry certain days.

Acts 11

11^1And the apostles and brethren that were in Judaea heard that the Gentiles had also received the word of God.

^2And when Peter was come up to Jerusalem, they that were of the circumcision contended with him,

^3Saying, Thou wentest in to men uncircumcised, and didst eat with them.

^4But Peter rehearsed the matter from the beginning, and expounded it by order unto them, saying,

^5I was in the city of Joppa praying: and in a trance I saw a vision, A certain vessel descend, as it had been a great sheet, let down from heaven by four corners; and it came even to me:

^6Upon the which when I had fastened mine eyes, I considered, and saw fourfooted beasts of the earth, and wild beasts, and creeping things, and fowls of the air.

^7And I heard a voice saying unto me, Arise, Peter; slay and eat.

^8But I said, Not so, Lord: for nothing common or unclean hath at any time entered into my mouth.

^9But the voice answered me again from heaven, What God hath cleansed, that call not thou common.

^10And this was done three times: and all were drawn up again into heaven.

^11And, behold, immediately there were three men already come unto the house where I was, sent from Caesarea unto me.

^12And the Spirit bade me go with them, nothing doubting. Moreover these six brethren accompanied me, and we entered into the man’s house:

^13And he shewed us how he had seen an angel in his house, which stood and said unto him, Send men to Joppa, and call for Simon, whose surname is Peter;

^14Who shall tell thee words, whereby thou and all thy house shall be saved.

^15And as I began to speak, the Holy Ghost fell on them, as on us at the beginning.

^16Then remembered I the word of the Lord, how that he said, John indeed baptized with water; but ye shall be baptized with the Holy Ghost.

^17Forasmuch then as God gave them the like gift as he did unto us, who believed on the Lord Jesus Christ; what was I, that I could withstand God?

^18When they heard these things, they held their peace, and glorified God, saying, Then hath God also to the Gentiles granted repentance unto life.

^19Now they which were scattered abroad upon the persecution that arose about Stephen travelled as far as Phenice, and Cyprus, and Antioch, preaching the word to none but unto the Jews only.

^20And some of them were men of Cyprus and Cyrene, which, when they were come to Antioch, spake unto the Grecians, preaching the Lord Jesus.

^21And the hand of the Lord was with them: and a great number believed, and turned unto the Lord.

^22Then tidings of these things came unto the ears of the church which was in Jerusalem: and they sent forth Barnabas, that he should go as far as Antioch.

^23Who, when he came, and had seen the grace of God, was glad, and exhorted them all, that with purpose of heart they would cleave unto the Lord.

^24For he was a good man, and full of the Holy Ghost and of faith: and much people was added unto the Lord.

^25Then departed Barnabas to Tarsus, for to seek Saul:

^26And when he had found him, he brought him unto Antioch. And it came to pass, that a whole year they assembled themselves with the church, and taught much people. And the disciples were called Christians first in Antioch.

^27And in these days came prophets from Jerusalem unto Antioch.

^28And there stood up one of them named Agabus, and signified by the Spirit that there should be great dearth throughout all the world: which came to pass in the days of Claudius Caesar.

^29Then the disciples, every man according to his ability, determined to send relief unto the brethren which dwelt in Judaea:

^30Which also they did, and sent it to the elders by the hands of Barnabas and Saul.

Acts 12

12^1Now about that time Herod the king stretched forth his hands to vex certain of the church.

^2And he killed James the brother of John with the sword.

^3And because he saw it pleased the Jews, he proceeded further to take Peter also. (Then were the days of unleavened bread.)

^4And when he had apprehended him, he put him in prison, and delivered him to four quaternions of soldiers to keep him; intending after Easter to bring him forth to the people.

^5Peter therefore was kept in prison: but prayer was made without ceasing of the church unto God for him.

^6And when Herod would have brought him forth, the same night Peter was sleeping between two soldiers, bound with two chains: and the keepers before the door kept the prison.

^7And, behold, the angel of the Lord came upon him, and a light shined in the prison: and he smote Peter on the side, and raised him up, saying, Arise up quickly. And his chains fell off from his hands.

^8And the angel said unto him, Gird thyself, and bind on thy sandals. And so he did. And he saith unto him, Cast thy garment about thee, and follow me.

^9And he went out, and followed him; and wist not that it was true which was done by the angel; but thought he saw a vision.

^10When they were past the first and the second ward, they came unto the iron gate that leadeth unto the city; which opened to them of his own accord: and they went out, and passed on through one street; and forthwith the angel departed from him.

^11And when Peter was come to himself, he said, Now I know of a surety, that the Lord hath sent his angel, and hath delivered me out of the hand of Herod, and from all the expectation of the people of the Jews.

^12And when he had considered the thing, he came to the house of Mary the mother of John, whose surname was Mark; where many were gathered together praying.

^13And as Peter knocked at the door of the gate, a damsel came to hearken, named Rhoda.

^14And when she knew Peter’s voice, she opened not the gate for gladness, but ran in, and told how Peter stood before the gate.

^15And they said unto her, Thou art mad. But she constantly affirmed that it was even so. Then said they, It is his angel.

^16But Peter continued knocking: and when they had opened the door, and saw him, they were astonished.

^17But he, beckoning unto them with the hand to hold their peace, declared unto them how the Lord had brought him out of the prison. And he said, Go shew these things unto James, and to the brethren. And he departed, and went into another place.

^18Now as soon as it was day, there was no small stir among the soldiers, what was become of Peter.

^19And when Herod had sought for him, and found him not, he examined the keepers, and commanded that they should be put to death. And he went down from Judaea to Caesarea, and there abode.

^20And Herod was highly displeased with them of Tyre and Sidon: but they came with one accord to him, and, having made Blastus the king’s chamberlain their friend, desired peace; because their country was nourished by the king’s country.

^21And upon a set day Herod, arrayed in royal apparel, sat upon his throne, and made an oration unto them.

^22And the people gave a shout, saying, It is the voice of a god, and not of a man.

^23And immediately the angel of the Lord smote him, because he gave not God the glory: and he was eaten of worms, and gave up the ghost.

^24But the word of God grew and multiplied.

^25And Barnabas and Saul returned from Jerusalem, when they had fulfilled their ministry, and took with them John, whose surname was Mark.

Acts 13

13^1Now there were in the church that was at Antioch certain prophets and teachers; as Barnabas, and Simeon that was called Niger, and Lucius of Cyrene, and Manaen, which had been brought up with Herod the tetrarch, and Saul.

^2As they ministered to the Lord, and fasted, the Holy Ghost said, Separate me Barnabas and Saul for the work whereunto I have called them.

^3And when they had fasted and prayed, and laid their hands on them, they sent them away.

^4So they, being sent forth by the Holy Ghost, departed unto Seleucia; and from thence they sailed to Cyprus.

^5And when they were at Salamis, they preached the word of God in the synagogues of the Jews: and they had also John to their minister.

^6And when they had gone through the isle unto Paphos, they found a certain sorcerer, a false prophet, a Jew, whose name was Barjesus:

^7Which was with the deputy of the country, Sergius Paulus, a prudent man; who called for Barnabas and Saul, and desired to hear the word of God.

^8But Elymas the sorcerer (for so is his name by interpretation) withstood them, seeking to turn away the deputy from the faith.

^9Then Saul, (who also is called Paul,) filled with the Holy Ghost, set his eyes on him.

^10And said, O full of all subtilty and all mischief, thou child of the devil, thou enemy of all righteousness, wilt thou not cease to pervert the right ways of the Lord?

^11And now, behold, the hand of the Lord is upon thee, and thou shalt be blind, not seeing the sun for a season. And immediately there fell on him a mist and a darkness; and he went about seeking some to lead him by the hand.

^12Then the deputy, when he saw what was done, believed, being astonished at the doctrine of the Lord.

^13Now when Paul and his company loosed from Paphos, they came to Perga in Pamphylia: and John departing from them returned to Jerusalem.

^14But when they departed from Perga, they came to Antioch in Pisidia, and went into the synagogue on the sabbath day, and sat down.

^15And after the reading of the law and the prophets the rulers of the synagogue sent unto them, saying, Ye men and brethren, if ye have any word of exhortation for the people, say on.

^16Then Paul stood up, and beckoning with his hand said, Men of Israel, and ye that fear God, give audience.

^17The God of this people of Israel chose our fathers, and exalted the people when they dwelt as strangers in the land of Egypt, and with an high arm brought he them out of it.

^18And about the time of forty years suffered he their manners in the wilderness.

^19And when he had destroyed seven nations in the land of Chanaan, he divided their land to them by lot.

^20And after that he gave unto them judges about the space of four hundred and fifty years, until Samuel the prophet.

^21And afterward they desired a king: and God gave unto them Saul the son of Cis, a man of the tribe of Benjamin, by the space of forty years.

^22And when he had removed him, he raised up unto them David to be their king; to whom also he gave their testimony, and said, I have found David the son of Jesse, a man after mine own heart, which shall fulfil all my will.

^23Of this man’s seed hath God according to his promise raised unto Israel a Saviour, Jesus:

^24When John had first preached before his coming the baptism of repentance to all the people of Israel.

^25And as John fulfilled his course, he said, Whom think ye that I am? I am not he. But, behold, there cometh one after me, whose shoes of his feet I am not worthy to loose.

^26Men and brethren, children of the stock of Abraham, and whosoever among you feareth God, to you is the word of this salvation sent.

^27For they that dwell at Jerusalem, and their rulers, because they knew him not, nor yet the voices of the prophets which are read every sabbath day, they have fulfilled them in condemning him.

^28And though they found no cause of death in him, yet desired they Pilate that he should be slain.

^29And when they had fulfilled all that was written of him, they took him down from the tree, and laid him in a sepulchre.

^30But God raised him from the dead:

^31And he was seen many days of them which came up with him from Galilee to Jerusalem, who are his witnesses unto the people.

^32And we declare unto you glad tidings, how that the promise which was made unto the fathers,

^33God hath fulfilled the same unto us their children, in that he hath raised up Jesus again; as it is also written in the second psalm, Thou art my Son, this day have I begotten thee.

^34And as concerning that he raised him up from the dead, now no more to return to corruption, he said on this wise, I will give you the sure mercies of David.

^35Wherefore he saith also in another psalm, Thou shalt not suffer thine Holy One to see corruption.

^36For David, after he had served his own generation by the will of God, fell on sleep, and was laid unto his fathers, and saw corruption:

^37But he, whom God raised again, saw no corruption.

^38Be it known unto you therefore, men and brethren, that through this man is preached unto you the forgiveness of sins:

^39And by him all that believe are justified from all things, from which ye could not be justified by the law of Moses.

^40Beware therefore, lest that come upon you, which is spoken of in the prophets;

^41Behold, ye despisers, and wonder, and perish: for I work a work in your days, a work which ye shall in no wise believe, though a man declare it unto you.

^42And when the Jews were gone out of the synagogue, the Gentiles besought that these words might be preached to them the next sabbath.

^43Now when the congregation was broken up, many of the Jews and religious proselytes followed Paul and Barnabas: who, speaking to them, persuaded them to continue in the grace of God.

^44And the next sabbath day came almost the whole city together to hear the word of God.

^45But when the Jews saw the multitudes, they were filled with envy, and spake against those things which were spoken by Paul, contradicting and blaspheming.

^46Then Paul and Barnabas waxed bold, and said, It was necessary that the word of God should first have been spoken to you: but seeing ye put it from you, and judge yourselves unworthy of everlasting life, lo, we turn to the Gentiles.

^47For so hath the Lord commanded us, saying, I have set thee to be a light of the Gentiles, that thou shouldest be for salvation unto the ends of the earth.

^48And when the Gentiles heard this, they were glad, and glorified the word of the Lord: and as many as were ordained to eternal life believed.

^49And the word of the Lord was published throughout all the region.

^50But the Jews stirred up the devout and honourable women, and the chief men of the city, and raised persecution against Paul and Barnabas, and expelled them out of their coasts.

^51But they shook off the dust of their feet against them, and came unto Iconium.

^52And the disciples were filled with joy, and with the Holy Ghost.

Acts 14

14^1And it came to pass in Iconium, that they went both together into the synagogue of the Jews, and so spake, that a great multitude both of the Jews and also of the Greeks believed.

^2But the unbelieving Jews stirred up the Gentiles, and made their minds evil affected against the brethren.

^3Long time therefore abode they speaking boldly in the Lord, which gave testimony unto the word of his grace, and granted signs and wonders to be done by their hands.

^4But the multitude of the city was divided: and part held with the Jews, and part with the apostles.

^5And when there was an assault made both of the Gentiles, and also of the Jews with their rulers, to use them despitefully, and to stone them,

^6They were ware of it, and fled unto Lystra and Derbe, cities of Lycaonia, and unto the region that lieth round about:

^7And there they preached the gospel.

^8And there sat a certain man at Lystra, impotent in his feet, being a cripple from his mother’s womb, who never had walked:

^9The same heard Paul speak: who stedfastly beholding him, and perceiving that he had faith to be healed,

^10Said with a loud voice, Stand upright on thy feet. And he leaped and walked.

^11And when the people saw what Paul had done, they lifted up their voices, saying in the speech of Lycaonia, The gods are come down to us in the likeness of men.

^12And they called Barnabas, Jupiter; and Paul, Mercurius, because he was the chief speaker.

^13Then the priest of Jupiter, which was before their city, brought oxen and garlands unto the gates, and would have done sacrifice with the people.

^14Which when the apostles, Barnabas and Paul, heard of, they rent their clothes, and ran in among the people, crying out,

^15And saying, Sirs, why do ye these things? We also are men of like passions with you, and preach unto you that ye should turn from these vanities unto the living God, which made heaven, and earth, and the sea, and all things that are therein:

^16Who in times past suffered all nations to walk in their own ways.

^17Nevertheless he left not himself without witness, in that he did good, and gave us rain from heaven, and fruitful seasons, filling our hearts with food and gladness.

^18And with these sayings scarce restrained they the people, that they had not done sacrifice unto them.

^19And there came thither certain Jews from Antioch and Iconium, who persuaded the people, and having stoned Paul, drew him out of the city, supposing he had been dead.

^20Howbeit, as the disciples stood round about him, he rose up, and came into the city: and the next day he departed with Barnabas to Derbe.

^21And when they had preached the gospel to that city, and had taught many, they returned again to Lystra, and to Iconium, and Antioch,

^22Confirming the souls of the disciples, and exhorting them to continue in the faith, and that we must through much tribulation enter into the kingdom of God.

^23And when they had ordained them elders in every church, and had prayed with fasting, they commended them to the Lord, on whom they believed.

^24And after they had passed throughout Pisidia, they came to Pamphylia.

^25And when they had preached the word in Perga, they went down into Attalia:

^26And thence sailed to Antioch, from whence they had been recommended to the grace of God for the work which they fulfilled.

^27And when they were come, and had gathered the church together, they rehearsed all that God had done with them, and how he had opened the door of faith unto the Gentiles.

^28And there they abode long time with the disciples.

Acts 15

15^1And certain men which came down from Judaea taught the brethren, and said, Except ye be circumcised after the manner of Moses, ye cannot be saved.

^2When therefore Paul and Barnabas had no small dissension and disputation with them, they determined that Paul and Barnabas, and certain other of them, should go up to Jerusalem unto the apostles and elders about this question.

^3And being brought on their way by the church, they passed through Phenice and Samaria, declaring the conversion of the Gentiles: and they caused great joy unto all the brethren.

^4And when they were come to Jerusalem, they were received of the church, and of the apostles and elders, and they declared all things that God had done with them.

^5But there rose up certain of the sect of the Pharisees which believed, saying, That it was needful to circumcise them, and to command them to keep the law of Moses.

^6And the apostles and elders came together for to consider of this matter.

^7And when there had been much disputing, Peter rose up, and said unto them, Men and brethren, ye know how that a good while ago God made choice among us, that the Gentiles by my mouth should hear the word of the gospel, and believe.

^8And God, which knoweth the hearts, bare them witness, giving them the Holy Ghost, even as he did unto us;

^9And put no difference between us and them, purifying their hearts by faith.

^10Now therefore why tempt ye God, to put a yoke upon the neck of the disciples, which neither our fathers nor we were able to bear?

^11But we believe that through the grace of the Lord Jesus Christ we shall be saved, even as they.

^12Then all the multitude kept silence, and gave audience to Barnabas and Paul, declaring what miracles and wonders God had wrought among the Gentiles by them.

^13And after they had held their peace, James answered, saying, Men and brethren, hearken unto me:

^14Simeon hath declared how God at the first did visit the Gentiles, to take out of them a people for his name.

^15And to this agree the words of the prophets; as it is written,

^16After this I will return, and will build again the tabernacle of David, which is fallen down; and I will build again the ruins thereof, and I will set it up:

^17That the residue of men might seek after the Lord, and all the Gentiles, upon whom my name is called, saith the Lord, who doeth all these things.

^18Known unto God are all his works from the beginning of the world.

^19Wherefore my sentence is, that we trouble not them, which from among the Gentiles are turned to God:

^20But that we write unto them, that they abstain from pollutions of idols, and from fornication, and from things strangled, and from blood.

^21For Moses of old time hath in every city them that preach him, being read in the synagogues every sabbath day.

^22Then pleased it the apostles and elders with the whole church, to send chosen men of their own company to Antioch with Paul and Barnabas; namely, Judas surnamed Barsabas and Silas, chief men among the brethren:

^23And they wrote letters by them after this manner; The apostles and elders and brethren send greeting unto the brethren which are of the Gentiles in Antioch and Syria and Cilicia.

^24Forasmuch as we have heard, that certain which went out from us have troubled you with words, subverting your souls, saying, Ye must be circumcised, and keep the law: to whom we gave no such commandment:

^25It seemed good unto us, being assembled with one accord, to send chosen men unto you with our beloved Barnabas and Paul,

^26Men that have hazarded their lives for the name of our Lord Jesus Christ.

^27We have sent therefore Judas and Silas, who shall also tell you the same things by mouth.

^28For it seemed good to the Holy Ghost, and to us, to lay upon you no greater burden than these necessary things;

^29That ye abstain from meats offered to idols, and from blood, and from things strangled, and from fornication: from which if ye keep yourselves, ye shall do well. Fare ye well.

^30So when they were dismissed, they came to Antioch: and when they had gathered the multitude together, they delivered the epistle:

^31Which when they had read, they rejoiced for the consolation.

^32And Judas and Silas, being prophets also themselves, exhorted the brethren with many words, and confirmed them.

^33And after they had tarried there a space, they were let go in peace from the brethren unto the apostles.

^34Notwithstanding it pleased Silas to abide there still.

^35Paul also and Barnabas continued in Antioch, teaching and preaching the word of the Lord, with many others also.

^36And some days after Paul said unto Barnabas, Let us go again and visit our brethren in every city where we have preached the word of the Lord, and see how they do.

^37And Barnabas determined to take with them John, whose surname was Mark.

^38But Paul thought not good to take him with them, who departed from them from Pamphylia, and went not with them to the work.

^39And the contention was so sharp between them, that they departed asunder one from the other: and so Barnabas took Mark, and sailed unto Cyprus;

^40And Paul chose Silas, and departed, being recommended by the brethren unto the grace of God.

^41And he went through Syria and Cilicia, confirming the churches.

Acts 16

16^1Then came he to Derbe and Lystra: and, behold, a certain disciple was there, named Timotheus, the son of a certain woman, which was a Jewess, and believed; but his father was a Greek:

^2Which was well reported of by the brethren that were at Lystra and Iconium.

^3Him would Paul have to go forth with him; and took and circumcised him because of the Jews which were in those quarters: for they knew all that his father was a Greek.

^4And as they went through the cities, they delivered them the decrees for to keep, that were ordained of the apostles and elders which were at Jerusalem.

^5And so were the churches established in the faith, and increased in number daily.

^6Now when they had gone throughout Phrygia and the region of Galatia, and were forbidden of the Holy Ghost to preach the word in Asia,

^7After they were come to Mysia, they assayed to go into Bithynia: but the Spirit suffered them not.

^8And they passing by Mysia came down to Troas.

^9And a vision appeared to Paul in the night; There stood a man of Macedonia, and prayed him, saying, Come over into Macedonia, and help us.

^10And after he had seen the vision, immediately we endeavoured to go into Macedonia, assuredly gathering that the Lord had called us for to preach the gospel unto them.

^11Therefore loosing from Troas, we came with a straight course to Samothracia, and the next day to Neapolis;

^12And from thence to Philippi, which is the chief city of that part of Macedonia, and a colony: and we were in that city abiding certain days.

^13And on the sabbath we went out of the city by a river side, where prayer was wont to be made; and we sat down, and spake unto the women which resorted thither.

^14And a certain woman named Lydia, a seller of purple, of the city of Thyatira, which worshipped God, heard us: whose heart the Lord opened, that she attended unto the things which were spoken of Paul.

^15And when she was baptized, and her household, she besought us, saying, If ye have judged me to be faithful to the Lord, come into my house, and abide there. And she constrained us.

^16And it came to pass, as we went to prayer, a certain damsel possessed with a spirit of divination met us, which brought her masters much gain by soothsaying:

^17The same followed Paul and us, and cried, saying, These men are the servants of the most high God, which shew unto us the way of salvation.

^18And this did she many days. But Paul, being grieved, turned and said to the spirit, I command thee in the name of Jesus Christ to come out of her. And he came out the same hour.

^19And when her masters saw that the hope of their gains was gone, they caught Paul and Silas, and drew them into the marketplace unto the rulers,

^20And brought them to the magistrates, saying, These men, being Jews, do exceedingly trouble our city,

^21And teach customs, which are not lawful for us to receive, neither to observe, being Romans.

^22And the multitude rose up together against them: and the magistrates rent off their clothes, and commanded to beat them.

^23And when they had laid many stripes upon them, they cast them into prison, charging the jailor to keep them safely:

^24Who, having received such a charge, thrust them into the inner prison, and made their feet fast in the stocks.

^25And at midnight Paul and Silas prayed, and sang praises unto God: and the prisoners heard them.

^26And suddenly there was a great earthquake, so that the foundations of the prison were shaken: and immediately all the doors were opened, and every one’s bands were loosed.

^27And the keeper of the prison awaking out of his sleep, and seeing the prison doors open, he drew out his sword, and would have killed himself, supposing that the prisoners had been fled.

^28But Paul cried with a loud voice, saying, Do thyself no harm: for we are all here.

^29Then he called for a light, and sprang in, and came trembling, and fell down before Paul and Silas,

^30And brought them out, and said, Sirs, what must I do to be saved?

^31And they said, Believe on the Lord Jesus Christ, and thou shalt be saved, and thy house.

^32And they spake unto him the word of the Lord, and to all that were in his house.

^33And he took them the same hour of the night, and washed their stripes; and was baptized, he and all his, straightway.

^34And when he had brought them into his house, he set meat before them, and rejoiced, believing in God with all his house.

^35And when it was day, the magistrates sent the serjeants, saying, Let those men go.

^36And the keeper of the prison told this saying to Paul, The magistrates have sent to let you go: now therefore depart, and go in peace.

^37But Paul said unto them, They have beaten us openly uncondemned, being Romans, and have cast us into prison; and now do they thrust us out privily? nay verily; but let them come themselves and fetch us out.

^38And the serjeants told these words unto the magistrates: and they feared, when they heard that they were Romans.

^39And they came and besought them, and brought them out, and desired them to depart out of the city.

^40And they went out of the prison, and entered into the house of Lydia: and when they had seen the brethren, they comforted them, and departed.

Acts 17

17^1Now when they had passed through Amphipolis and Apollonia, they came to Thessalonica, where was a synagogue of the Jews:

^2And Paul, as his manner was, went in unto them, and three sabbath days reasoned with them out of the scriptures,

^3Opening and alleging, that Christ must needs have suffered, and risen again from the dead; and that this Jesus, whom I preach unto you, is Christ.

^4And some of them believed, and consorted with Paul and Silas; and of the devout Greeks a great multitude, and of the chief women not a few.

^5But the Jews which believed not, moved with envy, took unto them certain lewd fellows of the baser sort, and gathered a company, and set all the city on an uproar, and assaulted the house of Jason, and sought to bring them out to the people.

^6And when they found them not, they drew Jason and certain brethren unto the rulers of the city, crying, These that have turned the world upside down are come hither also;

^7Whom Jason hath received: and these all do contrary to the decrees of Caesar, saying that there is another king, one Jesus.

^8And they troubled the people and the rulers of the city, when they heard these things.

^9And when they had taken security of Jason, and of the other, they let them go.

^10And the brethren immediately sent away Paul and Silas by night unto Berea: who coming thither went into the synagogue of the Jews.

^11These were more noble than those in Thessalonica, in that they received the word with all readiness of mind, and searched the scriptures daily, whether those things were so.

^12Therefore many of them believed; also of honourable women which were Greeks, and of men, not a few.

^13But when the Jews of Thessalonica had knowledge that the word of God was preached of Paul at Berea, they came thither also, and stirred up the people.

^14And then immediately the brethren sent away Paul to go as it were to the sea: but Silas and Timotheus abode there still.

^15And they that conducted Paul brought him unto Athens: and receiving a commandment unto Silas and Timotheus for to come to him with all speed, they departed.

^16Now while Paul waited for them at Athens, his spirit was stirred in him, when he saw the city wholly given to idolatry.

^17Therefore disputed he in the synagogue with the Jews, and with the devout persons, and in the market daily with them that met with him.

^18Then certain philosophers of the Epicureans, and of the Stoicks, encountered him. And some said, What will this babbler say? other some, He seemeth to be a setter forth of strange gods: because he preached unto them Jesus, and the resurrection.

^19And they took him, and brought him unto Areopagus, saying, May we know what this new doctrine, whereof thou speakest, is?

^20For thou bringest certain strange things to our ears: we would know therefore what these things mean.

^21(For all the Athenians and strangers which were there spent their time in nothing else, but either to tell, or to hear some new thing.)

^22Then Paul stood in the midst of Mars’ hill, and said, Ye men of Athens, I perceive that in all things ye are too superstitious.

^23For as I passed by, and beheld your devotions, I found an altar with this inscription, To the Unknown God. Whom therefore ye ignorantly worship, him declare I unto you.

^24God that made the world and all things therein, seeing that he is Lord of heaven and earth, dwelleth not in temples made with hands;

^25Neither is worshipped with men’s hands, as though he needed any thing, seeing he giveth to all life, and breath, and all things;

^26And hath made of one blood all nations of men for to dwell on all the face of the earth, and hath determined the times before appointed, and the bounds of their habitation;

^27That they should seek the Lord, if haply they might feel after him, and find him, though he be not far from every one of us:

^28For in him we live, and move, and have our being; as certain also of your own poets have said, For we are also his offspring.

^29Forasmuch then as we are the offspring of God, we ought not to think that the Godhead is like unto gold, or silver, or stone, graven by art and man’s device.

^30And the times of this ignorance God winked at; but now commandeth all men every where to repent:

^31Because he hath appointed a day, in the which he will judge the world in righteousness by that man whom he hath ordained; whereof he hath given assurance unto all men, in that he hath raised him from the dead.

^32And when they heard of the resurrection of the dead, some mocked: and others said, We will hear thee again of this matter.

^33So Paul departed from among them.

^34Howbeit certain men clave unto him, and believed: among the which was Dionysius the Areopagite, and a woman named Damaris, and others with them.

Acts 18

18^1After these things Paul departed from Athens, and came to Corinth;

^2And found a certain Jew named Aquila, born in Pontus, lately come from Italy, with his wife Priscilla; (because that Claudius had commanded all Jews to depart from Rome:) and came unto them.

^3And because he was of the same craft, he abode with them, and wrought: for by their occupation they were tentmakers.

^4And he reasoned in the synagogue every sabbath, and persuaded the Jews and the Greeks.

^5And when Silas and Timotheus were come from Macedonia, Paul was pressed in the spirit, and testified to the Jews that Jesus was Christ.

^6And when they opposed themselves, and blasphemed, he shook his raiment, and said unto them, Your blood be upon your own heads; I am clean; from henceforth I will go unto the Gentiles.

^7And he departed thence, and entered into a certain man’s house, named Justus, one that worshipped God, whose house joined hard to the synagogue.

^8And Crispus, the chief ruler of the synagogue, believed on the Lord with all his house; and many of the Corinthians hearing believed, and were baptized.

^9Then spake the Lord to Paul in the night by a vision, Be not afraid, but speak, and hold not thy peace:

^10For I am with thee, and no man shall set on thee to hurt thee: for I have much people in this city.

^11And he continued there a year and six months, teaching the word of God among them.

^12And when Gallio was the deputy of Achaia, the Jews made insurrection with one accord against Paul, and brought him to the judgment seat,

^13Saying, This fellow persuadeth men to worship God contrary to the law.

^14And when Paul was now about to open his mouth, Gallio said unto the Jews, If it were a matter of wrong or wicked lewdness, O ye Jews, reason would that I should bear with you:

^15But if it be a question of words and names, and of your law, look ye to it; for I will be no judge of such matters.

^16And he drave them from the judgment seat.

^17Then all the Greeks took Sosthenes, the chief ruler of the synagogue, and beat him before the judgment seat. And Gallio cared for none of those things.

^18And Paul after this tarried there yet a good while, and then took his leave of the brethren, and sailed thence into Syria, and with him Priscilla and Aquila; having shorn his head in Cenchrea: for he had a vow.

^19And he came to Ephesus, and left them there: but he himself entered into the synagogue, and reasoned with the Jews.

^20When they desired him to tarry longer time with them, he consented not;

^21But bade them farewell, saying, I must by all means keep this feast that cometh in Jerusalem: but I will return again unto you, if God will. And he sailed from Ephesus.

^22And when he had landed at Caesarea, and gone up, and saluted the church, he went down to Antioch.

^23And after he had spent some time there, he departed, and went over all the country of Galatia and Phrygia in order, strengthening all the disciples.

^24And a certain Jew named Apollos, born at Alexandria, an eloquent man, and mighty in the scriptures, came to Ephesus.

^25This man was instructed in the way of the Lord; and being fervent in the spirit, he spake and taught diligently the things of the Lord, knowing only the baptism of John.

^26And he began to speak boldly in the synagogue: whom when Aquila and Priscilla had heard, they took him unto them, and expounded unto him the way of God more perfectly.

^27And when he was disposed to pass into Achaia, the brethren wrote, exhorting the disciples to receive him: who, when he was come, helped them much which had believed through grace:

^28For he mightily convinced the Jews, and that publickly, shewing by the scriptures that Jesus was Christ.

Acts 19

19^1And it came to pass, that, while Apollos was at Corinth, Paul having passed through the upper coasts came to Ephesus: and finding certain disciples,

^2He said unto them, Have ye received the Holy Ghost since ye believed? And they said unto him, We have not so much as heard whether there be any Holy Ghost.

^3And he said unto them, Unto what then were ye baptized? And they said, Unto John’s baptism.

^4Then said Paul, John verily baptized with the baptism of repentance, saying unto the people, that they should believe on him which should come after him, that is, on Christ Jesus.

^5When they heard this, they were baptized in the name of the Lord Jesus.

^6And when Paul had laid his hands upon them, the Holy Ghost came on them; and they spake with tongues, and prophesied.

^7And all the men were about twelve.

^8And he went into the synagogue, and spake boldly for the space of three months, disputing and persuading the things concerning the kingdom of God.

^9But when divers were hardened, and believed not, but spake evil of that way before the multitude, he departed from them, and separated the disciples, disputing daily in the school of one Tyrannus.

^10And this continued by the space of two years; so that all they which dwelt in Asia heard the word of the Lord Jesus, both Jews and Greeks.

^11And God wrought special miracles by the hands of Paul:

^12So that from his body were brought unto the sick handkerchiefs or aprons, and the diseases departed from them, and the evil spirits went out of them.

^13Then certain of the vagabond Jews, exorcists, took upon them to call over them which had evil spirits the name of the Lord Jesus, saying, We adjure you by Jesus whom Paul preacheth.

^14And there were seven sons of one Sceva, a Jew, and chief of the priests, which did so.

^15And the evil spirit answered and said, Jesus I know, and Paul I know; but who are ye?

^16And the man in whom the evil spirit was leaped on them, and overcame them, and prevailed against them, so that they fled out of that house naked and wounded.

^17And this was known to all the Jews and Greeks also dwelling at Ephesus; and fear fell on them all, and the name of the Lord Jesus was magnified.

^18And many that believed came, and confessed, and shewed their deeds.

^19Many of them also which used curious arts brought their books together, and burned them before all men: and they counted the price of them, and found it fifty thousand pieces of silver.

^20So mightily grew the word of God and prevailed.

^21After these things were ended, Paul purposed in the spirit, when he had passed through Macedonia and Achaia, to go to Jerusalem, saying, After I have been there, I must also see Rome.

^22So he sent into Macedonia two of them that ministered unto him, Timotheus and Erastus; but he himself stayed in Asia for a season.

^23And the same time there arose no small stir about that way.

^24For a certain man named Demetrius, a silversmith, which made silver shrines for Diana, brought no small gain unto the craftsmen;

^25Whom he called together with the workmen of like occupation, and said, Sirs, ye know that by this craft we have our wealth.

^26Moreover ye see and hear, that not alone at Ephesus, but almost throughout all Asia, this Paul hath persuaded and turned away much people, saying that they be no gods, which are made with hands:

^27So that not only this our craft is in danger to be set at nought; but also that the temple of the great goddess Diana should be despised, and her magnificence should be destroyed, whom all Asia and the world worshippeth.

^28And when they heard these sayings, they were full of wrath, and cried out, saying, Great is Diana of the Ephesians.

^29And the whole city was filled with confusion: and having caught Gaius and Aristarchus, men of Macedonia, Paul’s companions in travel, they rushed with one accord into the theatre.

^30And when Paul would have entered in unto the people, the disciples suffered him not.

^31And certain of the chief of Asia, which were his friends, sent unto him, desiring him that he would not adventure himself into the theatre.

^32Some therefore cried one thing, and some another: for the assembly was confused: and the more part knew not wherefore they were come together.

^33And they drew Alexander out of the multitude, the Jews putting him forward. And Alexander beckoned with the hand, and would have made his defence unto the people.

^34But when they knew that he was a Jew, all with one voice about the space of two hours cried out, Great is Diana of the Ephesians.

^35And when the townclerk had appeased the people, he said, Ye men of Ephesus, what man is there that knoweth not how that the city of the Ephesians is a worshipper of the great goddess Diana, and of the image which fell down from Jupiter?

^36Seeing then that these things cannot be spoken against, ye ought to be quiet, and to do nothing rashly.

^37For ye have brought hither these men, which are neither robbers of churches, nor yet blasphemers of your goddess.

^38Wherefore if Demetrius, and the craftsmen which are with him, have a matter against any man, the law is open, and there are deputies: let them implead one another.

^39But if ye enquire any thing concerning other matters, it shall be determined in a lawful assembly.

^40For we are in danger to be called in question for this day’s uproar, there being no cause whereby we may give an account of this concourse.

^41And when he had thus spoken, he dismissed the assembly.

Acts 20

20^1And after the uproar was ceased, Paul called unto him the disciples, and embraced them, and departed for to go into Macedonia.

^2And when he had gone over those parts, and had given them much exhortation, he came into Greece,

^3And there abode three months. And when the Jews laid wait for him, as he was about to sail into Syria, he purposed to return through Macedonia.

^4And there accompanied him into Asia Sopater of Berea; and of the Thessalonians, Aristarchus and Secundus; and Gaius of Derbe, and Timotheus; and of Asia, Tychicus and Trophimus.

^5These going before tarried for us at Troas.

^6And we sailed away from Philippi after the days of unleavened bread, and came unto them to Troas in five days; where we abode seven days.

^7And upon the first day of the week, when the disciples came together to break bread, Paul preached unto them, ready to depart on the morrow; and continued his speech until midnight.

^8And there were many lights in the upper chamber, where they were gathered together.

^9And there sat in a window a certain young man named Eutychus, being fallen into a deep sleep: and as Paul was long preaching, he sunk down with sleep, and fell down from the third loft, and was taken up dead.

^10And Paul went down, and fell on him, and embracing him said, Trouble not yourselves; for his life is in him.

^11When he therefore was come up again, and had broken bread, and eaten, and talked a long while, even till break of day, so he departed.

^12And they brought the young man alive, and were not a little comforted.

^13And we went before to ship, and sailed unto Assos, there intending to take in Paul: for so had he appointed, minding himself to go afoot.

^14And when he met with us at Assos, we took him in, and came to Mitylene.

^15And we sailed thence, and came the next day over against Chios; and the next day we arrived at Samos, and tarried at Trogyllium; and the next day we came to Miletus.

^16For Paul had determined to sail by Ephesus, because he would not spend the time in Asia: for he hasted, if it were possible for him, to be at Jerusalem the day of Pentecost.

^17And from Miletus he sent to Ephesus, and called the elders of the church.

^18And when they were come to him, he said unto them, Ye know, from the first day that I came into Asia, after what manner I have been with you at all seasons,

^19Serving the Lord with all humility of mind, and with many tears, and temptations, which befell me by the lying in wait of the Jews:

^20And how I kept back nothing that was profitable unto you, but have shewed you, and have taught you publickly, and from house to house,

^21Testifying both to the Jews, and also to the Greeks, repentance toward God, and faith toward our Lord Jesus Christ.

^22And now, behold, I go bound in the spirit unto Jerusalem, not knowing the things that shall befall me there:

^23Save that the Holy Ghost witnesseth in every city, saying that bonds and afflictions abide me.

^24But none of these things move me, neither count I my life dear unto myself, so that I might finish my course with joy, and the ministry, which I have received of the Lord Jesus, to testify the gospel of the grace of God.

^25And now, behold, I know that ye all, among whom I have gone preaching the kingdom of God, shall see my face no more.

^26Wherefore I take you to record this day, that I am pure from the blood of all men.

^27For I have not shunned to declare unto you all the counsel of God.

^28Take heed therefore unto yourselves, and to all the flock, over the which the Holy Ghost hath made you overseers, to feed the church of God, which he hath purchased with his own blood.

^29For I know this, that after my departing shall grievous wolves enter in among you, not sparing the flock.

^30Also of your own selves shall men arise, speaking perverse things, to draw away disciples after them.

^31Therefore watch, and remember, that by the space of three years I ceased not to warn every one night and day with tears.

^32And now, brethren, I commend you to God, and to the word of his grace, which is able to build you up, and to give you an inheritance among all them which are sanctified.

^33I have coveted no man’s silver, or gold, or apparel.

^34Yea, ye yourselves know, that these hands have ministered unto my necessities, and to them that were with me.

^35I have shewed you all things, how that so labouring ye ought to support the weak, and to remember the words of the Lord Jesus, how he said, It is more blessed to give than to receive.

^36And when he had thus spoken, he kneeled down, and prayed with them all.

^37And they all wept sore, and fell on Paul’s neck, and kissed him,

^38Sorrowing most of all for the words which he spake, that they should see his face no more. And they accompanied him unto the ship.

Acts 21

21^1And it came to pass, that after we were gotten from them, and had launched, we came with a straight course unto Coos, and the day following unto Rhodes, and from thence unto Patara:

^2And finding a ship sailing over unto Phenicia, we went aboard, and set forth.

^3Now when we had discovered Cyprus, we left it on the left hand, and sailed into Syria, and landed at Tyre: for there the ship was to unlade her burden.

^4And finding disciples, we tarried there seven days: who said to Paul through the Spirit, that he should not go up to Jerusalem.

^5And when we had accomplished those days, we departed and went our way; and they all brought us on our way, with wives and children, till we were out of the city: and we kneeled down on the shore, and prayed.

^6And when we had taken our leave one of another, we took ship; and they returned home again.

^7And when we had finished our course from Tyre, we came to Ptolemais, and saluted the brethren, and abode with them one day.

^8And the next day we that were of Paul’s company departed, and came unto Caesarea: and we entered into the house of Philip the evangelist, which was one of the seven; and abode with him.

^9And the same man had four daughters, virgins, which did prophesy.

^10And as we tarried there many days, there came down from Judaea a certain prophet, named Agabus.

^11And when he was come unto us, he took Paul’s girdle, and bound his own hands and feet, and said, Thus saith the Holy Ghost, So shall the Jews at Jerusalem bind the man that owneth this girdle, and shall deliver him into the hands of the Gentiles.

^12And when we heard these things, both we, and they of that place, besought him not to go up to Jerusalem.

^13Then Paul answered, What mean ye to weep and to break mine heart? for I am ready not to be bound only, but also to die at Jerusalem for the name of the Lord Jesus.

^14And when he would not be persuaded, we ceased, saying, The will of the Lord be done.

^15And after those days we took up our carriages, and went up to Jerusalem.

^16There went with us also certain of the disciples of Caesarea, and brought with them one Mnason of Cyprus, an old disciple, with whom we should lodge.

^17And when we were come to Jerusalem, the brethren received us gladly.

^18And the day following Paul went in with us unto James; and all the elders were present.

^19And when he had saluted them, he declared particularly what things God had wrought among the Gentiles by his ministry.

^20And when they heard it, they glorified the Lord, and said unto him, Thou seest, brother, how many thousands of Jews there are which believe; and they are all zealous of the law:

^21And they are informed of thee, that thou teachest all the Jews which are among the Gentiles to forsake Moses, saying that they ought not to circumcise their children, neither to walk after the customs.

^22What is it therefore? the multitude must needs come together: for they will hear that thou art come.

^23Do therefore this that we say to thee: We have four men which have a vow on them;

^24Them take, and purify thyself with them, and be at charges with them, that they may shave their heads: and all may know that those things, whereof they were informed concerning thee, are nothing; but that thou thyself also walkest orderly, and keepest the law.

^25As touching the Gentiles which believe, we have written and concluded that they observe no such thing, save only that they keep themselves from things offered to idols, and from blood, and from strangled, and from fornication.

^26Then Paul took the men, and the next day purifying himself with them entered into the temple, to signify the accomplishment of the days of purification, until that an offering should be offered for every one of them.

^27And when the seven days were almost ended, the Jews which were of Asia, when they saw him in the temple, stirred up all the people, and laid hands on him,

^28Crying out, Men of Israel, help: This is the man, that teacheth all men every where against the people, and the law, and this place: and further brought Greeks also into the temple, and hath polluted this holy place.

^29(For they had seen before with him in the city Trophimus an Ephesian, whom they supposed that Paul had brought into the temple.)

^30And all the city was moved, and the people ran together: and they took Paul, and drew him out of the temple: and forthwith the doors were shut.

^31And as they went about to kill him, tidings came unto the chief captain of the band, that all Jerusalem was in an uproar.

^32Who immediately took soldiers and centurions, and ran down unto them: and when they saw the chief captain and the soldiers, they left beating of Paul.

^33Then the chief captain came near, and took him, and commanded him to be bound with two chains; and demanded who he was, and what he had done.

^34And some cried one thing, some another, among the multitude: and when he could not know the certainty for the tumult, he commanded him to be carried into the castle.

^35And when he came upon the stairs, so it was, that he was borne of the soldiers for the violence of the people.

^36For the multitude of the people followed after, crying, Away with him.

^37And as Paul was to be led into the castle, he said unto the chief captain, May I speak unto thee? Who said, Canst thou speak Greek?

^38Art not thou that Egyptian, which before these days madest an uproar, and leddest out into the wilderness four thousand men that were murderers?

^39But Paul said, I am a man which am a Jew of Tarsus, a city in Cilicia, a citizen of no mean city: and, I beseech thee, suffer me to speak unto the people.

^40And when he had given him licence, Paul stood on the stairs, and beckoned with the hand unto the people. And when there was made a great silence, he spake unto them in the Hebrew tongue, saying,

Acts 22

22^1Men, brethren, and fathers, hear ye my defence which I make now unto you.

^2(And when they heard that he spake in the Hebrew tongue to them, they kept the more silence: and he saith,)

^3I am verily a man which am a Jew, born in Tarsus, a city in Cilicia, yet brought up in this city at the feet of Gamaliel, and taught according to the perfect manner of the law of the fathers, and was zealous toward God, as ye all are this day.

^4And I persecuted this way unto the death, binding and delivering into prisons both men and women.

^5As also the high priest doth bear me witness, and all the estate of the elders: from whom also I received letters unto the brethren, and went to Damascus, to bring them which were there bound unto Jerusalem, for to be punished.

^6And it came to pass, that, as I made my journey, and was come nigh unto Damascus about noon, suddenly there shone from heaven a great light round about me.

^7And I fell unto the ground, and heard a voice saying unto me, Saul, Saul, why persecutest thou me?

^8And I answered, Who art thou, Lord? And he said unto me, I am Jesus of Nazareth, whom thou persecutest.

^9And they that were with me saw indeed the light, and were afraid; but they heard not the voice of him that spake to me.

^10And I said, What shall I do, Lord? And the Lord said unto me, Arise, and go into Damascus; and there it shall be told thee of all things which are appointed for thee to do.

^11And when I could not see for the glory of that light, being led by the hand of them that were with me, I came into Damascus.

^12And one Ananias, a devout man according to the law, having a good report of all the Jews which dwelt there,

^13Came unto me, and stood, and said unto me, Brother Saul, receive thy sight. And the same hour I looked up upon him.

^14And he said, The God of our fathers hath chosen thee, that thou shouldest know his will, and see that Just One, and shouldest hear the voice of his mouth.

^15For thou shalt be his witness unto all men of what thou hast seen and heard.

^16And now why tarriest thou? arise, and be baptized, and wash away thy sins, calling on the name of the Lord.

^17And it came to pass, that, when I was come again to Jerusalem, even while I prayed in the temple, I was in a trance;

^18And saw him saying unto me, Make haste, and get thee quickly out of Jerusalem: for they will not receive thy testimony concerning me.

^19And I said, Lord, they know that I imprisoned and beat in every synagogue them that believed on thee:

^20And when the blood of thy martyr Stephen was shed, I also was standing by, and consenting unto his death, and kept the raiment of them that slew him.

^21And he said unto me, Depart: for I will send thee far hence unto the Gentiles.

^22And they gave him audience unto this word, and then lifted up their voices, and said, Away with such a fellow from the earth: for it is not fit that he should live.

^23And as they cried out, and cast off their clothes, and threw dust into the air,

^24The chief captain commanded him to be brought into the castle, and bade that he should be examined by scourging; that he might know wherefore they cried so against him.

^25And as they bound him with thongs, Paul said unto the centurion that stood by, Is it lawful for you to scourge a man that is a Roman, and uncondemned?

^26When the centurion heard that, he went and told the chief captain, saying, Take heed what thou doest: for this man is a Roman.

^27Then the chief captain came, and said unto him, Tell me, art thou a Roman? He said, Yea.

^28And the chief captain answered, With a great sum obtained I this freedom. And Paul said, But I was free born.

^29Then straightway they departed from him which should have examined him: and the chief captain also was afraid, after he knew that he was a Roman, and because he had bound him.

^30On the morrow, because he would have known the certainty wherefore he was accused of the Jews, he loosed him from his bands, and commanded the chief priests and all their council to appear, and brought Paul down, and set him before them.

Acts 23

23^1And Paul, earnestly beholding the council, said, Men and brethren, I have lived in all good conscience before God until this day.

^2And the high priest Ananias commanded them that stood by him to smite him on the mouth.

^3Then said Paul unto him, God shall smite thee, thou whited wall: for sittest thou to judge me after the law, and commandest me to be smitten contrary to the law?

^4And they that stood by said, Revilest thou God’s high priest?

^5Then said Paul, I wist not, brethren, that he was the high priest: for it is written, Thou shalt not speak evil of the ruler of thy people.

^6But when Paul perceived that the one part were Sadducees, and the other Pharisees, he cried out in the council, Men and brethren, I am a Pharisee, the son of a Pharisee: of the hope and resurrection of the dead I am called in question.

^7And when he had so said, there arose a dissension between the Pharisees and the Sadducees: and the multitude was divided.

^8For the Sadducees say that there is no resurrection, neither angel, nor spirit: but the Pharisees confess both.

^9And there arose a great cry: and the scribes that were of the Pharisees’ part arose, and strove, saying, We find no evil in this man: but if a spirit or an angel hath spoken to him, let us not fight against God.

^10And when there arose a great dissension, the chief captain, fearing lest Paul should have been pulled in pieces of them, commanded the soldiers to go down, and to take him by force from among them, and to bring him into the castle.

^11And the night following the Lord stood by him, and said, Be of good cheer, Paul: for as thou hast testified of me in Jerusalem, so must thou bear witness also at Rome.

^12And when it was day, certain of the Jews banded together, and bound themselves under a curse, saying that they would neither eat nor drink till they had killed Paul.

^13And they were more than forty which had made this conspiracy.

^14And they came to the chief priests and elders, and said, We have bound ourselves under a great curse, that we will eat nothing until we have slain Paul.

^15Now therefore ye with the council signify to the chief captain that he bring him down unto you to morrow, as though ye would enquire something more perfectly concerning him: and we, or ever he come near, are ready to kill him.

^16And when Paul’s sister’s son heard of their lying in wait, he went and entered into the castle, and told Paul.

^17Then Paul called one of the centurions unto him, and said, Bring this young man unto the chief captain: for he hath a certain thing to tell him.

^18So he took him, and brought him to the chief captain, and said, Paul the prisoner called me unto him, and prayed me to bring this young man unto thee, who hath something to say unto thee.

^19Then the chief captain took him by the hand, and went with him aside privately, and asked him, What is that thou hast to tell me?

^20And he said, The Jews have agreed to desire thee that thou wouldest bring down Paul to morrow into the council, as though they would enquire somewhat of him more perfectly.

^21But do not thou yield unto them: for there lie in wait for him of them more than forty men, which have bound themselves with an oath, that they will neither eat nor drink till they have killed him: and now are they ready, looking for a promise from thee.

^22So the chief captain then let the young man depart, and charged him, See thou tell no man that thou hast shewed these things to me.

^23And he called unto him two centurions, saying, Make ready two hundred soldiers to go to Caesarea, and horsemen threescore and ten, and spearmen two hundred, at the third hour of the night;

^24And provide them beasts, that they may set Paul on, and bring him safe unto Felix the governor.

^25And he wrote a letter after this manner:

^26Claudius Lysias unto the most excellent governor Felix sendeth greeting.

^27This man was taken of the Jews, and should have been killed of them: then came I with an army, and rescued him, having understood that he was a Roman.

^28And when I would have known the cause wherefore they accused him, I brought him forth into their council:

^29Whom I perceived to be accused of questions of their law, but to have nothing laid to his charge worthy of death or of bonds.

^30And when it was told me how that the Jews laid wait for the man, I sent straightway to thee, and gave commandment to his accusers also to say before thee what they had against him. Farewell.

^31Then the soldiers, as it was commanded them, took Paul, and brought him by night to Antipatris.

^32On the morrow they left the horsemen to go with him, and returned to the castle:

^33Who, when they came to Caesarea and delivered the epistle to the governor, presented Paul also before him.

^34And when the governor had read the letter, he asked of what province he was. And when he understood that he was of Cilicia;

^35I will hear thee, said he, when thine accusers are also come. And he commanded him to be kept in Herod’s judgment hall.

Acts 24

24^1And after five days Ananias the high priest descended with the elders, and with a certain orator named Tertullus, who informed the governor against Paul.

^2And when he was called forth, Tertullus began to accuse him, saying, Seeing that by thee we enjoy great quietness, and that very worthy deeds are done unto this nation by thy providence,

^3We accept it always, and in all places, most noble Felix, with all thankfulness.

^4Notwithstanding, that I be not further tedious unto thee, I pray thee that thou wouldest hear us of thy clemency a few words.

^5For we have found this man a pestilent fellow, and a mover of sedition among all the Jews throughout the world, and a ringleader of the sect of the Nazarenes:

^6Who also hath gone about to profane the temple: whom we took, and would have judged according to our law.

^7But the chief captain Lysias came upon us, and with great violence took him away out of our hands,

^8Commanding his accusers to come unto thee: by examining of whom thyself mayest take knowledge of all these things, whereof we accuse him.

^9And the Jews also assented, saying that these things were so.

^10Then Paul, after that the governor had beckoned unto him to speak, answered, Forasmuch as I know that thou hast been of many years a judge unto this nation, I do the more cheerfully answer for myself:

^11Because that thou mayest understand, that there are yet but twelve days since I went up to Jerusalem for to worship.

^12And they neither found me in the temple disputing with any man, neither raising up the people, neither in the synagogues, nor in the city:

^13Neither can they prove the things whereof they now accuse me.

^14But this I confess unto thee, that after the way which they call heresy, so worship I the God of my fathers, believing all things which are written in the law and in the prophets:

^15And have hope toward God, which they themselves also allow, that there shall be a resurrection of the dead, both of the just and unjust.

^16And herein do I exercise myself, to have always a conscience void to offence toward God, and toward men.

^17Now after many years I came to bring alms to my nation, and offerings.

^18Whereupon certain Jews from Asia found me purified in the temple, neither with multitude, nor with tumult.

^19Who ought to have been here before thee, and object, if they had ought against me.

^20Or else let these same here say, if they have found any evil doing in me, while I stood before the council,

^21Except it be for this one voice, that I cried standing among them, Touching the resurrection of the dead I am called in question by you this day.

^22And when Felix heard these things, having more perfect knowledge of that way, he deferred them, and said, When Lysias the chief captain shall come down, I will know the uttermost of your matter.

^23And he commanded a centurion to keep Paul, and to let him have liberty, and that he should forbid none of his acquaintance to minister or come unto him.

^24And after certain days, when Felix came with his wife Drusilla, which was a Jewess, he sent for Paul, and heard him concerning the faith in Christ.

^25And as he reasoned of righteousness, temperance, and judgment to come, Felix trembled, and answered, Go thy way for this time; when I have a convenient season, I will call for thee.

^26He hoped also that money should have been given him of Paul, that he might loose him: wherefore he sent for him the oftener, and communed with him.

^27But after two years Porcius Festus came into Felix’ room: and Felix, willing to shew the Jews a pleasure, left Paul bound.

Acts 25

25^1Now when Festus was come into the province, after three days he ascended from Caesarea to Jerusalem.

^2Then the high priest and the chief of the Jews informed him against Paul, and besought him,

^3And desired favour against him, that he would send for him to Jerusalem, laying wait in the way to kill him.

^4But Festus answered, that Paul should be kept at Caesarea, and that he himself would depart shortly thither.

^5Let them therefore, said he, which among you are able, go down with me, and accuse this man, if there be any wickedness in him.

^6And when he had tarried among them more than ten days, he went down unto Caesarea; and the next day sitting on the judgment seat commanded Paul to be brought.

^7And when he was come, the Jews which came down from Jerusalem stood round about, and laid many and grievous complaints against Paul, which they could not prove.

^8While he answered for himself, Neither against the law of the Jews, neither against the temple, nor yet against Caesar, have I offended any thing at all.

^9But Festus, willing to do the Jews a pleasure, answered Paul, and said, Wilt thou go up to Jerusalem, and there be judged of these things before me?

^10Then said Paul, I stand at Caesar’s judgment seat, where I ought to be judged: to the Jews have I done no wrong, as thou very well knowest.

^11For if I be an offender, or have committed any thing worthy of death, I refuse not to die: but if there be none of these things whereof these accuse me, no man may deliver me unto them. I appeal unto Caesar.

^12Then Festus, when he had conferred with the council, answered, Hast thou appealed unto Caesar? unto Caesar shalt thou go.

^13And after certain days king Agrippa and Bernice came unto Caesarea to salute Festus.

^14And when they had been there many days, Festus declared Paul’s cause unto the king, saying, There is a certain man left in bonds by Felix:

^15About whom, when I was at Jerusalem, the chief priests and the elders of the Jews informed me, desiring to have judgment against him.

^16To whom I answered, It is not the manner of the Romans to deliver any man to die, before that he which is accused have the accusers face to face, and have licence to answer for himself concerning the crime laid against him.

^17Therefore, when they were come hither, without any delay on the morrow I sat on the judgment seat, and commanded the man to be brought forth.

^18Against whom when the accusers stood up, they brought none accusation of such things as I supposed:

^19But had certain questions against him of their own superstition, and of one Jesus, which was dead, whom Paul affirmed to be alive.

^20And because I doubted of such manner of questions, I asked him whether he would go to Jerusalem, and there be judged of these matters.

^21But when Paul had appealed to be reserved unto the hearing of Augustus, I commanded him to be kept till I might send him to Caesar.

^22Then Agrippa said unto Festus, I would also hear the man myself. To morrow, said he, thou shalt hear him.

^23And on the morrow, when Agrippa was come, and Bernice, with great pomp, and was entered into the place of hearing, with the chief captains, and principal men of the city, at Festus’ commandment Paul was brought forth.

^24And Festus said, King Agrippa, and all men which are here present with us, ye see this man, about whom all the multitude of the Jews have dealt with me, both at Jerusalem, and also here, crying that he ought not to live any longer.

^25But when I found that he had committed nothing worthy of death, and that he himself hath appealed to Augustus, I have determined to send him.

^26Of whom I have no certain thing to write unto my lord. Wherefore I have brought him forth before you, and specially before thee, O king Agrippa, that, after examination had, I might have somewhat to write.

^27For it seemeth to me unreasonable to send a prisoner, and not withal to signify the crimes laid against him.

Acts 26

26^1Then Agrippa said unto Paul, Thou art permitted to speak for thyself. Then Paul stretched forth the hand, and answered for himself:

^2I think myself happy, king Agrippa, because I shall answer for myself this day before thee touching all the things whereof I am accused of the Jews:

^3Especially because I know thee to be expert in all customs and questions which are among the Jews: wherefore I beseech thee to hear me patiently.

^4My manner of life from my youth, which was at the first among mine own nation at Jerusalem, know all the Jews;

^5Which knew me from the beginning, if they would testify, that after the most straitest sect of our religion I lived a Pharisee.

^6And now I stand and am judged for the hope of the promise made of God, unto our fathers:

^7Unto which promise our twelve tribes, instantly serving God day and night, hope to come. For which hope’s sake, king Agrippa, I am accused of the Jews.

^8Why should it be thought a thing incredible with you, that God should raise the dead?

^9I verily thought with myself, that I ought to do many things contrary to the name of Jesus of Nazareth.

^10Which thing I also did in Jerusalem: and many of the saints did I shut up in prison, having received authority from the chief priests; and when they were put to death, I gave my voice against them.

^11And I punished them oft in every synagogue, and compelled them to blaspheme; and being exceedingly mad against them, I persecuted them even unto strange cities.

^12Whereupon as I went to Damascus with authority and commission from the chief priests,

^13At midday, O king, I saw in the way a light from heaven, above the brightness of the sun, shining round about me and them which journeyed with me.

^14And when we were all fallen to the earth, I heard a voice speaking unto me, and saying in the Hebrew tongue, Saul, Saul, why persecutest thou me? it is hard for thee to kick against the pricks.

^15And I said, Who art thou, Lord? And he said, I am Jesus whom thou persecutest.

^16But rise, and stand upon thy feet: for I have appeared unto thee for this purpose, to make thee a minister and a witness both of these things which thou hast seen, and of those things in the which I will appear unto thee;

^17Delivering thee from the people, and from the Gentiles, unto whom now I send thee,

^18To open their eyes, and to turn them from darkness to light, and from the power of Satan unto God, that they may receive forgiveness of sins, and inheritance among them which are sanctified by faith that is in me.

^19Whereupon, O king Agrippa, I was not disobedient unto the heavenly vision:

^20But shewed first unto them of Damascus, and at Jerusalem, and throughout all the coasts of Judaea, and then to the Gentiles, that they should repent and turn to God, and do works meet for repentance.

^21For these causes the Jews caught me in the temple, and went about to kill me.

^22Having therefore obtained help of God, I continue unto this day, witnessing both to small and great, saying none other things than those which the prophets and Moses did say should come:

^23That Christ should suffer, and that he should be the first that should rise from the dead, and should shew light unto the people, and to the Gentiles.

^24And as he thus spake for himself, Festus said with a loud voice, Paul, thou art beside thyself; much learning doth make thee mad.

^25But he said, I am not mad, most noble Festus; but speak forth the words of truth and soberness.

^26For the king knoweth of these things, before whom also I speak freely: for I am persuaded that none of these things are hidden from him; for this thing was not done in a corner.

^27King Agrippa, believest thou the prophets? I know that thou believest.

^28Then Agrippa said unto Paul, Almost thou persuadest me to be a Christian.

^29And Paul said, I would to God, that not only thou, but also all that hear me this day, were both almost, and altogether such as I am, except these bonds.

^30And when he had thus spoken, the king rose up, and the governor, and Bernice, and they that sat with them:

^31And when they were gone aside, they talked between themselves, saying, This man doeth nothing worthy of death or of bonds.

^32Then said Agrippa unto Festus, This man might have been set at liberty, if he had not appealed unto Caesar.

Acts 27

27^1And when it was determined that we should sail into Italy, they delivered Paul and certain other prisoners unto one named Julius, a centurion of Augustus’ band.

^2And entering into a ship of Adramyttium, we launched, meaning to sail by the coasts of Asia; one Aristarchus, a Macedonian of Thessalonica, being with us.

^3And the next day we touched at Sidon. And Julius courteously entreated Paul, and gave him liberty to go unto his friends to refresh himself.

^4And when we had launched from thence, we sailed under Cyprus, because the winds were contrary.

^5And when we had sailed over the sea of Cilicia and Pamphylia, we came to Myra, a city of Lycia.

^6And there the centurion found a ship of Alexandria sailing into Italy; and he put us therein.

^7And when we had sailed slowly many days, and scarce were come over against Cnidus, the wind not suffering us, we sailed under Crete, over against Salmone;

^8And, hardly passing it, came unto a place which is called The fair havens; nigh whereunto was the city of Lasea.

^9Now when much time was spent, and when sailing was now dangerous, because the fast was now already past, Paul admonished them,

^10And said unto them, Sirs, I perceive that this voyage will be with hurt and much damage, not only of the lading and ship, but also of our lives.

^11Nevertheless the centurion believed the master and the owner of the ship, more than those things which were spoken by Paul.

^12And because the haven was not commodious to winter in, the more part advised to depart thence also, if by any means they might attain to Phenice, and there to winter; which is an haven of Crete, and lieth toward the south west and north west.

^13And when the south wind blew softly, supposing that they had obtained their purpose, loosing thence, they sailed close by Crete.

^14But not long after there arose against it a tempestuous wind, called Euroclydon.

^15And when the ship was caught, and could not bear up into the wind, we let her drive.

^16And running under a certain island which is called Clauda, we had much work to come by the boat:

^17Which when they had taken up, they used helps, undergirding the ship; and, fearing lest they should fall into the quicksands, strake sail, and so were driven.

^18And we being exceedingly tossed with a tempest, the next day they lightened the ship;

^19And the third day we cast out with our own hands the tackling of the ship.

^20And when neither sun nor stars in many days appeared, and no small tempest lay on us, all hope that we should be saved was then taken away.

^21But after long abstinence Paul stood forth in the midst of them, and said, Sirs, ye should have hearkened unto me, and not have loosed from Crete, and to have gained this harm and loss.

^22And now I exhort you to be of good cheer: for there shall be no loss of any man’s life among you, but of the ship.

^23For there stood by me this night the angel of God, whose I am, and whom I serve,

^24Saying, Fear not, Paul; thou must be brought before Caesar: and, lo, God hath given thee all them that sail with thee.

^25Wherefore, sirs, be of good cheer: for I believe God, that it shall be even as it was told me.

^26Howbeit we must be cast upon a certain island.

^27But when the fourteenth night was come, as we were driven up and down in Adria, about midnight the shipmen deemed that they drew near to some country;

^28And sounded, and found it twenty fathoms: and when they had gone a little further, they sounded again, and found it fifteen fathoms.

^29Then fearing lest we should have fallen upon rocks, they cast four anchors out of the stern, and wished for the day.

^30And as the shipmen were about to flee out of the ship, when they had let down the boat into the sea, under colour as though they would have cast anchors out of the foreship,

^31Paul said to the centurion and to the soldiers, Except these abide in the ship, ye cannot be saved.

^32Then the soldiers cut off the ropes of the boat, and let her fall off.

^33And while the day was coming on, Paul besought them all to take meat, saying, This day is the fourteenth day that ye have tarried and continued fasting, having taken nothing.

^34Wherefore I pray you to take some meat: for this is for your health: for there shall not an hair fall from the head of any of you.

^35And when he had thus spoken, he took bread, and gave thanks to God in presence of them all: and when he had broken it, he began to eat.

^36Then were they all of good cheer, and they also took some meat.

^37And we were in all in the ship two hundred threescore and sixteen souls.

^38And when they had eaten enough, they lightened the ship, and cast out the wheat into the sea.

^39And when it was day, they knew not the land: but they discovered a certain creek with a shore, into the which they were minded, if it were possible, to thrust in the ship.

^40And when they had taken up the anchors, they committed themselves unto the sea, and loosed the rudder bands, and hoised up the mainsail to the wind, and made toward shore.

^41And falling into a place where two seas met, they ran the ship aground; and the forepart stuck fast, and remained unmoveable, but the hinder part was broken with the violence of the waves.

^42And the soldiers’ counsel was to kill the prisoners, lest any of them should swim out, and escape.

^43But the centurion, willing to save Paul, kept them from their purpose; and commanded that they which could swim should cast themselves first into the sea, and get to land:

^44And the rest, some on boards, and some on broken pieces of the ship. And so it came to pass, that they escaped all safe to land.

Acts 28

28^1And when they were escaped, then they knew that the island was called Melita.

^2And the barbarous people shewed us no little kindness: for they kindled a fire, and received us every one, because of the present rain, and because of the cold.

^3And when Paul had gathered a bundle of sticks, and laid them on the fire, there came a viper out of the heat, and fastened on his hand.

^4And when the barbarians saw the venomous beast hang on his hand, they said among themselves, No doubt this man is a murderer, whom, though he hath escaped the sea, yet vengeance suffereth not to live.

^5And he shook off the beast into the fire, and felt no harm.

^6Howbeit they looked when he should have swollen, or fallen down dead suddenly: but after they had looked a great while, and saw no harm come to him, they changed their minds, and said that he was a god.

^7In the same quarters were possessions of the chief man of the island, whose name was Publius; who received us, and lodged us three days courteously.

^8And it came to pass, that the father of Publius lay sick of a fever and of a bloody flux: to whom Paul entered in, and prayed, and laid his hands on him, and healed him.

^9So when this was done, others also, which had diseases in the island, came, and were healed:

^10Who also honoured us with many honours; and when we departed, they laded us with such things as were necessary.

^11And after three months we departed in a ship of Alexandria, which had wintered in the isle, whose sign was Castor and Pollux.

^12And landing at Syracuse, we tarried there three days.

^13And from thence we fetched a compass, and came to Rhegium: and after one day the south wind blew, and we came the next day to Puteoli:

^14Where we found brethren, and were desired to tarry with them seven days: and so we went toward Rome.

^15And from thence, when the brethren heard of us, they came to meet us as far as Appii forum, and The three taverns: whom when Paul saw, he thanked God, and took courage.

^16And when we came to Rome, the centurion delivered the prisoners to the captain of the guard: but Paul was suffered to dwell by himself with a soldier that kept him.

^17And it came to pass, that after three days Paul called the chief of the Jews together: and when they were come together, he said unto them, Men and brethren, though I have committed nothing against the people, or customs of our fathers, yet was I delivered prisoner from Jerusalem into the hands of the Romans.

^18Who, when they had examined me, would have let me go, because there was no cause of death in me.

^19But when the Jews spake against it, I was constrained to appeal unto Caesar; not that I had ought to accuse my nation of.

^20For this cause therefore have I called for you, to see you, and to speak with you: because that for the hope of Israel I am bound with this chain.

^21And they said unto him, We neither received letters out of Judaea concerning thee, neither any of the brethren that came shewed or spake any harm of thee.

^22But we desire to hear of thee what thou thinkest: for as concerning this sect, we know that every where it is spoken against.

^23And when they had appointed him a day, there came many to him into his lodging; to whom he expounded and testified the kingdom of God, persuading them concerning Jesus, both out of the law of Moses, and out of the prophets, from morning till evening.

^24And some believed the things which were spoken, and some believed not.

^25And when they agreed not among themselves, they departed, after that Paul had spoken one word, Well spake the Holy Ghost by Esaias the prophet unto our fathers,

^26Saying, Go unto this people, and say, Hearing ye shall hear, and shall not understand; and seeing ye shall see, and not perceive:

^27For the heart of this people is waxed gross, and their ears are dull of hearing, and their eyes have they closed; lest they should see with their eyes, and hear with their ears, and understand with their heart, and should be converted, and I should heal them.

^28Be it known therefore unto you, that the salvation of God is sent unto the Gentiles, and that they will hear it.

^29And when he had said these words, the Jews departed, and had great reasoning among themselves.

^30And Paul dwelt two whole years in his own hired house, and received all that came in unto him,

^31Preaching the kingdom of God, and teaching those things which concern the Lord Jesus Christ, with all confidence, no man forbidding him.

Romans

The Epistle of Paul the Apostle to the

Romans

I

^1Paul, a servant of Jesus Christ, called to be an apostle, separated unto the gospel of God,

^2(Which he had promised afore by his prophets in the holy scriptures,)

^3Concerning his Son Jesus Christ our Lord, which was made of the seed of David according to the flesh;

^4And declared to be the Son of God with power, according to the spirit of holiness, by the resurrection from the dead:

^5By whom we have received grace and apostleship, for obedience to the faith among all nations, for his name:

^6Among whom are ye also the called of Jesus Christ:

^7To all that be in Rome, beloved of God, called to be saints: Grace to you and peace from God our Father, and the Lord Jesus Christ.

^8First, I thank my God through Jesus Christ for you all, that your faith is spoken of throughout the whole world.

^9For God is my witness, whom I serve with my spirit in the gospel of his Son, that without ceasing I make mention of you always in my prayers;

^10Making request, if by any means now at length I might have a prosperous journey by the will of God to come unto you.

^11For I long to see you, that I may impart unto you some spiritual gift, to the end ye may be established;

^12That is, that I may be comforted together with you by the mutual faith both of you and me.

^13Now I would not have you ignorant, brethren, that oftentimes I purposed to come unto you, (but was let hitherto,) that I might have some fruit among you also, even as among other Gentiles.

^14I am debtor both to the Greeks, and to the Barbarians; both to the wise, and to the unwise.

^15So, as much as in me is, I am ready to preach the gospel to you that are at Rome also.

^16For I am not ashamed of the gospel of Christ: for it is the power of God unto salvation to every one that believeth; to the Jew first, and also to the Greek.

^17For therein is the righteousness of God revealed from faith to faith: as it is written, The just shall live by faith.

^18For the wrath of God is revealed from heaven against all ungodliness and unrighteousness of men, who hold the truth in unrighteousness;

^19Because that which may be known of God is manifest in them; for God hath shewed it unto them.

^20For the invisible things of him from the creation of the world are clearly seen, being understood by the things that are made, even his eternal power and Godhead; so that they are without excuse:

^21Because that, when they knew God, they glorified him not as God, neither were thankful; but became vain in their imaginations, and their foolish heart was darkened.

^22Professing themselves to be wise, they became fools,

^23And changed the glory of the uncorruptible God into an image made like to corruptible man, and to birds, and fourfooted beasts, and creeping things.

^24Wherefore God also gave them up to uncleanness through the lusts of their own hearts, to dishonour their own bodies between themselves:

^25Who changed the truth of God into a lie, and worshipped and served the creature more than the Creator, who is blessed for ever. Amen.

^26For this cause God gave them up unto vile affections: for even their women did change the natural use into that which is against nature:

^27And likewise also the men, leaving the natural use of the woman, burned in their lust one toward another; men with men working that which is unseemly, and receiving in themselves that recompence of their error which was meet.

^28And even as they did not like to retain God in their knowledge, God gave them over to a reprobate mind, to do those things which are not convenient;

^29Being filled with all unrighteousness, fornication, wickedness, covetousness, maliciousness; full of envy, murder, debate, deceit, malignity; whisperers,

^30Backbiters, haters of God, despiteful, proud, boasters, inventors of evil things, disobedient to parents,

^31Without understanding, covenantbreakers, without natural affection, implacable, unmerciful:

^32Who knowing the judgment of God, that they which commit such things are worthy of death, not only do the same, but have pleasure in them that do them.

II

^1Therefore thou art inexcusable, O man, whosoever thou art that judgest: for wherein thou judgest another, thou condemnest thyself; for thou that judgest doest the same things.

^2But we are sure that the judgment of God is according to truth against them which commit such things.

^3And thinkest thou this, O man, that judgest them which do such things, and doest the same, that thou shalt escape the judgment of God?

^4Or despisest thou the riches of his goodness and forbearance and longsuffering; not knowing that the goodness of God leadeth thee to repentance?

^5But after thy hardness and impenitent heart treasurest up unto thyself wrath against the day of wrath and revelation of the righteous judgment of God;

^6Who will render to every man according to his deeds:

^7To them who by patient continuance in well doing seek for glory and honour and immortality, eternal life:

^8But unto them that are contentious, and do not obey the truth, but obey unrighteousness, indignation and wrath,

^9Tribulation and anguish, upon every soul of man that doeth evil, of the Jew first, and also of the Gentile;

^10But glory, honour, and peace, to every man that worketh good, to the Jew first, and also to the Gentile:

^11For there is no respect of persons with God.

^12For as many as have sinned without law shall also perish without law: and as many as have sinned in the law shall be judged by the law;

^13(For not the hearers of the law are just before God, but the doers of the law shall be justified.

^14For when the Gentiles, which have not the law, do by nature the things contained in the law, these, having not the law, are a law unto themselves:

^15Which shew the work of the law written in their hearts, their conscience also bearing witness, and their thoughts the mean while accusing or else excusing one another;)

^16In the day when God shall judge the secrets of men by Jesus Christ according to my gospel.

^17Behold, thou art called a Jew, and restest in the law, and makest thy boast of God,

^18And knowest his will, and approvest the things that are more excellent, being instructed out of the law;

^19And art confident that thou thyself art a guide of the blind, a light of them which are in darkness,

^20An instructor of the foolish, a teacher of babes, which hast the form of knowledge and of the truth in the law.

^21Thou therefore which teachest another, teachest thou not thyself? thou that preachest a man should not steal, dost thou steal?

^22Thou that sayest a man should not commit adultery, dost thou commit adultery? thou that abhorrest idols, dost thou commit sacrilege?

^23Thou that makest thy boast of the law, through breaking the law dishonourest thou God?

^24For the name of God is blasphemed among the Gentiles through you, as it is written.

^25For circumcision verily profiteth, if thou keep the law: but if thou be a breaker of the law, thy circumcision is made uncircumcision.

^26Therefore if the uncircumcision keep the righteousness of the law, shall not his uncircumcision be counted for circumcision?

^27And shall not uncircumcision which is by nature, if it fulfil the law, judge thee, who by the letter and circumcision dost transgress the law?

^28For he is not a Jew, which is one outwardly; neither is that circumcision, which is outward in the flesh:

^29But he is a Jew, which is one inwardly; and circumcision is that of the heart, in the spirit, and not in the letter; whose praise is not of men, but of God.

III

^1What advantage then hath the Jew? or what profit is there of circumcision?

^2Much every way: chiefly, because that unto them were committed the oracles of God.

^3For what if some did not believe? shall their unbelief make the faith of God without effect?

^4God forbid: yea, let God be true, but every man a liar; as it is written, That thou mightest be justified in thy sayings, and mightest overcome when thou art judged.

^5But if our unrighteousness commend the righteousness of God, what shall we say? Is God unrighteous who taketh vengeance? (I speak as a man)

^6God forbid: for then how shall God judge the world?

^7For if the truth of God hath more abounded through my lie unto his glory; why yet am I also judged as a sinner?

^8And not rather, (as we be slanderously reported, and as some affirm that we say,) Let us do evil, that good may come? whose damnation is just.

^9What then? are we better than they? No, in no wise: for we have before proved both Jews and Gentiles, that they are all under sin;

^10As it is written, There is none righteous, no, not one:

^11There is none that understandeth, there is none that seeketh after God.

^12They are all gone out of the way, they are together become unprofitable; there is none that doeth good, no, not one.

^13Their throat is an open sepulchre; with their tongues they have used deceit; the poison of asps is under their lips:

^14Whose mouth is full of cursing and bitterness:

^15Their feet are swift to shed blood:

^16Destruction and misery are in their ways:

^17And the way of peace have they not known:

^18There is no fear of God before their eyes.

^19Now we know that what things soever the law saith, it saith to them who are under the law: that every mouth may be stopped, and all the world may become guilty before God.

^20Therefore by the deeds of the law there shall no flesh be justified in his sight: for by the law is the knowledge of sin.

^21But now the righteousness of God without the law is manifested, being witnessed by the law and the prophets;

^22Even the righteousness of God which is by faith of Jesus Christ unto all and upon all them that believe: for there is no difference:

^23For all have sinned, and come short of the glory of God;

^24Being justified freely by his grace through the redemption that is in Christ Jesus:

^25Whom God hath set forth to be a propitiation through faith in his blood, to declare his righteousness for the remission of sins that are past, through the forbearance of God;

^26To declare, I say, at this time his righteousness: that he might be just, and the justifier of him which believeth in Jesus.

^27Where is boasting then? It is excluded. By what law? of works? Nay: but by the law of faith.

^28Therefore we conclude that a man is justified by faith without the deeds of the law.

^29Is he the God of the Jews only? is he not also of the Gentiles? Yes, of the Gentiles also:

^30Seeing it is one God, which shall justify the circumcision by faith, and uncircumcision through faith.

^31Do we then make void the law through faith? God forbid: yea, we establish the law.

IV

^1What shall we say then that Abraham our father, as pertaining to the flesh, hath found?

^2For if Abraham were justified by works, he hath whereof to glory; but not before God.

^3For what saith the scripture? Abraham believed God, and it was counted unto him for righteousness.

^4Now to him that worketh is the reward not reckoned of grace, but of debt.

^5But to him that worketh not, but believeth on him that justifieth the ungodly, his faith is counted for righteousness.

^6Even as David also describeth the blessedness of the man, unto whom God imputeth righteousness without works,

^7Saying, Blessed are they whose iniquities are forgiven, and whose sins are covered.

^8Blessed is the man to whom the Lord will not impute sin.

^9Cometh this blessedness then upon the circumcision only, or upon the uncircumcision also? for we say that faith was reckoned to Abraham for righteousness.

^10How was it then reckoned? when he was in circumcision, or in uncircumcision? Not in circumcision, but in uncircumcision.

^11And he received the sign of circumcision, a seal of the righteousness of the faith which he had yet being uncircumcised: that he might be the father of all them that believe, though they be not circumcised; that righteousness might be imputed unto them also:

^12And the father of circumcision to them who are not of the circumcision only, but who also walk in the steps of that faith of our father Abraham, which he had being yet uncircumcised.

^13For the promise, that he should be the heir of the world, was not to Abraham, or to his seed, through the law, but through the righteousness of faith.

^14For if they which are of the law be heirs, faith is made void, and the promise made of none effect:

^15Because the law worketh wrath: for where no law is, there is no transgression.

^16Therefore it is of faith, that it might be by grace; to the end the promise might be sure to all the seed; not to that only which is of the law, but to that also which is of the faith of Abraham; who is the father of us all,

^17(As it is written, I have made thee a father of many nations,) before him whom he believed, even God, who quickeneth the dead, and calleth those things which be not as though they were.

^18Who against hope believed in hope, that he might become the father of many nations, according to that which was spoken, So shall thy seed be.

^19And being not weak in faith, he considered not his own body now dead, when he was about an hundred years old, neither yet the deadness of Sarah’s womb:

^20He staggered not at the promise of God through unbelief; but was strong in faith, giving glory to God;

^21And being fully persuaded that, what he had promised, he was able also to perform.

^22And therefore it was imputed to him for righteousness.

^23Now it was not written for his sake alone, that it was imputed to him;

^24But for us also, to whom it shall be imputed, if we believe on him that raised up Jesus our Lord from the dead;

^25Who was delivered for our offences, and was raised again for our justification.

V

^1Therefore being justified by faith, we have peace with God through our Lord Jesus Christ:

^2By whom also we have access by faith into this grace wherein we stand, and rejoice in hope of the glory of God.

^3And not only so, but we glory in tribulations also: knowing that tribulation worketh patience;

^4And patience, experience; and experience, hope:

^5And hope maketh not ashamed; because the love of God is shed abroad in our hearts by the Holy Ghost which is given unto us.

^6For when we were yet without strength, in due time Christ died for the ungodly.

^7For scarcely for a righteous man will one die: yet peradventure for a good man some would even dare to die.

^8But God commendeth his love toward us, in that, while we were yet sinners, Christ died for us.

^9Much more then, being now justified by his blood, we shall be saved from wrath through him.

^10For if, when we were enemies, we were reconciled to God by the death of his Son, much more, being reconciled, we shall be saved by his life.

^11And not only so, but we also joy in God through our Lord Jesus Christ, by whom we have now received the atonement.

^12Wherefore, as by one man sin entered into the world, and death by sin; and so death passed upon all men, for that all have sinned:

^13(For until the law sin was in the world: but sin is not imputed when there is no law.

^14Nevertheless death reigned from Adam to Moses, even over them that had not sinned after the similitude of Adam’s transgression, who is the figure of him that was to come.

^15But not as the offence, so also is the free gift. For if through the offence of one many be dead, much more the grace of God, and the gift by grace, which is by one man, Jesus Christ, hath abounded unto many.

^16And not as it was by one that sinned, so is the gift: for the judgment was by one to condemnation, but the free gift is of many offences unto justification.

^17For if by one man’s offence death reigned by one; much more they which receive abundance of grace and of the gift of righteousness shall reign in life by one, Jesus Christ.)

^18Therefore as by the offence of one judgment came upon all men to condemnation; even so by the righteousness of one the free gift came upon all men unto justification of life.

^19For as by one man’s disobedience many were made sinners, so by the obedience of one shall many be made righteous.

^20Moreover the law entered, that the offence might abound. But where sin abounded, grace did much more abound:

^21That as sin hath reigned unto death, even so might grace reign through righteousness unto eternal life by Jesus Christ our Lord.

VI

^1What shall we say then? Shall we continue in sin, that grace may abound?

^2God forbid. How shall we, that are dead to sin, live any longer therein?

^3Know ye not, that so many of us as were baptized into Jesus Christ were baptized into his death?

^4Therefore we are buried with him by baptism into death: that like as Christ was raised up from the dead by the glory of the Father, even so we also should walk in newness of life.

^5For if we have been planted together in the likeness of his death, we shall be also in the likeness of his resurrection:

^6Knowing this, that our old man is crucified with him, that the body of sin might be destroyed, that henceforth we should not serve sin.

^7For he that is dead is freed from sin.

^8Now if we be dead with Christ, we believe that we shall also live with him:

^9Knowing that Christ being raised from the dead dieth no more; death hath no more dominion over him.

^10For in that he died, he died unto sin once: but in that he liveth, he liveth unto God.

^11Likewise reckon ye also yourselves to be dead indeed unto sin, but alive unto God through Jesus Christ our Lord.

^12Let not sin therefore reign in your mortal body, that ye should obey it in the lusts thereof.

^13Neither yield ye your members as instruments of unrighteousness unto sin: but yield yourselves unto God, as those that are alive from the dead, and your members as instruments of righteousness unto God.

^14For sin shall not have dominion over you: for ye are not under the law, but under grace.

^15What then? shall we sin, because we are not under the law, but under grace? God forbid.

^16Know ye not, that to whom ye yield yourselves servants to obey, his servants ye are to whom ye obey; whether of sin unto death, or of obedience unto righteousness?

^17But God be thanked, that ye were the servants of sin, but ye have obeyed from the heart that form of doctrine which was delivered you.

^18Being then made free from sin, ye became the servants of righteousness.

^19I speak after the manner of men because of the infirmity of your flesh: for as ye have yielded your members servants to uncleanness and to iniquity unto iniquity; even so now yield your members servants to righteousness unto holiness.

^20For when ye were the servants of sin, ye were free from righteousness.

^21What fruit had ye then in those things whereof ye are now ashamed? for the end of those things is death.

^22But now being made free from sin, and become servants to God, ye have your fruit unto holiness, and the end everlasting life.

^23For the wages of sin is death; but the gift of God is eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord.

VII

^1Know ye not, brethren, (for I speak to them that know the law,) how that the law hath dominion over a man as long as he liveth?

^2For the woman which hath an husband is bound by the law to her husband so long as he liveth; but if the husband be dead, she is loosed from the law of her husband.

^3So then if, while her husband liveth, she be married to another man, she shall be called an adulteress: but if her husband be dead, she is free from that law; so that she is no adulteress, though she be married to another man.

^4Wherefore, my brethren, ye also are become dead to the law by the body of Christ; that ye should be married to another, even to him who is raised from the dead, that we should bring forth fruit unto God.

^5For when we were in the flesh, the motions of sins, which were by the law, did work in our members to bring forth fruit unto death.

^6But now we are delivered from the law, that being dead wherein we were held; that we should serve in newness of spirit, and not in the oldness of the letter.

^7What shall we say then? Is the law sin? God forbid. Nay, I had not known sin, but by the law: for I had not known lust, except the law had said, Thou shalt not covet.

^8But sin, taking occasion by the commandment, wrought in me all manner of concupiscence. For without the law sin was dead.

^9For I was alive without the law once: but when the commandment came, sin revived, and I died.

^10And the commandment, which was ordained to life, I found to be unto death.

^11For sin, taking occasion by the commandment, deceived me, and by it slew me.

^12Wherefore the law is holy, and the commandment holy, and just, and good.

^13Was then that which is good made death unto me? God forbid. But sin, that it might appear sin, working death in me by that which is good; that sin by the commandment might become exceeding sinful.

^14For we know that the law is spiritual: but I am carnal, sold under sin.

^15For that which I do I allow not: for what I would, that do I not; but what I hate, that do I.

^16If then I do that which I would not, I consent unto the law that it is good.

^17Now then it is no more I that do it, but sin that dwelleth in me.

^18For I know that in me (that is, in my flesh,) dwelleth no good thing: for to will is present with me; but how to perform that which is good I find not.

^19For the good that I would I do not: but the evil which I would not, that I do.

^20Now if I do that I would not, it is no more I that do it, but sin that dwelleth in me.

^21I find then a law, that, when I would do good, evil is present with me.

^22For I delight in the law of God after the inward man:

^23But I see another law in my members, warring against the law of my mind, and bringing me into captivity to the law of sin which is in my members.

^24O wretched man that I am! who shall deliver me from the body of this death?

^25I thank God through Jesus Christ our Lord. So then with the mind I myself serve the law of God; but with the flesh the law of sin.

VIII

^1There is therefore now no condemnation to them which are in Christ Jesus, who walk not after the flesh, but after the Spirit.

^2For the law of the Spirit of life in Christ Jesus hath made me free from the law of sin and death.

^3For what the law could not do, in that it was weak through the flesh, God sending his own Son in the likeness of sinful flesh, and for sin, condemned sin in the flesh:

^4That the righteousness of the law might be fulfilled in us, who walk not after the flesh, but after the Spirit.

^5For they that are after the flesh do mind the things of the flesh; but they that are after the Spirit the things of the Spirit.

^6For to be carnally minded is death; but to be spiritually minded is life and peace.

^7Because the carnal mind is enmity against God: for it is not subject to the law of God, neither indeed can be.

^8So then they that are in the flesh cannot please God.

^9But ye are not in the flesh, but in the Spirit, if so be that the Spirit of God dwell in you. Now if any man have not the Spirit of Christ, he is none of his.

^10And if Christ be in you, the body is dead because of sin; but the Spirit is life because of righteousness.

^11But if the Spirit of him that raised up Jesus from the dead dwell in you, he that raised up Christ from the dead shall also quicken your mortal bodies by his Spirit that dwelleth in you.

^12Therefore, brethren, we are debtors, not to the flesh, to live after the flesh.

^13For if ye live after the flesh, ye shall die: but if ye through the Spirit do mortify the deeds of the body, ye shall live.

^14For as many as are led by the Spirit of God, they are the sons of God.

^15For ye have not received the spirit of bondage again to fear; but ye have received the Spirit of adoption, whereby we cry, Abba, Father.

^16The Spirit itself beareth witness with our spirit, that we are the children of God:

^17And if children, then heirs; heirs of God, and joint-heirs with Christ; if so be that we suffer with him, that we may be also glorified together.

^18For I reckon that the sufferings of this present time are not worthy to be compared with the glory which shall be revealed in us.

^19For the earnest expectation of the creature waiteth for the manifestation of the sons of God.

^20For the creature was made subject to vanity, not willingly, but by reason of him who hath subjected the same in hope,

^21Because the creature itself also shall be delivered from the bondage of corruption into the glorious liberty of the children of God.

^22For we know that the whole creation groaneth and travaileth in pain together until now.

^23And not only they, but ourselves also, which have the firstfruits of the Spirit, even we ourselves groan within ourselves, waiting for the adoption, to wit, the redemption of our body.

^24For we are saved by hope: but hope that is seen is not hope: for what a man seeth, why doth he yet hope for?

^25But if we hope for that we see not, then do we with patience wait for it.

^26Likewise the Spirit also helpeth our infirmities: for we know not what we should pray for as we ought: but the Spirit itself maketh intercession for us with groanings which cannot be uttered.

^27And he that searcheth the hearts knoweth what is the mind of the Spirit, because he maketh intercession for the saints according to the will of God.

^28And we know that all things work together for good to them that love God, to them who are the called according to his purpose.

^29For whom he did foreknow, he also did predestinate to be conformed to the image of his Son, that he might be the firstborn among many brethren.

^30Moreover whom he did predestinate, them he also called: and whom he called, them he also justified: and whom he justified, them he also glorified.

^31What shall we then say to these things? If God be for us, who can be against us?

^32He that spared not his own Son, but delivered him up for us all, how shall he not with him also freely give us all things?

^33Who shall lay any thing to the charge of God’s elect? It is God that justifieth.

^34Who is he that condemneth? It is Christ that died, yea rather, that is risen again, who is even at the right hand of God, who also maketh intercession for us.

^35Who shall separate us from the love of Christ? shall tribulation, or distress, or persecution, or famine, or nakedness, or peril, or sword?

^36As it is written, For thy sake we are killed all the day long; we are accounted as sheep for the slaughter.

^37Nay, in all these things we are more than conquerors through him that loved us.

^38For I am persuaded, that neither death, nor life, nor angels, nor principalities, nor powers, nor things present, nor things to come,

^39Nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature, shall be able to separate us from the love of God, which is in Christ Jesus our Lord.

IX

^1I say the truth in Christ, I lie not, my conscience also bearing me witness in the Holy Ghost,

^2That I have great heaviness and continual sorrow in my heart.

^3For I could wish that myself were accursed from Christ for my brethren, my kinsmen according to the flesh:

^4Who are Israelites; to whom pertaineth the adoption, and the glory, and the covenants, and the giving of the law, and the service of God, and the promises;

^5Whose are the fathers, and of whom as concerning the flesh Christ came, who is over all, God blessed for ever. Amen.

^6Not as though the word of God hath taken none effect. For they are not all Israel, which are of Israel:

^7Neither, because they are the seed of Abraham, are they all children: but, In Isaac shall thy seed be called.

^8That is, They which are the children of the flesh, these are not the children of God: but the children of the promise are counted for the seed.

^9For this is the word of promise, At this time will I come, and Sarah shall have a son.

^10And not only this; but when Rebecca also had conceived by one, even by our father Isaac;

^11(For the children being not yet born, neither having done any good or evil, that the purpose of God according to election might stand, not of works, but of him that calleth;)

^12It was said unto her, The elder shall serve the younger.

^13As it is written, Jacob have I loved, but Esau have I hated.

^14What shall we say then? Is there unrighteousness with God? God forbid.

^15For he saith to Moses, I will have mercy on whom I will have mercy, and I will have compassion on whom I will have compassion.

^16So then it is not of him that willeth, nor of him that runneth, but of God that sheweth mercy.

^17For the scripture saith unto Pharaoh, Even for this same purpose have I raised thee up, that I might shew my power in thee, and that my name might be declared throughout all the earth.

^18Therefore hath he mercy on whom he will have mercy, and whom he will he hardeneth.

^19Thou wilt say then unto me, Why doth he yet find fault? For who hath resisted his will?

^20Nay but, O man, who art thou that repliest against God? Shall the thing formed say to him that formed it, Why hast thou made me thus?

^21Hath not the potter power over the clay, of the same lump to make one vessel unto honour, and another unto dishonour?

^22What if God, willing to shew his wrath, and to make his power known, endured with much longsuffering the vessels of wrath fitted to destruction:

^23And that he might make known the riches of his glory on the vessels of mercy, which he had afore prepared unto glory,

^24Even us, whom he hath called, not of the Jews only, but also of the Gentiles?

^25As he saith also in Osee, I will call them my people, which were not my people; and her beloved, which was not beloved.

^26And it shall come to pass, that in the place where it was said unto them, Ye are not my people; there shall they be called the children of the living God.

^27Esaias also crieth concerning Israel, Though the number of the children of Israel be as the sand of the sea, a remnant shall be saved:

^28For he will finish the work, and cut it short in righteousness: because a short work will the Lord make upon the earth.

^29And as Esaias said before, Except the Lord of Sabaoth had left us a seed, we had been as Sodoma, and been made like unto Gomorrha.

^30What shall we say then? That the Gentiles, which followed not after righteousness, have attained to righteousness, even the righteousness which is of faith.

^31But Israel, which followed after the law of righteousness, hath not attained to the law of righteousness.

^32Wherefore? Because they sought it not by faith, but as it were by the works of the law. For they stumbled at that stumblingstone;

^33As it is written, Behold, I lay in Sion a stumblingstone and rock of offence: and whosoever believeth on him shall not be ashamed.

X

^1Brethren, my heart’s desire and prayer to God for Israel is, that they might be saved.

^2For I bear them record that they have a zeal of God, but not according to knowledge.

^3For they being ignorant of God’s righteousness, and going about to establish their own righteousness, have not submitted themselves unto the righteousness of God.

^4For Christ is the end of the law for righteousness to every one that believeth.

^5For Moses describeth the righteousness which is of the law, That the man which doeth those things shall live by them.

^6But the righteousness which is of faith speaketh on this wise, Say not in thine heart, Who shall ascend into heaven? (that is, to bring Christ down from above:)

^7Or, Who shall descend into the deep? (that is, to bring up Christ again from the dead.)

^8But what saith it? The word is nigh thee, even in thy mouth, and in thy heart: that is, the word of faith, which we preach;

^9That if thou shalt confess with thy mouth the Lord Jesus, and shalt believe in thine heart that God hath raised him from the dead, thou shalt be saved.

^10For with the heart man believeth unto righteousness; and with the mouth confession is made unto salvation.

^11For the scripture saith, Whosoever believeth on him shall not be ashamed.

^12For there is no difference between the Jew and the Greek: for the same Lord over all is rich unto all that call upon him.

^13For whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord shall be saved.

^14How then shall they call on him in whom they have not believed? and how shall they believe in him of whom they have not heard? and how shall they hear without a preacher?

^15And how shall they preach, except they be sent? as it is written, How beautiful are the feet of them that preach the gospel of peace, and bring glad tidings of good things!

^16But they have not all obeyed the gospel. For Esaias saith, Lord, who hath believed our report?

^17So then faith cometh by hearing, and hearing by the word of God.

^18But I say, Have they not heard? Yes verily, their sound went into all the earth, and their words unto the ends of the world.

^19But I say, Did not Israel know? First Moses saith, I will provoke you to jealousy by them that are no people, and by a foolish nation I will anger you.

^20But Esaias is very bold, and saith, I was found of them that sought me not; I was made manifest unto them that asked not after me.

^21But to Israel he saith, All day long I have stretched forth my hands unto a disobedient and gainsaying people.

XI

^1I say then, Hath God cast away his people? God forbid. For I also am an Israelite, of the seed of Abraham, of the tribe of Benjamin.

^2God hath not cast away his people which he foreknew. Wot ye not what the scripture saith of Elias? how he maketh intercession to God against Israel saying,

^3Lord, they have killed thy prophets, and digged down thine altars; and I am left alone, and they seek my life.

^4But what saith the answer of God unto him? I have reserved to myself seven thousand men, who have not bowed the knee to the image of Baal.

^5Even so then at this present time also there is a remnant according to the election of grace.

^6And if by grace, then is it no more of works: otherwise grace is no more grace. But if it be of works, then it is no more grace: otherwise work is no more work.

^7What then? Israel hath not obtained that which he seeketh for; but the election hath obtained it, and the rest were blinded.

^8(According as it is written, God hath given them the spirit of slumber, eyes that they should not see, and ears that they should not hear;) unto this day.

^9And David saith, Let their table be made a snare, and a trap, and a stumblingblock, and a recompence unto them:

^10Let their eyes be darkened, that they may not see, and bow down their back alway.

^11I say then, Have they stumbled that they should fall? God forbid: but rather through their fall salvation is come unto the Gentiles, for to provoke them to jealousy.

^12Now if the fall of them be the riches of the world, and the diminishing of them the riches of the Gentiles; how much more their fulness?

^13For I speak to you Gentiles, inasmuch as I am the apostle of the Gentiles, I magnify mine office:

^14If by any means I may provoke to emulation them which are my flesh, and might save some of them.

^15For if the casting away of them be the reconciling of the world, what shall the receiving of them be, but life from the dead?

^16For if the firstfruit be holy, the lump is also holy: and if the root be holy, so are the branches.

^17And if some of the branches be broken off, and thou, being a wild olive tree, wert graffed in among them, and with them partakest of the root and fatness of the olive tree;

^18Boast not against the branches. But if thou boast, thou bearest not the root, but the root thee.

^19Thou wilt say then, The branches were broken off, that I might be graffed in.

^20Well; because of unbelief they were broken off, and thou standest by faith. Be not highminded, but fear:

^21For if God spared not the natural branches, take heed lest he also spare not thee.

^22Behold therefore the goodness and severity of God: on them which fell, severity; but toward thee, goodness, if thou continue in his goodness: otherwise thou also shalt be cut off.

^23And they also, if they abide not still in unbelief, shall be graffed in: for God is able to graff them in again.

^24For if thou wert cut out of the olive tree which is wild by nature, and wert graffed contrary to nature into a good olive tree: how much more shall these, which be the natural branches, be graffed into their own olive tree?

^25For I would not, brethren, that ye should be ignorant of this mystery, lest ye should be wise in your own conceits; that blindness in part is happened to Israel, until the fulness of the Gentiles be come in.

^26And so all Israel shall be saved: as it is written, There shall come out of Sion the Deliverer, and shall turn away ungodliness from Jacob:

^27For this is my covenant unto them, when I shall take away their sins.

^28As concerning the gospel, they are enemies for your sakes: but as touching the election, they are beloved for the father’s sakes.

^29For the gifts and calling of God are without repentance.

^30For as ye in times past have not believed God, yet have now obtained mercy through their unbelief:

^31Even so have these also now not believed, that through your mercy they also may obtain mercy.

^32For God hath concluded them all in unbelief, that he might have mercy upon all.

^33O the depth of the riches both of the wisdom and knowledge of God! how unsearchable are his judgments, and his ways past finding out!

^34For who hath known the mind of the Lord? or who hath been his counsellor?

^35Or who hath first given to him, and it shall be recompensed unto him again?

^36For of him, and through him, and to him, are all things: to whom be glory for ever. Amen.

XII

^1I beseech you therefore, brethren, by the mercies of God, that ye present your bodies a living sacrifice, holy, acceptable unto God, which is your reasonable service.

^2And be not conformed to this world: but be ye transformed by the renewing of your mind, that ye may prove what is that good, and acceptable, and perfect, will of God.

^3For I say, through the grace given unto me, to every man that is among you, not to think of himself more highly than he ought to think; but to think soberly, according as God hath dealt to every man the measure of faith.

^4For as we have many members in one body, and all members have not the same office:

^5So we, being many, are one body in Christ, and every one members one of another.

^6Having then gifts differing according to the grace that is given to us, whether prophecy, let us prophesy according to the proportion of faith;

^7Or ministry, let us wait on our ministering: or he that teacheth, on teaching;

^8Or he that exhorteth, on exhortation: he that giveth, let him do it with simplicity; he that ruleth, with diligence; he that sheweth mercy, with cheerfulness.

^9Let love be without dissimulation. Abhor that which is evil; cleave to that which is good.

^10Be kindly affectioned one to another with brotherly love; in honour preferring one another;

^11Not slothful in business; fervent in spirit; serving the Lord;

^12Rejoicing in hope; patient in tribulation; continuing instant in prayer;

^13Distributing to the necessity of saints; given to hospitality.

^14Bless them which persecute you: bless, and curse not.

^15Rejoice with them that do rejoice, and weep with them that weep.

^16Be of the same mind one toward another. Mind not high things, but condescend to men of low estate. Be not wise in your own conceits.

^17Recompense to no man evil for evil. Provide things honest in the sight of all men.

^18If it be possible, as much as lieth in you, live peaceably with all men.

^19Dearly beloved, avenge not yourselves, but rather give place unto wrath: for it is written, Vengeance is mine; I will repay, saith the Lord.

^20Therefore if thine enemy hunger, feed him; if he thirst, give him drink: for in so doing thou shalt heap coals of fire on his head.

^21Be not overcome of evil, but overcome evil with good.

XIII

^1Let every soul be subject unto the higher powers. For there is no power but of God: the powers that be are ordained of God.

^2Whosoever therefore resisteth the power, resisteth the ordinance of God: and they that resist shall receive to themselves damnation.

^3For rulers are not a terror to good works, but to the evil. Wilt thou then not be afraid of the power? do that which is good, and thou shalt have praise of the same:

^4For he is the minister of God to thee for good. But if thou do that which is evil, be afraid; for he beareth not the sword in vain: for he is the minister of God, a revenger to execute wrath upon him that doeth evil.

^5Wherefore ye must needs be subject, not only for wrath, but also for conscience sake.

^6For for this cause pay ye tribute also: for they are God’s ministers, attending continually upon this very thing.

^7Render therefore to all their dues: tribute to whom tribute is due; custom to whom custom; fear to whom fear; honour to whom honour.

^8Owe no man any thing, but to love one another: for he that loveth another hath fulfilled the law.

^9For this, Thou shalt not commit adultery, Thou shalt not kill, Thou shalt not steal, Thou shalt not bear false witness, Thou shalt not covet; and if there be any other commandment, it is briefly comprehended in this saying, namely, Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself.

^10Love worketh no ill to his neighbour: therefore love is the fulfilling of the law.

^11And that, knowing the time, that now it is high time to awake out of sleep: for now is our salvation nearer than when we believed.

^12The night is far spent, the day is at hand: let us therefore cast off the works of darkness, and let us put on the armour of light.

^13Let us walk honestly, as in the day; not in rioting and drunkenness, not in chambering and wantonness, not in strife and envying.

^14But put ye on the Lord Jesus Christ, and make not provision for the flesh, to fulfil the lusts thereof.

XIV

^1Him that is weak in the faith receive ye, but not to doubtful disputations.

^2For one believeth that he may eat all things: another, who is weak, eateth herbs.

^3Let not him that eateth despise him that eateth not; and let not him which eateth not judge him that eateth: for God hath received him.

^4Who art thou that judgest another man’s servant? to his own master he standeth or falleth. Yea, he shall be holden up: for God is able to make him stand.

^5One man esteemeth one day above another: another esteemeth every day alike. Let every man be fully persuaded in his own mind.

^6He that regardeth the day, regardeth it unto the Lord; and he that regardeth not the day, to the Lord he doth not regard it. He that eateth, eateth to the Lord, for he giveth God thanks; and he that eateth not, to the Lord he eateth not, and giveth God thanks.

^7For none of us liveth to himself, and no man dieth to himself.

^8For whether we live, we live unto the Lord; and whether we die, we die unto the Lord: whether we live therefore, or die, we are the Lord’s.

^9For to this end Christ both died, and rose, and revived, that he might be Lord both of the dead and living.

^10But why dost thou judge thy brother? or why dost thou set at nought thy brother? for we shall all stand before the judgment seat of Christ.

^11For it is written, As I live, saith the Lord, every knee shall bow to me, and every tongue shall confess to God.

^12So then every one of us shall give account of himself to God.

^13Let us not therefore judge one another any more: but judge this rather, that no man put a stumblingblock or an occasion to fall in his brother’s way.

^14I know, and am persuaded by the Lord Jesus, that there is nothing unclean of itself: but to him that esteemeth any thing to be unclean, to him it is unclean.

^15But if thy brother be grieved with thy meat, now walkest thou not charitably. Destroy not him with thy meat, for whom Christ died.

^16Let not then your good be evil spoken of:

^17For the kingdom of God is not meat and drink; but righteousness, and peace, and joy in the Holy Ghost.

^18For he that in these things serveth Christ is acceptable to God, and approved of men.

^19Let us therefore follow after the things which make for peace, and things wherewith one may edify another.

^20For meat destroy not the work of God. All things indeed are pure; but it is evil for that man who eateth with offence.

^21It is good neither to eat flesh, nor to drink wine, nor any thing whereby thy brother stumbleth, or is offended, or is made weak.

^22Hast thou faith? have it to thyself before God. Happy is he that condemneth not himself in that thing which he alloweth.

^23And he that doubteth is damned if he eat, because he eateth not of faith: for whatsoever is not of faith is sin.

XV

^1We then that are strong ought to bear the infirmities of the weak, and not to please ourselves.

^2Let every one of us please his neighbour for his good to edification.

^3For even Christ pleased not himself; but, as it is written, The reproaches of them that reproached thee fell on me.

^4For whatsoever things were written aforetime were written for our learning, that we through patience and comfort of the scriptures might have hope.

^5Now the God of patience and consolation grant you to be likeminded one toward another according to Christ Jesus:

^6That ye may with one mind and one mouth glorify God, even the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ.

^7Wherefore receive ye one another, as Christ also received us to the glory of God.

^8Now I say that Jesus Christ was a minister of the circumcision for the truth of God, to confirm the promises made unto the fathers:

^9And that the Gentiles might glorify God for his mercy; as it is written, For this cause I will confess to thee among the Gentiles, and sing unto thy name.

^10And again he saith, Rejoice, ye Gentiles, with his people.

^11And again, Praise the Lord, all ye Gentiles; and laud him, all ye people.

^12And again, Esaias saith, There shall be a root of Jesse, and he that shall rise to reign over the Gentiles; in him shall the Gentiles trust.

^13Now the God of hope fill you with all joy and peace in believing, that ye may abound in hope, through the power of the Holy Ghost.

^14And I myself also am persuaded of you, my brethren, that ye also are full of goodness, filled with all knowledge, able also to admonish one another.

^15Nevertheless, brethren, I have written the more boldly unto you in some sort, as putting you in mind, because of the grace that is given to me of God,

^16That I should be the minister of Jesus Christ to the Gentiles, ministering the gospel of God, that the offering up of the Gentiles might be acceptable, being sanctified by the Holy Ghost.

^17I have therefore whereof I may glory through Jesus Christ in those things which pertain to God.

^18For I will not dare to speak of any of those things which Christ hath not wrought by me, to make the Gentiles obedient, by word and deed,

^19Through mighty signs and wonders, by the power of the Spirit of God; so that from Jerusalem, and round about unto Illyricum, I have fully preached the gospel of Christ.

^20Yea, so have I strived to preach the gospel, not where Christ was named, lest I should build upon another man’s foundation:

^21But as it is written, To whom he was not spoken of, they shall see: and they that have not heard shall understand.

^22For which cause also I have been much hindered from coming to you.

^23But now having no more place in these parts, and having a great desire these many years to come unto you;

^24Whensoever I take my journey into Spain, I will come to you: for I trust to see you in my journey, and to be brought on my way thitherward by you, if first I be somewhat filled with your company.

^25But now I go unto Jerusalem to minister unto the saints.

^26For it hath pleased them of Macedonia and Achaia to make a certain contribution for the poor saints which are at Jerusalem.

^27It hath pleased them verily; and their debtors they are. For if the Gentiles have been made partakers of their spiritual things, their duty is also to minister unto them in carnal things.

^28When therefore I have performed this, and have sealed to them this fruit, I will come by you into Spain.

^29And I am sure that, when I come unto you, I shall come in the fulness of the blessing of the gospel of Christ.

^30Now I beseech you, brethren, for the Lord Jesus Christ’s sake, and for the love of the Spirit, that ye strive together with me in your prayers to God for me;

^31That I may be delivered from them that do not believe in Judaea; and that my service which I have for Jerusalem may be accepted of the saints;

^32That I may come unto you with joy by the will of God, and may with you be refreshed.

^33Now the God of peace be with you all. Amen.

XVI

^1I commend unto you Phebe our sister, which is a servant of the church which is at Cenchrea:

^2That ye receive her in the Lord, as becometh saints, and that ye assist her in whatsoever business she hath need of you: for she hath been a succourer of many, and of myself also.

^3Greet Priscilla and Aquila my helpers in Christ Jesus:

^4Who have for my life laid down their own necks: unto whom not only I give thanks, but also all the churches of the Gentiles.

^5Likewise greet the church that is in their house. Salute my well-beloved Epaenetus, who is the firstfruits of Achaia unto Christ.

^6Greet Mary, who bestowed much labour on us.

^7Salute Andronicus and Junia, my kinsmen, and my fellow-prisoners, who are of note among the apostles, who also were in Christ before me.

^8Greet Amplias my beloved in the Lord.

^9Salute Urbane, our helper in Christ, and Stachys my beloved.

^10Salute Apelles approved in Christ. Salute them which are of Aristobulus’ household.

^11Salute Herodion my kinsman. Greet them that be of the household of Narcissus, which are in the Lord.

^12Salute Tryphena and Tryphosa, who labour in the Lord. Salute the beloved Persis, which laboured much in the Lord.

^13Salute Rufus chosen in the Lord, and his mother and mine.

^14Salute Asyncritus, Phlegon, Hermas, Patrobas, Hermes, and the brethren which are with them.

^15Salute Philologus, and Julia, Nereus, and his sister, and Olympas, and all the saints which are with them.

^16Salute one another with an holy kiss. The churches of Christ salute you.

^17Now I beseech you, brethren, mark them which cause divisions and offences contrary to the doctrine which ye have learned; and avoid them.

^18For they that are such serve not our Lord Jesus Christ, but their own belly; and by good words and fair speeches deceive the hearts of the simple.

^19For your obedience is come abroad unto all men. I am glad therefore on your behalf: but yet I would have you wise unto that which is good, and simple concerning evil.

^20And the God of peace shall bruise Satan under your feet shortly. The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you. Amen.

^21Timotheus my workfellow, and Lucius, and Jason, and Sosipater, my kinsmen, salute you.

^22I Tertius, who wrote this epistle, salute you in the Lord.

^23Gaius mine host, and of the whole church, saluteth you. Erastus the chamberlain of the city saluteth you, and Quartus a brother.

^24The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you all. Amen.

^25Now to him that is of power to stablish you according to my gospel, and the preaching of Jesus Christ, according to the revelation of the mystery, which was kept secret since the world began,

^26But now is made manifest, and by the scriptures of the prophets, according to the commandment of the everlasting God, made known to all nations for the obedience of faith:

^27To God only wise, be glory through Jesus Christ for ever. Amen.

I Corinthians 1

1^1Paul called to be an apostle of Jesus Christ through the will of God, and Sosthenes our brother,

^2Unto the church of God which is at Corinth, to them that are sanctified in Christ Jesus, called to be saints, with all that in every place call upon the name of Jesus Christ our Lord, both their’s and our’s:

^3Grace be unto you, and peace, from God our Father, and from the Lord Jesus Christ.

^4I thank my God always on your behalf, for the grace of God which is given you by Jesus Christ;

^5That in every thing ye are enriched by him, in all utterance, and in all knowledge;

^6Even as the testimony of Christ was confirmed in you:

^7So that ye come behind in no gift; waiting for the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ:

^8Who shall also confirm you unto the end, that ye may be blameless in the day of our Lord Jesus Christ.

^9God is faithful, by whom ye were called unto the fellowship of his Son Jesus Christ our Lord.

^10Now I beseech you, brethren, by the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, that ye all speak the same thing, and that there be no divisions among you; but that ye be perfectly joined together in the same mind and in the same judgment.

^11For it hath been declared unto me of you, my brethren, by them which are of the house of Chloe, that there are contentions among you.

^12Now this I say, that every one of you saith, I am of Paul; and I of Apollos; and I of Cephas; and I of Christ.

^13Is Christ divided? was Paul crucified for you? or were ye baptized in the name of Paul?

^14I thank God that I baptized none of you, but Crispus and Gaius;

^15Lest any should say that I had baptized in mine own name.

^16And I baptized also the household of Stephanas: besides, I know not whether I baptized any other.

^17For Christ sent me not to baptize, but to preach the gospel: not with wisdom of words, lest the cross of Christ should be made of none effect.

^18For the preaching of the cross is to them that perish foolishness; but unto us which are saved it is the power of God.

^19For it is written, I will destroy the wisdom of the wise, and will bring to nothing the understanding of the prudent.

^20Where is the wise? where is the scribe? where is the disputer of this world? hath not God made foolish the wisdom of this world?

^21For after that in the wisdom of God the world by wisdom knew not God, it pleased God by the foolishness of preaching to save them that believe.

^22For the Jews require a sign, and the Greeks seek after wisdom:

^23But we preach Christ crucified, unto the Jews a stumblingblock, and unto the Greeks foolishness;

^24But unto them which are called, both Jews and Greeks, Christ the power of God, and the wisdom of God.

^25Because the foolishness of God is wiser than men; and the weakness of God is stronger than men.

^26For ye see your calling, brethren, how that not many wise men after the flesh, not many mighty, not many noble, are called:

^27But God hath chosen the foolish things of the world to confound the wise; and God hath chosen the weak things of the world to confound the things which are mighty;

^28And base things of the world, and things which are despised, hath God chosen, yea, and things which are not, to bring to nought things that are:

^29That no flesh should glory in his presence.

^30But of him are ye in Christ Jesus, who of God is made unto us wisdom, and righteousness, and sanctification, and redemption:

^31That, according as it is written, He that glorieth, let him glory in the Lord.

I Corinthians 2

2^1And I, brethren, when I came to you, came not with excellency of speech or of wisdom, declaring unto you the testimony of God.

^2For I determined not to know any thing among you, save Jesus Christ, and him crucified.

^3And I was with you in weakness, and in fear, and in much trembling.

^4And my speech and my preaching was not with enticing words of man’s wisdom, but in demonstration of the Spirit and of power:

^5That your faith should not stand in the wisdom of men, but in the power of God.

^6Howbeit we speak wisdom among them that are perfect: yet not the wisdom of this world, nor of the princes of this world, that come to nought:

^7But we speak the wisdom of God in a mystery, even the hidden wisdom, which God ordained before the world unto our glory:

^8Which none of the princes of this world knew: for had they known it, they would not have crucified the Lord of glory.

^9But as it is written, Eye hath not seen, nor ear heard, neither have entered into the heart of man, the things which God hath prepared for them that love him.

^10But God hath revealed them unto us by his Spirit: for the Spirit searcheth all things, yea, the deep things of God.

^11For what man knoweth the things of a man, save the spirit of man which is in him? even so the things of God knoweth no man, but the Spirit of God.

^12Now we have received, not the spirit of the world, but the spirit which is of God; that we might know the things that are freely given to us of God.

^13Which things also we speak, not in the words which man’s wisdom teacheth, but which the Holy Ghost teacheth; comparing spiritual things with spiritual.

^14But the natural man receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God: for they are foolishness unto him: neither can he know them, because they are spiritually discerned.

^15But he that is spiritual judgeth all things, yet he himself is judged of no man.

^16For who hath known the mind of the Lord, that he may instruct him? But we have the mind of Christ.

I Corinthians 3

3^1And I, brethren, could not speak unto you as unto spiritual, but as unto carnal, even as unto babes in Christ.

^2I have fed you with milk, and not with meat: for hitherto ye were not able to bear it, neither yet now are ye able.

^3For ye are yet carnal: for whereas there is among you envying, and strife, and divisions, are ye not carnal, and walk as men?

^4For while one saith, I am of Paul; and another, I am of Apollos; are ye not carnal?

^5Who then is Paul, and who is Apollos, but ministers by whom ye believed, even as the Lord gave to every man?

^6I have planted, Apollos watered; but God gave the increase.

^7So then neither is he that planteth any thing, neither he that watereth; but God that giveth the increase.

^8Now he that planteth and he that watereth are one: and every man shall receive his own reward according to his own labour.

^9For we are labourers together with God: ye are God’s husbandry, ye are God’s building.

^10According to the grace of God which is given unto me, as a wise masterbuilder, I have laid the foundation, and another buildeth thereon. But let every man take heed how he buildeth thereupon.

^11For other foundation can no man lay than that is laid, which is Jesus Christ.

^12Now if any man build upon this foundation gold, silver, precious stones, wood, hay, stubble;

^13Every man’s work shall be made manifest: for the day shall declare it, because it shall be revealed by fire; and the fire shall try every man’s work of what sort it is.

^14If any man’s work abide which he hath built thereupon, he shall receive a reward.

^15If any man’s work shall be burned, he shall suffer loss: but he himself shall be saved; yet so as by fire.

^16Know ye not that ye are the temple of God, and that the Spirit of God dwelleth in you?

^17If any man defile the temple of God, him shall God destroy; for the temple of God is holy, which temple ye are.

^18Let no man deceive himself. If any man among you seemeth to be wise in this world, let him become a fool, that he may be wise.

^19For the wisdom of this world is foolishness with God. For it is written, He taketh the wise in their own craftiness.

^20And again, The Lord knoweth the thoughts of the wise, that they are vain.

^21Therefore let no man glory in men. For all things are your’s;

^22Whether Paul, or Apollos, or Cephas, or the world, or life, or death, or things present, or things to come; all are your’s;

^23And ye are Christ’s; and Christ is God’s.

I Corinthians 4

4^1Let a man so account of us, as of the ministers of Christ, and stewards of the mysteries of God.

^2Moreover it is required in stewards, that a man be found faithful.

^3But with me it is a very small thing that I should be judged of you, or of man’s judgment: yea, I judge not mine own self.

^4For I know nothing by myself; yet am I not hereby justified: but he that judgeth me is the Lord.

^5Therefore judge nothing before the time, until the Lord come, who both will bring to light the hidden things of darkness, and will make manifest the counsels of the hearts: and then shall every man have praise of God.

^6And these things, brethren, I have in a figure transferred to myself and to Apollos for your sakes; that ye might learn in us not to think of men above that which is written, that no one of you be puffed up for one against another.

^7For who maketh thee to differ from another? and what hast thou that thou didst not receive? now if thou didst receive it, why dost thou glory, as if thou hadst not received it?

^8Now ye are full, now ye are rich, ye have reigned as kings without us: and I would to God ye did reign, that we also might reign with you.

^9For I think that God hath set forth us the apostles last, as it were appointed to death: for we are made a spectacle unto the world, and to angels, and to men.

^10We are fools for Christ’s sake, but ye are wise in Christ; we are weak, but ye are strong; ye are honourable, but we are despised.

^11Even unto this present hour we both hunger, and thirst, and are naked, and are buffeted, and have no certain dwellingplace;

^12And labour, working with our own hands: being reviled, we bless; being persecuted, we suffer it:

^13Being defamed, we intreat: we are made as the filth of the world, and are the offscouring of all things unto this day.

^14I write not these things to shame you, but as my beloved sons I warn you.

^15For though ye have ten thousand instructors in Christ, yet have ye not many fathers: for in Christ Jesus I have begotten you through the gospel.

^16Wherefore I beseech you, be ye followers of me.

^17For this cause have I sent unto you Timotheus, who is my beloved son, and faithful in the Lord, who shall bring you into remembrance of my ways which be in Christ, as I teach every where in every church.

^18Now some are puffed up, as though I would not come to you.

^19But I will come to you shortly, if the Lord will, and will know, not the speech of them which are puffed up, but the power.

^20For the kingdom of God is not in word, but in power.

^21What will ye? shall I come unto you with a rod, or in love, and in the spirit of meekness?

I Corinthians 5

5^1It is reported commonly that there is fornication among you, and such fornication as is not so much as named among the Gentiles, that one should have his father’s wife.

^2And ye are puffed up, and have not rather mourned, that he that hath done this deed might be taken away from among you.

^3For I verily, as absent in body, but present in spirit, have judged already, as though I were present, concerning him that hath so done this deed,

^4In the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, when ye are gathered together, and my spirit, with the power of our Lord Jesus Christ,

^5To deliver such an one unto Satan for the destruction of the flesh, that the spirit may be saved in the day of the Lord Jesus.

^6Your glorying is not good. Know ye not that a little leaven leaveneth the whole lump?

^7Purge out therefore the old leaven, that ye may be a new lump, as ye are unleavened. For even Christ our passover is sacrificed for us:

^8Therefore let us keep the feast, not with old leaven, neither with the leaven of malice and wickedness; but with the unleavened bread of sincerity and truth.

^9I wrote unto you in an epistle not to company with fornicators:

^10Yet not altogether with the fornicators of this world, or with the covetous, or extortioners, or with idolaters; for then must ye needs go out of the world.

^11But now I have written unto you not to keep company, if any man that is called a brother be a fornicator, or covetous, or an idolater, or a railer, or a drunkard, or an extortioner; with such an one no not to eat.

^12For what have I to do to judge them also that are without? do not ye judge them that are within?

^13But them that are without God judgeth. Therefore put away from among yourselves that wicked person.

I Corinthians 6

6^1Dare any of you, having a matter against another, go to law before the unjust, and not before the saints?

^2Do ye not know that the saints shall judge the world? and if the world shall be judged by you, are ye unworthy to judge the smallest matters?

^3Know ye not that we shall judge angels? how much more things that pertain to this life?

^4If then ye have judgments of things pertaining to this life, set them to judge who are least esteemed in the church.

^5I speak to your shame. Is it so, that there is not a wise man among you? no, not one that shall be able to judge between his brethren?

^6But brother goeth to law with brother, and that before the unbelievers.

^7Now therefore there is utterly a fault among you, because ye go to law one with another. Why do ye not rather take wrong? why do ye not rather suffer yourselves to be defrauded?

^8Nay, ye do wrong, and defraud, and that your brethren.

^9Know ye not that the unrighteous shall not inherit the kingdom of God? Be not deceived: neither fornicators, nor idolaters, nor adulterers, nor effeminate, nor abusers of themselves with mankind,

^10Nor thieves, nor covetous, nor drunkards, nor revilers, nor extortioners, shall inherit the kingdom of God.

^11And such were some of you: but ye are washed, but ye are sanctified, but ye are justified in the name of the Lord Jesus, and by the Spirit of our God.

^12All things are lawful unto me, but all things are not expedient: all things are lawful for me, but I will not be brought under the power of any.

^13Meats for the belly, and the belly for meats: but God shall destroy both it and them. Now the body is not for fornication, but for the Lord; and the Lord for the body.

^14And God hath both raised up the Lord, and will also raise up us by his own power.

^15Know ye not that your bodies are the members of Christ? shall I then take the members of Christ, and make them the members of an harlot? God forbid.

^16What? know ye not that he which is joined to an harlot is one body? for two, saith he, shall be one flesh.

^17But he that is joined unto the Lord is one spirit.

^18Flee fornication. Every sin that a man doeth is without the body; but he that committeth fornication sinneth against his own body.

^19What? know ye not that your body is the temple of the Holy Ghost which is in you, which ye have of God, and ye are not your own?

^20For ye are bought with a price: therefore glorify God in your body, and in your spirit, which are God’s.

I Corinthians 7

7^1Now concerning the things whereof ye wrote unto me: It is good for a man not to touch a woman.

^2Nevertheless, to avoid fornication, let every man have his own wife, and let every woman have her own husband.

^3Let the husband render unto the wife due benevolence: and likewise also the wife unto the husband.

^4The wife hath not power of her own body, but the husband: and likewise also the husband hath not power of his own body, but the wife.

^5Defraud ye not one the other, except it be with consent for a time, that ye may give yourselves to fasting and prayer; and come together again, that Satan tempt you not for your incontinency.

^6But I speak this by permission, and not of commandment.

^7For I would that all men were even as I myself. But every man hath his proper gift of God, one after this manner, and another after that.

^8I say therefore to the unmarried and widows, It is good for them if they abide even as I.

^9But if they cannot contain, let them marry: for it is better to marry than to burn.

^10And unto the married I command, yet not I, but the Lord, Let not the wife depart from her husband:

^11But and if she depart, let her remain unmarried or be reconciled to her husband: and let not the husband put away his wife.

^12But to the rest speak I, not the Lord: If any brother hath a wife that believeth not, and she be pleased to dwell with him, let him not put her away.

^13And the woman which hath an husband that believeth not, and if he be pleased to dwell with her, let her not leave him.

^14For the unbelieving husband is sanctified by the wife, and the unbelieving wife is sanctified by the husband: else were your children unclean; but now are they holy.

^15But if the unbelieving depart, let him depart. A brother or a sister is not under bondage in such cases: but God hath called us to peace.

^16For what knowest thou, O wife, whether thou shalt save thy husband? or how knowest thou, O man, whether thou shalt save thy wife?

^17But as God hath distributed to every man, as the Lord hath called every one, so let him walk. And so ordain I in all churches.

^18Is any man called being circumcised? let him not become uncircumcised. Is any called in uncircumcision? let him not be circumcised.

^19Circumcision is nothing, and uncircumcision is nothing, but the keeping of the commandments of God.

^20Let every man abide in the same calling wherein he was called.

^21Art thou called being a servant? care not for it: but if thou mayest be made free, use it rather.

^22For he that is called in the Lord, being a servant, is the Lord’s freeman: likewise also he that is called, being free, is Christ’s servant.

^23Ye are bought with a price; be not ye the servants of men.

^24Brethren, let every man, wherein he is called, therein abide with God.

^25Now concerning virgins I have no commandment of the Lord: yet I give my judgment, as one that hath obtained mercy of the Lord to be faithful.

^26I suppose therefore that this is good for the present distress, I say, that it is good for a man so to be.

^27Art thou bound unto a wife? seek not to be loosed. Art thou loosed from a wife? seek not a wife.

^28But and if thou marry, thou hast not sinned; and if a virgin marry, she hath not sinned. Nevertheless such shall have trouble in the flesh: but I spare you.

^29But this I say, brethren, the time is short: it remaineth, that both they that have wives be as though they had none;

^30And they that weep, as though they wept not; and they that rejoice, as though they rejoiced not; and they that buy, as though they possessed not;

^31And they that use this world, as not abusing it: for the fashion of this world passeth away.

^32But I would have you without carefulness. He that is unmarried careth for the things that belong to the Lord, how he may please the Lord:

^33But he that is married careth for the things that are of the world, how he may please his wife.

^34There is difference also between a wife and a virgin. The unmarried woman careth for the things of the Lord, that she may be holy both in body and in spirit: but she that is married careth for the things of the world, how she may please her husband.

^35And this I speak for your own profit; not that I may cast a snare upon you, but for that which is comely, and that ye may attend upon the Lord without distraction.

^36But if any man think that he behaveth himself uncomely toward his virgin, if she pass the flower of her age, and need so require, let him do what he will, he sinneth not: let them marry.

^37Nevertheless he that standeth stedfast in his heart, having no necessity, but hath power over his own will, and hath so decreed in his heart that he will keep his virgin, doeth well.

^38So then he that giveth her in marriage doeth well; but he that giveth her not in marriage doeth better.

^39The wife is bound by the law as long as her husband liveth; but if her husband be dead, she is at liberty to be married to whom she will; only in the Lord.

^40But she is happier if she so abide, after my judgment: and I think also that I have the Spirit of God.

I Corinthians 8

8^1Now as touching things offered unto idols, we know that we all have knowledge. Knowledge puffeth up, but charity edifieth.

^2And if any man think that he knoweth any thing, he knoweth nothing yet as he ought to know.

^3But if any man love God, the same is known of him.

^4As concerning therefore the eating of those things that are offered in sacrifice unto idols, we know that an idol is nothing in the world, and that there is none other God but one.

^5For though there be that are called gods, whether in heaven or in earth, (as there be gods many, and lords many,)

^6But to us there is but one God, the Father, of whom are all things, and we in him; and one Lord Jesus Christ, by whom are all things, and we by him.

^7Howbeit there is not in every man that knowledge: for some with conscience of the idol unto this hour eat it as a thing offered unto an idol; and their conscience being weak is defiled.

^8But meat commendeth us not to God: for neither, if we eat, are we the better; neither, if we eat not, are we the worse.

^9But take heed lest by any means this liberty of your’s become a stumblingblock to them that are weak.

^10For if any man see thee which hast knowledge sit at meat in the idol’s temple, shall not the conscience of him which is weak be emboldened to eat those things which are offered to idols;

^11And through thy knowledge shall the weak brother perish, for whom Christ died?

^12But when ye sin so against the brethren, and wound their weak conscience, ye sin against Christ.

^13Wherefore, if meat make my brother to offend, I will eat no flesh while the world standeth, lest I make my brother to offend.

I Corinthians 9

9^1Am I not an apostle? am I not free? have I not seen Jesus Christ our Lord? are not ye my work in the Lord?

^2If I be not an apostle unto others, yet doubtless I am to you: for the seal of mine apostleship are ye in the Lord.

^3Mine answer to them that do examine me is this,

^4Have we not power to eat and to drink?

^5Have we not power to lead about a sister, a wife, as well as other apostles, and as the brethren of the Lord, and Cephas?

^6Or I only and Barnabas, have not we power to forbear working?

^7Who goeth a warfare any time at his own charges? who planteth a vineyard, and eateth not of the fruit thereof? or who feedeth a flock, and eateth not of the milk of the flock?

^8Say I these things as a man? or saith not the law the same also?

^9For it is written in the law of Moses, Thou shalt not muzzle the mouth of the ox that treadeth out the corn. Doth God take care for oxen?

^10Or saith he it altogether for our sakes? For our sakes, no doubt, this is written: that he that ploweth should plow in hope; and that he that thresheth in hope should be partaker of his hope.

^11If we have sown unto you spiritual things, is it a great thing if we shall reap your carnal things?

^12If others be partakers of this power over you, are not we rather? Nevertheless we have not used this power; but suffer all things, lest we should hinder the gospel of Christ.

^13Do ye not know that they which minister about holy things live of the things of the temple? and they which wait at the altar are partakers with the altar?

^14Even so hath the Lord ordained that they which preach the gospel should live of the gospel.

^15But I have used none of these things: neither have I written these things, that it should be so done unto me: for it were better for me to die, than that any man should make my glorying void.

^16For though I preach the gospel, I have nothing to glory of: for necessity is laid upon me; yea, woe is unto me, if I preach not the gospel!

^17For if I do this thing willingly, I have a reward: but if against my will, a dispensation of the gospel is committed unto me.

^18What is my reward then? Verily that, when I preach the gospel, I may make the gospel of Christ without charge, that I abuse not my power in the gospel.

^19For though I be free from all men, yet have I made myself servant unto all, that I might gain the more.

^20And unto the Jews I became as a Jew, that I might gain the Jews; to them that are under the law, as under the law, that I might gain them that are under the law;

^21To them that are without law, as without law, (being not without law to God, but under the law to Christ,) that I might gain them that are without law.

^22To the weak became I as weak, that I might gain the weak: I am made all things to all men, that I might by all means save some.

^23And this I do for the gospel’s sake, that I might be partaker thereof with you.

^24Know ye not that they which run in a race run all, but one receiveth the prize? So run, that ye may obtain.

^25And every man that striveth for the mastery is temperate in all things. Now they do it to obtain a corruptible crown; but we an incorruptible.

^26I therefore so run, not as uncertainly; so fight I, not as one that beateth the air:

^27But I keep under my body, and bring it into subjection: lest that by any means, when I have preached to others, I myself should be a castaway.

I Corinthians 10

10^1Moreover, brethren, I would not that ye should be ignorant, how that all our fathers were under the cloud, and all passed through the sea;

^2And were all baptized unto Moses in the cloud and in the sea;

^3And did all eat the same spiritual meat;

^4And did all drink the same spiritual drink: for they drank of that spiritual Rock that followed them: and that Rock was Christ.

^5But with many of them God was not well pleased: for they were overthrown in the wilderness.

^6Now these things were our examples, to the intent we should not lust after evil things, as they also lusted.

^7Neither be ye idolaters, as were some of them; as it is written, The people sat down to eat and drink, and rose up to play.

^8Neither let us commit fornication, as some of them committed, and fell in one day three and twenty thousand.

^9Neither let us tempt Christ, as some of them also tempted, and were destroyed of serpents.

^10Neither murmur ye, as some of them also murmured, and were destroyed of the destroyer.

^11Now all these things happened unto them for ensamples: and they are written for our admonition, upon whom the ends of the world are come.

^12Wherefore let him that thinketh he standeth take heed lest he fall.

^13There hath no temptation taken you but such as is common to man: but God is faithful, who will not suffer you to be tempted above that ye are able; but will with the temptation also make a way to escape, that ye may be able to bear it.

^14Wherefore, my dearly beloved, flee from idolatry.

^15I speak as to wise men; judge ye what I say.

^16The cup of blessing which we bless, is it not the communion of the blood of Christ? The bread which we break, is it not the communion of the body of Christ?

^17For we being many are one bread, and one body: for we are all partakers of that one bread.

^18Behold Israel after the flesh: are not they which eat of the sacrifices partakers of the altar?

^19What say I then? that the idol is any thing, or that which is offered in sacrifice to idols is any thing?

^20But I say, that the things which the Gentiles sacrifice, they sacrifice to devils, and not to God: and I would not that ye should have fellowship with devils.

^21Ye cannot drink the cup of the Lord, and the cup of devils: ye cannot be partakers of the Lord’s table, and of the table of devils.

^22Do we provoke the Lord to jealousy? are we stronger than he?

^23All things are lawful for me, but all things are not expedient: all things are lawful for me, but all things edify not.

^24Let no man seek his own, but every man another’s wealth.

^25Whatsoever is sold in the shambles, that eat, asking no question for conscience sake:

^26For the earth is the Lord’s, and the fulness thereof.

^27If any of them that believe not bid you to a feast, and ye be disposed to go; whatsoever is set before you, eat, asking no question for conscience sake.

^28But if any man say unto you, This is offered in sacrifice unto idols, eat not for his sake that shewed it, and for conscience sake: for the earth is the Lord’s, and the fulness thereof:

^29Conscience, I say, not thine own, but of the other: for why is my liberty judged of another man’s conscience?

^30For if I by grace be a partaker, why am I evil spoken of for that for which I give thanks?

^31Whether therefore ye eat, or drink, or whatsoever ye do, do all to the glory of God.

^32Give none offence, neither to the Jews, nor to the Gentiles, nor to the church of God:

^33Even as I please all men in all things, not seeking mine own profit, but the profit of many, that they may be saved.

I Corinthians 11

11^1Be ye followers of me, even as I also am of Christ.

^2Now I praise you, brethren, that ye remember me in all things, and keep the ordinances, as I delivered them to you.

^3But I would have you know, that the head of every man is Christ; and the head of the woman is the man; and the head of Christ is God.

^4Every man praying or prophesying, having his head covered, dishonoureth his head.

^5But every woman that prayeth or prophesieth with her head uncovered dishonoureth her head: for that is even all one as if she were shaven.

^6For if the woman be not covered, let her also be shorn: but if it be a shame for a woman to be shorn or shaven, let her be covered.

^7For a man indeed ought not to cover his head, forasmuch as he is the image and glory of God: but the woman is the glory of the man.

^8For the man is not of the woman: but the woman of the man.

^9Neither was the man created for the woman; but the woman for the man.

^10For this cause ought the woman to have power on her head because of the angels.

^11Nevertheless neither is the man without the woman, neither the woman without the man, in the Lord.

^12For as the woman is of the man, even so is the man also by the woman; but all things of God.

^13Judge in yourselves: is it comely that a woman pray unto God uncovered?

^14Doth not even nature itself teach you, that, if a man have long hair, it is a shame unto him?

^15But if a woman have long hair, it is a glory to her: for her hair is given her for a covering.

^16But if any man seem to be contentious, we have no such custom, neither the churches of God.

^17Now in this that I declare unto you I praise you not, that ye come together not for the better, but for the worse.

^18For first of all, when ye come together in the church, I hear that there be divisions among you; and I partly believe it.

^19For there must be also heresies among you, that they which are approved may be made manifest among you.

^20When ye come together therefore into one place, this is not to eat the Lord’s supper.

^21For in eating every one taketh before other his own supper: and one is hungry, and another is drunken.

^22What? have ye not houses to eat and to drink in? or despise ye the church of God, and shame them that have not? What shall I say to you? shall I praise you in this? I praise you not.

^23For I have received of the Lord that which also I delivered unto you, That the Lord Jesus the same night in which he was betrayed took bread:

^24And when he had given thanks, he brake it, and said, Take, eat: this is my body, which is broken for you: this do in remembrance of me.

^25After the same manner also he took the cup, when he had supped, saying, This cup is the new testament in my blood: this do ye, as oft as ye drink it, in remembrance of me.

^26For as often as ye eat this bread, and drink this cup, ye do shew the Lord’s death till he come.

^27Wherefore whosoever shall eat this bread, and drink this cup of the Lord, unworthily, shall be guilty of the body and blood of the Lord.

^28But let a man examine himself, and so let him eat of that bread, and drink of that cup.

^29For he that eateth and drinketh unworthily, eateth and drinketh damnation to himself, not discerning the Lord’s body.

^30For this cause many are weak and sickly among you, and many sleep.

^31For if we would judge ourselves, we should not be judged.

^32But when we are judged, we are chastened of the Lord, that we should not be condemned with the world.

^33Wherefore, my brethren, when ye come together to eat, tarry one for another.

^34And if any man hunger, let him eat at home; that ye come not together unto condemnation. And the rest will I set in order when I come.

I Corinthians 12

12^1Now concerning spiritual gifts, brethren, I would not have you ignorant.

^2Ye know that ye were Gentiles, carried away unto these dumb idols, even as ye were led.

^3Wherefore I give you to understand, that no man speaking by the Spirit of God calleth Jesus accursed: and that no man can say that Jesus is the Lord, but by the Holy Ghost.

^4Now there are diversities of gifts, but the same Spirit.

^5And there are differences of administrations, but the same Lord.

^6And there are diversities of operations, but it is the same God which worketh all in all.

^7But the manifestation of the Spirit is given to every man to profit withal.

^8For to one is given by the Spirit the word of wisdom; to another the word of knowledge by the same Spirit;

^9To another faith by the same Spirit; to another the gifts of healing by the same Spirit;

^10To another the working of miracles; to another prophecy; to another discerning of spirits; to another divers kinds of tongues; to another the interpretation of tongues:

^11But all these worketh that one and the selfsame Spirit, dividing to every man severally as he will.

^12For as the body is one, and hath many members, and all the members of that one body, being many, are one body: so also is Christ.

^13For by one Spirit are we all baptized into one body, whether we be Jews or Gentiles, whether we be bond or free; and have been all made to drink into one Spirit.

^14For the body is not one member, but many.

^15If the foot shall say, Because I am not the hand, I am not of the body; is it therefore not of the body?

^16And if the ear shall say, Because I am not the eye, I am not of the body; is it therefore not of the body?

^17If the whole body were an eye, where were the hearing? If the whole were hearing, where were the smelling?

^18But now hath God set the members every one of them in the body, as it hath pleased him.

^19And if they were all one member, where were the body?

^20But now are they many members, yet but one body.

^21And the eye cannot say unto the hand, I have no need of thee: nor again the head to the feet, I have no need of you.

^22Nay, much more those members of the body, which seem to be more feeble, are necessary:

^23And those members of the body, which we think to be less honourable, upon these we bestow more abundant honour; and our uncomely parts have more abundant comeliness.

^24For our comely parts have no need: but God hath tempered the body together, having given more abundant honour to that part which lacked.

^25That there should be no schism in the body; but that the members should have the same care one for another.

^26And whether one member suffer, all the members suffer with it; or one member be honoured, all the members rejoice with it.

^27Now ye are the body of Christ, and members in particular.

^28And God hath set some in the church, first apostles, secondarily prophets, thirdly teachers, after that miracles, then gifts of healings, helps, governments, diversities of tongues.

^29Are all apostles? are all prophets? are all teachers? are all workers of miracles?

^30Have all the gifts of healing? do all speak with tongues? do all interpret?

^31But covet earnestly the best gifts: and yet shew I unto you a more excellent way.

I Corinthians 13

13^1Though I speak with the tongues of men and of angels, and have not charity, I am become as sounding brass, or a tinkling cymbal.

^2And though I have the gift of prophecy, and understand all mysteries, and all knowledge; and though I have all faith, so that I could remove mountains, and have not charity, I am nothing.

^3And though I bestow all my goods to feed the poor, and though I give my body to be burned, and have not charity, it profiteth me nothing.

^4Charity suffereth long, and is kind; charity envieth not; charity vaunteth not itself, is not puffed up,

^5Doth not behave itself unseemly, seeketh not her own, is not easily provoked, thinketh no evil;

^6Rejoiceth not in iniquity, but rejoiceth in the truth;

^7Beareth all things, believeth all things, hopeth all things, endureth all things.

^8Charity never faileth: but whether there be prophecies, they shall fail; whether there be tongues, they shall cease; whether there be knowledge, it shall vanish away.

^9For we know in part, and we prophesy in part.

^10But when that which is perfect is come, then that which is in part shall be done away.

^11When I was a child, I spake as a child, I understood as a child, I thought as a child: but when I became a man, I put away childish things.

^12For now we see through a glass, darkly; but then face to face: now I know in part; but then shall I know even as also I am known.

^13And now abideth faith, hope, charity, these three; but the greatest of these is charity.

I Corinthians 14

14^1Follow after charity, and desire spiritual gifts, but rather that ye may prophesy.

^2For he that speaketh in an unknown tongue speaketh not unto men, but unto God: for no man understandeth him; howbeit in the spirit he speaketh mysteries.

^3But he that prophesieth speaketh unto men to edification, and exhortation, and comfort.

^4He that speaketh in an unknown tongue edifieth himself; but he that prophesieth edifieth the church.

^5I would that ye all spake with tongues but rather that ye prophesied: for greater is he that prophesieth than he that speaketh with tongues, except he interpret, that the church may receive edifying.

^6Now, brethren, if I come unto you speaking with tongues, what shall I profit you, except I shall speak to you either by revelation, or by knowledge, or by prophesying, or by doctrine?

^7And even things without life giving sound, whether pipe or harp, except they give a distinction in the sounds, how shall it be known what is piped or harped?

^8For if the trumpet give an uncertain sound, who shall prepare himself to the battle?

^9So likewise ye, except ye utter by the tongue words easy to be understood, how shall it be known what is spoken? for ye shall speak into the air.

^10There are, it may be, so many kinds of voices in the world, and none of them is without signification.

^11Therefore if I know not the meaning of the voice, I shall be unto him that speaketh a barbarian, and he that speaketh shall be a barbarian unto me.

^12Even so ye, forasmuch as ye are zealous of spiritual gifts, seek that ye may excel to the edifying of the church.

^13Wherefore let him that speaketh in an unknown tongue pray that he may interpret.

^14For if I pray in an unknown tongue, my spirit prayeth, but my understanding is unfruitful.

^15What is it then? I will pray with the spirit, and I will pray with the understanding also: I will sing with the spirit, and I will sing with the understanding also.

^16Else when thou shalt bless with the spirit, how shall he that occupieth the room of the unlearned say Amen at thy giving of thanks, seeing he understandeth not what thou sayest?

^17For thou verily givest thanks well, but the other is not edified.

^18I thank my God, I speak with tongues more than ye all:

^19Yet in the church I had rather speak five words with my understanding, that by my voice I might teach others also, than ten thousand words in an unknown tongue.

^20Brethren, be not children in understanding: howbeit in malice be ye children, but in understanding be men.

^21In the law it is written, With men of other tongues and other lips will I speak unto this people; and yet for all that will they not hear me, saith the Lord.

^22Wherefore tongues are for a sign, not to them that believe, but to them that believe not: but prophesying serveth not for them that believe not, but for them which believe.

^23If therefore the whole church be come together into one place, and all speak with tongues, and there come in those that are unlearned, or unbelievers, will they not say that ye are mad?

^24But if all prophesy, and there come in one that believeth not, or one unlearned, he is convinced of all, he is judged of all:

^25And thus are the secrets of his heart made manifest; and so falling down on his face he will worship God, and report that God is in you of a truth.

^26How is it then, brethren? when ye come together, every one of you hath a psalm, hath a doctrine, hath a tongue, hath a revelation, hath an interpretation. Let all things be done unto edifying.

^27If any man speak in an unknown tongue, let it be by two, or at the most by three, and that by course; and let one interpret.

^28But if there be no interpreter, let him keep silence in the church; and let him speak to himself, and to God.

^29Let the prophets speak two or three, and let the other judge.

^30If any thing be revealed to another that sitteth by, let the first hold his peace.

^31For ye may all prophesy one by one, that all may learn, and all may be comforted.

^32And the spirits of the prophets are subject to the prophets.

^33For God is not the author of confusion, but of peace, as in all churches of the saints.

^34Let your women keep silence in the churches: for it is not permitted unto them to speak; but they are commanded to be under obedience as also saith the law.

^35And if they will learn any thing, let them ask their husbands at home: for it is a shame for women to speak in the church.

^36What? came the word of God out from you? or came it unto you only?

^37If any man think himself to be a prophet, or spiritual, let him acknowledge that the things that I write unto you are the commandments of the Lord.

^38But if any man be ignorant, let him be ignorant.

^39Wherefore, brethren, covet to prophesy, and forbid not to speak with tongues.

^40Let all things be done decently and in order.

I Corinthians 15

15^1Moreover, brethren, I declare unto you the gospel which I preached unto you, which also ye have received, and wherein ye stand;

^2By which also ye are saved, if ye keep in memory what I preached unto you, unless ye have believed in vain.

^3For I delivered unto you first of all that which I also received, how that Christ died for our sins according to the scriptures;

^4And that he was buried, and that he rose again the third day according to the scriptures:

^5And that he was seen of Cephas, then of the twelve:

^6After that, he was seen of above five hundred brethren at once; of whom the greater part remain unto this present, but some are fallen asleep.

^7After that, he was seen of James; then of all the apostles.

^8And last of all he was seen of me also, as of one born out of due time.

^9For I am the least of the apostles, that am not meet to be called an apostle, because I persecuted the church of God.

^10But by the grace of God I am what I am: and his grace which was bestowed upon me was not in vain; but I laboured more abundantly than they all: yet not I, but the grace of God which was with me.

^11Therefore whether it were I or they, so we preach, and so ye believed.

^12Now if Christ be preached that he rose from the dead, how say some among you that there is no resurrection of the dead?

^13But if there be no resurrection of the dead, then is Christ not risen:

^14And if Christ be not risen, then is our preaching vain, and your faith is also vain.

^15Yea, and we are found false witnesses of God; because we have testified of God that he raised up Christ: whom he raised not up, if so be that the dead rise not.

^16For if the dead rise not, then is not Christ raised:

^17And if Christ be not raised, your faith is vain; ye are yet in your sins.

^18Then they also which are fallen asleep in Christ are perished.

^19If in this life only we have hope in Christ, we are of all men most miserable.

^20But now is Christ risen from the dead, and become the firstfruits of them that slept.

^21For since by man came death, by man came also the resurrection of the dead.

^22For as in Adam all die, even so in Christ shall all be made alive.

^23But every man in his own order: Christ the firstfruits; afterward they that are Christ’s at his coming.

^24Then cometh the end, when he shall have delivered up the kingdom to God, even the Father; when he shall have put down all rule and all authority and power.

^25For he must reign, till he hath put all enemies under his feet.

^26The last enemy that shall be destroyed is death.

^27For he hath put all things under his feet. But when he saith all things are put under him, it is manifest that he is excepted, which did put all things under him.

^28And when all things shall be subdued unto him, then shall the Son also himself be subject unto him that put all things under him, that God may be all in all.

^29Else what shall they do which are baptized for the dead, if the dead rise not at all? why are they then baptized for the dead?

^30And why stand we in jeopardy every hour?

^31I protest by your rejoicing which I have in Christ Jesus our Lord, I die daily.

^32If after the manner of men I have fought with beasts at Ephesus, what advantageth it me, if the dead rise not? let us eat and drink; for to morrow we die.

^33Be not deceived: evil communications corrupt good manners.

^34Awake to righteousness, and sin not; for some have not the knowledge of God: I speak this to your shame.

^35But some man will say, How are the dead raised up? and with what body do they come?

^36Thou fool, that which thou sowest is not quickened, except it die:

^37And that which thou sowest, thou sowest not that body that shall be, but bare grain, it may chance of wheat, or of some other grain:

^38But God giveth it a body as it hath pleased him, and to every seed his own body.

^39All flesh is not the same flesh: but there is one kind of flesh of men, another flesh of beasts, another of fishes, and another of birds.

^40There are also celestial bodies, and bodies terrestrial: but the glory of the celestial is one, and the glory of the terrestrial is another.

^41There is one glory of the sun, and another glory of the moon, and another glory of the stars: for one star differeth from another star in glory.

^42So also is the resurrection of the dead. It is sown in corruption; it is raised in incorruption:

^43It is sown in dishonour; it is raised in glory: it is sown in weakness; it is raised in power:

^44It is sown a natural body; it is raised a spiritual body. There is a natural body, and there is a spiritual body.

^45And so it is written, The first man Adam was made a living soul; the last Adam was made a quickening spirit.

^46Howbeit that was not first which is spiritual, but that which is natural; and afterward that which is spiritual.

^47The first man is of the earth, earthy; the second man is the Lord from heaven.

^48As is the earthy, such are they also that are earthy: and as is the heavenly, such are they also that are heavenly.

^49And as we have borne the image of the earthy, we shall also bear the image of the heavenly.

^50Now this I say, brethren, that flesh and blood cannot inherit the kingdom of God; neither doth corruption inherit incorruption.

^51Behold, I shew you a mystery; We shall not all sleep, but we shall all be changed,

^52In a moment, in the twinkling of an eye, at the last trump: for the trumpet shall sound, and the dead shall be raised incorruptible, and we shall be changed.

^53For this corruptible must put on incorruption, and this mortal must put on immortality.

^54So when this corruptible shall have put on incorruption, and this mortal shall have put on immortality, then shall be brought to pass the saying that is written, Death is swallowed up in victory.

^55O death, where is thy sting? O grave, where is thy victory?

^56The sting of death is sin; and the strength of sin is the law.

^57But thanks be to God, which giveth us the victory through our Lord Jesus Christ.

^58Therefore, my beloved brethren, be ye stedfast, unmoveable, always abounding in the work of the Lord, forasmuch as ye know that your labour is not in vain in the Lord.

I Corinthians 16

16^1Now concerning the collection for the saints, as I have given order to the churches of Galatia, even so do ye.

^2Upon the first day of the week let every one of you lay by him in store, as God hath prospered him, that there be no gatherings when I come.

^3And when I come, whomsoever ye shall approve by your letters, them will I send to bring your liberality unto Jerusalem.

^4And if it be meet that I go also, they shall go with me.

^5Now I will come unto you, when I shall pass through Macedonia: for I do pass through Macedonia.

^6And it may be that I will abide, yea, and winter with you, that ye may bring me on my journey whithersoever I go.

^7For I will not see you now by the way; but I trust to tarry a while with you, if the Lord permit.

^8But I will tarry at Ephesus until Pentecost.

^9For a great door and effectual is opened unto me, and there are many adversaries.

^10Now if Timotheus come, see that he may be with you without fear: for he worketh the work of the Lord, as I also do.

^11Let no man therefore despise him: but conduct him forth in peace, that he may come unto me: for I look for him with the brethren.

^12As touching our brother Apollos, I greatly desired him to come unto you with the brethren: but his will was not at all to come at this time; but he will come when he shall have convenient time.

^13Watch ye, stand fast in the faith, quit you like men, be strong.

^14Let all your things be done with charity.

^15I beseech you, brethren, (ye know the house of Stephanas, that it is the firstfruits of Achaia, and that they have addicted themselves to the ministry of the saints,)

^16That ye submit yourselves unto such, and to every one that helpeth with us, and laboureth.

^17I am glad of the coming of Stephanas and Fortunatus and Achaicus: for that which was lacking on your part they have supplied.

^18For they have refreshed my spirit and your’s: therefore acknowledge ye them that are such.

^19The churches of Asia salute you. Aquila and Priscilla salute you much in the Lord, with the church that is in their house.

^20All the brethren greet you. Greet ye one another with an holy kiss.

^21The salutation of me Paul with mine own hand.

^22If any man love not the Lord Jesus Christ, let him be Anathema Maranatha.

^23The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you.

^24My love be with you all in Christ Jesus. Amen.

II Corinthians

The Second Epistle of Paul the Apostle to the

Corinthians

I

1^1Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ by the will of God, and Timothy our brother, unto the church of God which is at Corinth, with all the saints which are in all Achaia:

^2Grace be to you and peace from God our Father, and from the Lord Jesus Christ.

^3Blessed be God, even the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of mercies, and the God of all comfort;

^4Who comforteth us in all our tribulation, that we may be able to comfort them which are in any trouble, by the comfort wherewith we ourselves are comforted of God.

^5For as the sufferings of Christ abound in us, so our consolation also aboundeth by Christ.

^6And whether we be afflicted, it is for your consolation and salvation, which is effectual in the enduring of the same sufferings which we also suffer: or whether we be comforted, it is for your consolation and salvation.

^7And our hope of you is stedfast, knowing, that as ye are partakers of the sufferings, so shall ye be also of the consolation.

^8For we would not, brethren, have you ignorant of our trouble which came to us in Asia, that we were pressed out of measure, above strength, insomuch that we despaired even of life:

^9But we had the sentence of death in ourselves, that we should not trust in ourselves, but in God which raiseth the dead:

^10Who delivered us from so great a death, and doth deliver: in whom we trust that he will yet deliver us;

^11Ye also helping together by prayer for us, that for the gift bestowed upon us by the means of many persons thanks may be given by many on our behalf.

^12For our rejoicing is this, the testimony of our conscience, that in simplicity and godly sincerity, not with fleshly wisdom, but by the grace of God, we have had our conversation in the world, and more abundantly to you-ward.

^13For we write none other things unto you, than what ye read or acknowledge; and I trust ye shall acknowledge even to the end;

^14As also ye have acknowledged us in part, that we are your rejoicing, even as ye also are our’s in the day of the Lord Jesus.

^15And in this confidence I was minded to come unto you before, that ye might have a second benefit;

^16And to pass by you into Macedonia, and to come again out of Macedonia unto you, and of you to be brought on my way toward Judaea.

^17When I therefore was thus minded, did I use lightness? or the things that I purpose, do I purpose according to the flesh, that with me there should be yea yea, and nay nay?

^18But as God is true, our word toward you was not yea and nay.

^19For the Son of God, Jesus Christ, who was preached among you by us, even by me and Silvanus and Timotheus, was not yea and nay, but in him was yea.

^20For all the promises of God in him are yea, and in him Amen, unto the glory of God by us.

^21Now he which stablisheth us with you in Christ, and hath anointed us, is God;

^22Who hath also sealed us, and given the earnest of the Spirit in our hearts.

^23Moreover I call God for a record upon my soul, that to spare you I came not as yet unto Corinth.

^24Not for that we have dominion over your faith, but are helpers of your joy: for by faith ye stand.

II

2^1But I determined this with myself, that I would not come again to you in heaviness.

^2For if I make you sorry, who is he then that maketh me glad, but the same which is made sorry by me?

^3And I wrote this same unto you, lest, when I came, I should have sorrow from them of whom I ought to rejoice; having confidence in you all, that my joy is the joy of you all.

^4For out of much affliction and anguish of heart I wrote unto you with many tears; not that ye should be grieved, but that ye might know the love which I have more abundantly unto you.

^5But if any have caused grief, he hath not grieved me, but in part: that I may not overcharge you all.

^6Sufficient to such a man is this punishment, which was inflicted of many.

^7So that contrariwise ye ought rather to forgive him, and comfort him, lest perhaps such a one should be swallowed up with overmuch sorrow.

^8Wherefore I beseech you that ye would confirm your love toward him.

^9For to this end also did I write, that I might know the proof of you, whether ye be obedient in all things.

^10To whom ye forgive any thing, I forgive also: for if I forgave any thing, to whom I forgave it, for your sakes forgave I it in the person of Christ;

^11Lest Satan should get an advantage of us: for we are not ignorant of his devices.

^12Furthermore, when I came to Troas to preach Christ’s gospel, and a door was opened unto me of the Lord,

^13I had no rest in my spirit, because I found not Titus my brother: but taking my leave of them, I went from thence into Macedonia.

^14Now thanks be unto God, which always causeth us to triumph in Christ, and maketh manifest the savour of his knowledge by us in every place.

^15For we are unto God a sweet savour of Christ, in them that are saved, and in them that perish:

^16To the one we are the savour of death unto death; and to the other the savour of life unto life. And who is sufficient for these things?

^17For we are not as many, which corrupt the word of God: but as of sincerity, but as of God, in the sight of God speak we in Christ.

III

3^1Do we begin again to commend ourselves? or need we, as some others, epistles of commendation to you, or letters of commendation from you?

^2Ye are our epistle written in our hearts, known and read of all men:

^3Forasmuch as ye are manifestly declared to be the epistle of Christ ministered by us, written not with ink, but with the Spirit of the living God; not in tables of stone, but in fleshy tables of the heart.

^4And such trust have we through Christ to God-ward:

^5Not that we are sufficient of ourselves to think any thing as of ourselves; but our sufficiency is of God;

^6Who also hath made us able ministers of the new testament; not of the letter, but of the spirit: for the letter killeth, but the spirit giveth life.

^7But if the ministration of death, written and engraven in stones, was glorious, so that the children of Israel could not stedfastly behold the face of Moses for the glory of his countenance; which glory was to be done away:

^8How shall not the ministration of the spirit be rather glorious?

^9For if the ministration of condemnation be glory, much more doth the ministration of righteousness exceed in glory.

^10For even that which was made glorious had no glory in this respect, by reason of the glory that excelleth.

^11For if that which is done away was glorious, much more that which remaineth is glorious.

^12Seeing then that we have such hope, we use great plainness of speech:

^13And not as Moses, which put a vail over his face, that the children of Israel could not stedfastly look to the end of that which is abolished:

^14But their minds were blinded: for until this day remaineth the same vail untaken away in the reading of the old testament; which vail is done away in Christ.

^15But even unto this day, when Moses is read, the vail is upon their heart.

^16Nevertheless when it shall turn to the Lord, the vail shall be taken away.

^17Now the Lord is that Spirit: and where the Spirit of the Lord is, there is liberty.

^18But we all, with open face beholding as in a glass the glory of the Lord, are changed into the same image from glory to glory, even as by the Spirit of the Lord.

IV

4^1Therefore seeing we have this ministry, as we have received mercy, we faint not;

^2But have renounced the hidden things of dishonesty, not walking in craftiness, nor handling the word of God deceitfully; but by manifestation of the truth commending ourselves to every man’s conscience in the sight of God.

^3But if our gospel be hid, it is hid to them that are lost:

^4In whom the god of this world hath blinded the minds of them which believe not, lest the light of the glorious gospel of Christ, who is the image of God, should shine unto them.

^5For we preach not ourselves, but Christ Jesus the Lord; and ourselves your servants for Jesus’ sake.

^6For God, who commanded the light to shine out of darkness, hath shined in our hearts, to give the light of the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jesus Christ.

^7But we have this treasure in earthen vessels, that the excellency of the power may be of God, and not of us.

^8We are troubled on every side, yet not distressed; we are perplexed, but not in despair;

^9Persecuted, but not forsaken; cast down, but not destroyed;

^10Always bearing about in the body the dying of the Lord Jesus, that the life also of Jesus might be made manifest in our body.

^11For we which live are alway delivered unto death for Jesus’ sake, that the life also of Jesus might be made manifest in our mortal flesh.

^12So then death worketh in us, but life in you.

^13We having the same spirit of faith, according as it is written, I believed, and therefore have I spoken; we also believe, and therefore speak;

^14Knowing that he which raised up the Lord Jesus shall raise up us also by Jesus, and shall present us with you.

^15For all things are for your sakes, that the abundant grace might through the thanksgiving of many redound to the glory of God.

^16For which cause we faint not; but though our outward man perish, yet the inward man is renewed day by day.

^17For our light affliction, which is but for a moment, worketh for us a far more exceeding and eternal weight of glory;

^18While we look not at the things which are seen, but at the things which are not seen: for the things which are seen are temporal; but the things which are not seen are eternal.

V

5^1For we know that if our earthly house of this tabernacle were dissolved, we have a building of God, an house not made with hands, eternal in the heavens.

^2For in this we groan, earnestly desiring to be clothed upon with our house which is from heaven:

^3If so be that being clothed we shall not be found naked.

^4For we that are in this tabernacle do groan, being burdened: not for that we would be unclothed, but clothed upon, that mortality might be swallowed up of life.

^5Now he that hath wrought us for the selfsame thing is God, who also hath given unto us the earnest of the Spirit.

^6Therefore we are always confident, knowing that, whilst we are at home in the body, we are absent from the Lord:

^7(For we walk by faith, not by sight:)

^8We are confident, I say, and willing rather to be absent from the body, and to be present with the Lord.

^9Wherefore we labour, that, whether present or absent, we may be accepted of him.

^10For we must all appear before the judgment seat of Christ; that every one may receive the things done in his body, according to that he hath done, whether it be good or bad.

^11Knowing therefore the terror of the Lord, we persuade men; but we are made manifest unto God; and I trust also are made manifest in your consciences.

^12For we commend not ourselves again unto you, but give you occasion to glory on our behalf, that ye may have somewhat to answer them which glory in appearance, and not in heart.

^13For whether we be beside ourselves, it is to God: or whether we be sober, it is for your cause.

^14For the love of Christ constraineth us; because we thus judge, that if one died for all, then were all dead:

^15And that he died for all, that they which live should not henceforth live unto themselves, but unto him which died for them, and rose again.

^16Wherefore henceforth know we no man after the flesh: yea, though we have known Christ after the flesh, yet now henceforth know we him no more.

^17Therefore if any man be in Christ, he is a new creature: old things are passed away; behold, all things are become new.

^18And all things are of God, who hath reconciled us to himself by Jesus Christ, and hath given to us the ministry of reconciliation;

^19To wit, that God was in Christ, reconciling the world unto himself, not imputing their trespasses unto them; and hath committed unto us the word of reconciliation.

^20Now then we are ambassadors for Christ, as though God did beseech you by us: we pray you in Christ’s stead, be ye reconciled to God.

^21For he hath made him to be sin for us, who knew no sin; that we might be made the righteousness of God in him.

VI

6^1We then, as workers together with him, beseech you also that ye receive not the grace of God in vain.

^2(For he saith, I have heard thee in a time accepted, and in the day of salvation have I succoured thee: behold, now is the accepted time; behold, now is the day of salvation.)

^3Giving no offence in any thing, that the ministry be not blamed:

^4But in all things approving ourselves as the ministers of God, in much patience, in afflictions, in necessities, in distresses,

^5In stripes, in imprisonments, in tumults, in labours, in watchings, in fastings;

^6By pureness, by knowledge, by longsuffering, by kindness, by the Holy Ghost, by love unfeigned,

^7By the word of truth, by the power of God, by the armour of righteousness on the right hand and on the left,

^8By honour and dishonour, by evil report and good report: as deceivers, and yet true;

^9As unknown, and yet well known; as dying, and, behold, we live; as chastened, and not killed;

^10As sorrowful, yet alway rejoicing; as poor, yet making many rich; as having nothing, and yet possessing all things.

^11O ye Corinthians, our mouth is open unto you, our heart is enlarged.

^12Ye are not straitened in us, but ye are straitened in your own bowels.

^13Now for a recompence in the same, (I speak as unto my children,) be ye also enlarged.

^14Be ye not unequally yoked together with unbelievers: for what fellowship hath righteousness with unrighteousness? and what communion hath light with darkness?

^15And what concord hath Christ with Belial? or what part hath he that believeth with an infidel?

^16And what agreement hath the temple of God with idols? for ye are the temple of the living God; as God hath said, I will dwell in them, and walk in them; and I will be their God, and they shall be my people.

^17Wherefore come out from among them, and be ye separate, saith the Lord, and touch not the unclean thing; and I will receive you.

^18And will be a Father unto you, and ye shall be my sons and daughters, saith the Lord Almighty.

VII

7^1Having therefore these promises, dearly beloved, let us cleanse ourselves from all filthiness of the flesh and spirit, perfecting holiness in the fear of God.

^2Receive us; we have wronged no man, we have corrupted no man, we have defrauded no man.

^3I speak not this to condemn you: for I have said before, that ye are in our hearts to die and live with you.

^4Great is my boldness of speech toward you, great is my glorying of you: I am filled with comfort, I am exceeding joyful in all our tribulation.

^5For, when we were come into Macedonia, our flesh had no rest, but we were troubled on every side; without were fightings, within were fears.

^6Nevertheless God, that comforteth those that are cast down, comforted us by the coming of Titus;

^7And not by his coming only, but by the consolation wherewith he was comforted in you, when he told us your earnest desire, your mourning, your fervent mind toward me; so that I rejoiced the more.

^8For though I made you sorry with a letter, I do not repent, though I did repent: for I perceive that the same epistle hath made you sorry, though it were but for a season.

^9Now I rejoice, not that ye were made sorry, but that ye sorrowed to repentance: for ye were made sorry after a godly manner, that ye might receive damage by us in nothing.

^10For godly sorrow worketh repentance to salvation not to be repented of: but the sorrow of the world worketh death.

^11For behold this selfsame thing, that ye sorrowed after a godly sort, what carefulness it wrought in you, yea, what clearing of yourselves, yea, what indignation, yea, what fear, yea, what vehement desire, yea, what zeal, yea, what revenge! In all things ye have approved yourselves to be clear in this matter.

^12Wherefore, though I wrote unto you, I did it not for his cause that had done the wrong, nor for his cause that suffered wrong, but that our care for you in the sight of God might appear unto you.

^13Therefore we were comforted in your comfort: yea, and exceedingly the more joyed we for the joy of Titus, because his spirit was refreshed by you all.

^14For if I have boasted any thing to him of you, I am not ashamed; but as we spake all things to you in truth, even so our boasting, which I made before Titus, is found a truth.

^15And his inward affection is more abundant toward you, whilst he remembereth the obedience of you all, how with fear and trembling ye received him.

^16I rejoice therefore that I have confidence in you in all things.

VIII

8^1Moreover, brethren, we do you to wit of the grace of God bestowed on the churches of Macedonia;

^2How that in a great trial of affliction the abundance of their joy and their deep poverty abounded unto the riches of their liberality.

^3For to their power, I bear record, yea, and beyond their power they were willing of themselves;

^4Praying us with much intreaty that we would receive the gift, and take upon us the fellowship of the ministering to the saints.

^5And this they did, not as we hoped, but first gave their own selves to the Lord, and unto us by the will of God.

^6Insomuch that we desired Titus, that as he had begun, so he would also finish in you the same grace also.

^7Therefore, as ye abound in every thing, in faith, and utterance, and knowledge, and in all diligence, and in your love to us, see that ye abound in this grace also.

^8I speak not by commandment, but by occasion of the forwardness of others, and to prove the sincerity of your love.

^9For ye know the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ, that, though he was rich, yet for your sakes he became poor, that ye through his poverty might be rich.

^10And herein I give my advice: for this is expedient for you, who have begun before, not only to do, but also to be forward a year ago.

^11Now therefore perform the doing of it; that as there was a readiness to will, so there may be a performance also out of that which ye have.

^12For if there be first a willing mind, it is accepted according to that a man hath, and not according to that he hath not.

^13For I mean not that other men be eased, and ye burdened:

^14But by an equality, that now at this time your abundance may be a supply for their want, that their abundance also may be a supply for your want: that there may be equality:

^15As it is written, He that had gathered much had nothing over; and he that had gathered little had no lack.

^16But thanks be to God, which put the same earnest care into the heart of Titus for you.

^17For indeed he accepted the exhortation; but being more forward, of his own accord he went unto you.

^18And we have sent with him the brother, whose praise is in the gospel throughout all the churches;

^19And not that only, but who was also chosen of the churches to travel with us with this grace, which is administered by us to the glory of the same Lord, and declaration of your ready mind:

^20Avoiding this, that no man should blame us in this abundance which is administered by us:

^21Providing for honest things, not only in the sight of the Lord, but also in the sight of men.

^22And we have sent with them our brother, whom we have oftentimes proved diligent in many things, but now much more diligent, upon the great confidence which I have in you.

^23Whether any do enquire of Titus, he is my partner and fellowhelper concerning you: or our brethren be enquired of, they are the messengers of the churches, and the glory of Christ.

^24Wherefore shew ye to them, and before the churches, the proof of your love, and of our boasting on your behalf.

IX

9^1For as touching the ministering to the saints, it is superfluous for me to write to you:

^2For I know the forwardness of your mind, for which I boast of you to them of Macedonia, that Achaia was ready a year ago; and your zeal hath provoked very many.

^3Yet have I sent the brethren, lest our boasting of you should be in vain in this behalf; that, as I said, ye may be ready:

^4Lest haply if they of Macedonia come with me, and find you unprepared, we (that we say not, ye) should be ashamed in this same confident boasting.

^5Therefore I thought it necessary to exhort the brethren, that they would go before unto you, and make up beforehand your bounty, whereof ye had notice before, that the same might be ready, as a matter of bounty, and not as of covetousness.

^6But this I say, He which soweth sparingly shall reap also sparingly; and he which soweth bountifully shall reap also bountifully.

^7Every man according as he purposeth in his heart, so let him give; not grudgingly, or of necessity: for God loveth a cheerful giver.

^8And God is able to make all grace abound toward you; that ye, always having all sufficiency in all things, may abound to every good work:

^9(As it is written, He hath dispersed abroad; he hath given to the poor: his righteousness remaineth for ever.

^10Now he that ministereth seed to the sower both minister bread for your food, and multiply your seed sown, and increase the fruits of your righteousness;)

^11Being enriched in every thing to all bountifulness, which causeth through us thanksgiving to God.

^12For the administration of this service not only supplieth the want of the saints, but is abundant also by many thanksgivings unto God;

^13Whiles by the experiment of this ministration they glorify God for your professed subjection unto the gospel of Christ, and for your liberal distribution unto them, and unto all men;

^14And by their prayer for you, which long after you for the exceeding grace of God in you.

^15Thanks be unto God for his unspeakable gift.

X

10^1Now I Paul myself beseech you by the meekness and gentleness of Christ, who in presence am base among you, but being absent am bold toward you:

^2But I beseech you, that I may not be bold when I am present with that confidence, wherewith I think to be bold against some, which think of us as if we walked according to the flesh.

^3For though we walk in the flesh, we do not war after the flesh:

^4(For the weapons of our warfare are not carnal, but mighty through God to the pulling down of strong holds;)

^5Casting down imaginations, and every high thing that exalteth itself against the knowledge of God, and bringing into captivity every thought to the obedience of Christ;

^6And having in a readiness to revenge all disobedience, when your obedience is fulfilled.

^7Do ye look on things after the outward appearance? If any man trust to himself that he is Christ’s, let him of himself think this again, that, as he is Christ’s, even so are we Christ’s.

^8For though I should boast somewhat more of our authority, which the Lord hath given us for edification, and not for your destruction, I should not be ashamed:

^9That I may not seem as if I would terrify you by letters.

^10For his letters, say they, are weighty and powerful; but his bodily presence is weak, and his speech contemptible.

^11Let such an one think this, that, such as we are in word by letters when we are absent, such will we be also in deed when we are present.

^12For we dare not make ourselves of the number, or compare ourselves with some that commend themselves: but they measuring themselves by themselves, and comparing themselves among themselves, are not wise.

^13But we will not boast of things without our measure, but according to the measure of the rule which God hath distributed to us, a measure to reach even unto you.

^14For we stretch not ourselves beyond our measure, as though we reached not unto you: for we are come as far as to you also in preaching the gospel of Christ:

^15Not boasting of things without our measure, that is, of other men’s labours; but having hope, when your faith is increased, that we shall be enlarged by you according to our rule abundantly,

^16To preach the gospel in the regions beyond you, and not to boast in another man’s line of things made ready to our hand.

^17But he that glorieth, let him glory in the Lord.

^18For not he that commendeth himself is approved, but whom the Lord commendeth.

XI

11^1Would to God ye could bear with me a little in my folly: and indeed bear with me.

^2For I am jealous over you with godly jealousy: for I have espoused you to one husband, that I may present you as a chaste virgin to Christ.

^3But I fear, lest by any means, as the serpent beguiled Eve through his subtilty, so your minds should be corrupted from the simplicity that is in Christ.

^4For if he that cometh preacheth another Jesus, whom we have not preached, or if ye receive another spirit, which ye have not received, or another gospel, which ye have not accepted, ye might well bear with him.

^5For I suppose I was not a whit behind the very chiefest apostles.

^6But though I be rude in speech, yet not in knowledge; but we have been throughly made manifest among you in all things.

^7Have I committed an offence in abasing myself that ye might be exalted, because I have preached to you the gospel of God freely?

^8I robbed other churches, taking wages of them, to do you service.

^9And when I was present with you, and wanted, I was chargeable to no man: for that which was lacking to me the brethren which came from Macedonia supplied: and in all things I have kept myself from being burdensome unto you, and so will I keep myself.

^10As the truth of Christ is in me, no man shall stop me of this boasting in the regions of Achaia.

^11Wherefore? because I love you not? God knoweth.

^12But what I do, that I will do, that I may cut off occasion from them which desire occasion; that wherein they glory, they may be found even as we.

^13For such are false apostles, deceitful workers, transforming themselves into the apostles of Christ.

^14And no marvel; for Satan himself is transformed into an angel of light.

^15Therefore it is no great thing if his ministers also be transformed as the ministers of righteousness; whose end shall be according to their works.

^16I say again, Let no man think me a fool; if otherwise, yet as a fool receive me, that I may boast myself a little.

^17That which I speak, I speak it not after the Lord, but as it were foolishly, in this confidence of boasting.

^18Seeing that many glory after the flesh, I will glory also.

^19For ye suffer fools gladly, seeing ye yourselves are wise.

^20For ye suffer, if a man bring you into bondage, if a man devour you, if a man take of you, if a man exalt himself, if a man smite you on the face.

^21I speak as concerning reproach, as though we had been weak. Howbeit whereinsoever any is bold, (I speak foolishly,) I am bold also.

^22Are they Hebrews? so am I. Are they Israelites? so am I. Are they the seed of Abraham? so am I.

^23Are they ministers of Christ? (I speak as a fool) I am more; in labours more abundant, in stripes above measure, in prisons more frequent, in deaths oft.

^24Of the Jews five times received I forty stripes save one.

^25Thrice was I beaten with rods, once was I stoned, thrice I suffered shipwreck, a night and a day I have been in the deep;

^26In journeyings often, in perils of waters, in perils of robbers, in perils by mine own countrymen, in perils by the heathen, in perils in the city, in perils in the wilderness, in perils in the sea, in perils among false brethren;

^27In weariness and painfulness, in watchings often, in hunger and thirst, in fastings often, in cold and nakedness.

^28Beside those things that are without, that which cometh upon me daily, the care of all the churches.

^29Who is weak, and I am not weak? who is offended, and I burn not?

^30If I must needs glory, I will glory of the things which concern mine infirmities.

^31The God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, which is blessed for evermore, knoweth that I lie not.

^32In Damascus the governor under Aretas the king kept the city of the Damascenes with a garrison, desirous to apprehend me:

^33And through a window in a basket was I let down by the wall, and escaped his hands.

XII

12^1It is not expedient for me doubtless to glory. I will come to visions and revelations of the Lord.

^2I knew a man in Christ above fourteen years ago, (whether in the body, I cannot tell; or whether out of the body, I cannot tell: God knoweth;) such an one caught up to the third heaven.

^3And I knew such a man, (whether in the body, or out of the body, I cannot tell: God knoweth;)

^4How that he was caught up into paradise, and heard unspeakable words, which it is not lawful for a man to utter.

^5Of such an one will I glory: yet of myself I will not glory, but in mine infirmities.

^6For though I would desire to glory, I shall not be a fool; for I will say the truth: but now I forbear, lest any man should think of me above that which he seeth me to be, or that he heareth of me.

^7And lest I should be exalted above measure through the abundance of the revelations, there was given to me a thorn in the flesh, the messenger of Satan to buffet me, lest I should be exalted above measure.

^8For this thing I besought the Lord thrice, that it might depart from me.

^9And he said unto me, My grace is sufficient for thee: for my strength is made perfect in weakness. Most gladly therefore will I rather glory in my infirmities, that the power of Christ may rest upon me.

^10Therefore I take pleasure in infirmities, in reproaches, in necessities, in persecutions, in distresses for Christ’s sake: for when I am weak, then am I strong.

^11I am become a fool in glorying; ye have compelled me: for I ought to have been commended of you: for in nothing am I behind the very chiefest apostles, though I be nothing.

^12Truly the signs of an apostle were wrought among you in all patience, in signs, and wonders, and mighty deeds.

^13For what is it wherein ye were inferior to other churches, except it be that I myself was not burdensome to you? forgive me this wrong.

^14Behold, the third time I am ready to come to you; and I will not be burdensome to you: for I seek not your’s but you: for the children ought not to lay up for the parents, but the parents for the children.

^15And I will very gladly spend and be spent for you; though the more abundantly I love you, the less I be loved.

^16But be it so, I did not burden you: nevertheless, being crafty, I caught you with guile.

^17Did I make a gain of you by any of them whom I sent unto you?

^18I desired Titus, and with him I sent a brother. Did Titus make a gain of you? walked we not in the same spirit? walked we not in the same steps?

^19Again, think ye that we excuse ourselves unto you? we speak before God in Christ: but we do all things, dearly beloved, for your edifying.

^20For I fear, lest, when I come, I shall not find you such as I would, and that I shall be found unto you such as ye would not: lest there be debates, envyings, wraths, strifes, backbitings, whisperings, swellings, tumults:

^21And lest, when I come again, my God will humble me among you, and that I shall bewail many which have sinned already, and have not repented of the uncleanness and fornication and lasciviousness which they have committed.

XIII

13^1This is the third time I am coming to you. In the mouth of two or three witnesses shall every word be established.

^2I told you before, and foretell you, as if I were present, the second time; and being absent now I write to them which heretofore have sinned, and to all other, that, if I come again, I will not spare:

^3Since ye seek a proof of Christ speaking in me, which to you-ward is not weak, but is mighty in you.

^4For though he was crucified through weakness, yet he liveth by the power of God. For we also are weak in him, but we shall live with him by the power of God toward you.

^5Examine yourselves, whether ye be in the faith; prove your own selves. Know ye not your own selves, how that Jesus Christ is in you, except ye be reprobates?

^6But I trust that ye shall know that we are not reprobates.

^7Now I pray to God that ye do no evil; not that we should appear approved, but that ye should do that which is honest, though we be as reprobates.

^8For we can do nothing against the truth, but for the truth.

^9For we are glad, when we are weak, and ye are strong: and this also we wish, even your perfection.

^10Therefore I write these things being absent, lest being present I should use sharpness, according to the power which the Lord hath given me to edification, and not to destruction.

^11Finally, brethren, farewell. Be perfect, be of good comfort, be of one mind, live in peace; and the God of love and peace shall be with you.

^12Greet one another with an holy kiss.

^13All the saints salute you.

^14The grace of the Lord Jesus Christ, and the love of God, and the communion of the Holy Ghost, be with you all. Amen.

Book 48 Galatians

48:001:001 Paul, an apostle, (not of men, neither by man, but by Jesus Christ, and God the Father, who raised him from the dead;)

48:001:002 And all the brethren which are with me, unto the churches of Galatia:

48:001:003 Grace be to you and peace from God the Father, and from our Lord Jesus Christ,

48:001:004 Who gave himself for our sins, that he might deliver us from this present evil world, according to the will of God and our Father:

48:001:005 To whom be glory for ever and ever. Amen.

48:001:006 I marvel that ye are so soon removed from him that called you into the grace of Christ unto another gospel:

48:001:007 Which is not another; but there be some that trouble you, and would pervert the gospel of Christ.

48:001:008 But though we, or an angel from heaven, preach any other gospel unto you than that which we have preached unto you, let him be accursed.

48:001:009 As we said before, so say I now again, if any man preach any other gospel unto you than that ye have received, let him be accursed.

48:001:010 For do I now persuade men, or God? or do I seek to please men? for if I yet pleased men, I should not be the servant of Christ.

48:001:011 But I certify you, brethren, that the gospel which was preached of me is not after man.

48:001:012 For I neither received it of man, neither was I taught it, but by the revelation of Jesus Christ.

48:001:013 For ye have heard of my conversation in time past in the Jews' religion, how that beyond measure I persecuted the church of God, and wasted it:

48:001:014 And profited in the Jews' religion above many my equals in mine own nation, being more exceedingly zealous of the traditions of my fathers.

48:001:015 But when it pleased God, who separated me from my mother's womb, and called me by his grace,

48:001:016 To reveal his Son in me, that I might preach him among the heathen; immediately I conferred not with flesh and blood:

48:001:017 Neither went I up to Jerusalem to them which were apostles before me; but I went into Arabia, and returned again unto Damascus.

48:001:018 Then after three years I went up to Jerusalem to see Peter, and abode with him fifteen days.

48:001:019 But other of the apostles saw I none, save James the Lord's brother.

48:001:020 Now the things which I write unto you, behold, before God, I lie not.

48:001:021 Afterwards I came into the regions of Syria and Cilicia;

48:001:022 And was unknown by face unto the churches of Judaea which were in Christ:

48:001:023 But they had heard only, That he which persecuted us in times past now preacheth the faith which once he destroyed.

48:001:024 And they glorified God in me.

48:002:001 Then fourteen years after I went up again to Jerusalem with Barnabas, and took Titus with me also.

48:002:002 And I went up by revelation, and communicated unto them that gospel which I preach among the Gentiles, but privately to them which were of reputation, lest by any means I should run, or had run, in vain.

48:002:003 But neither Titus, who was with me, being a Greek, was compelled to be circumcised:

48:002:004 And that because of false brethren unawares brought in, who came in privily to spy out our liberty which we have in Christ Jesus, that they might bring us into bondage:

48:002:005 To whom we gave place by subjection, no, not for an hour; that the truth of the gospel might continue with you.

48:002:006 But of these who seemed to be somewhat, (whatsoever they were, it maketh no matter to me: God accepteth no man's person:) for they who seemed to be somewhat in conference added nothing to me:

48:002:007 But contrariwise, when they saw that the gospel of the uncircumcision was committed unto me, as the gospel of the circumcision was unto Peter;

48:002:008 (For he that wrought effectually in Peter to the apostleship of the circumcision, the same was mighty in me toward the Gentiles:)

48:002:009 And when James, Cephas, and John, who seemed to be pillars, perceived the grace that was given unto me, they gave to me and Barnabas the right hands of fellowship; that we should go unto the heathen, and they unto the circumcision.

48:002:010 Only they would that we should remember the poor; the same which I also was forward to do.

48:002:011 But when Peter was come to Antioch, I withstood him to the face, because he was to be blamed.

48:002:012 For before that certain came from James, he did eat with the Gentiles: but when they were come, he withdrew and separated himself, fearing them which were of the circumcision.

48:002:013 And the other Jews dissembled likewise with him; insomuch that Barnabas also was carried away with their dissimulation.

48:002:014 But when I saw that they walked not uprightly according to the truth of the gospel, I said unto Peter before them all, If thou, being a Jew, livest after the manner of Gentiles, and not as do the Jews, why compellest thou the Gentiles to live as do the Jews?

48:002:015 We who are Jews by nature, and not sinners of the Gentiles,

48:002:016 Knowing that a man is not justified by the works of the law, but by the faith of Jesus Christ, even we have believed in Jesus Christ, that we might be justified by the faith of Christ, and not by the works of the law: for by the works of the law shall no flesh be justified.

48:002:017 But if, while we seek to be justified by Christ, we ourselves also are found sinners, is therefore Christ the minister of sin? God forbid.

48:002:018 For if I build again the things which I destroyed, I make myself a transgressor.

48:002:019 For I through the law am dead to the law, that I might live unto God.

48:002:020 I am crucified with Christ: neverthless I live; yet not I, but Christ liveth in me: and the life which I now live in the flesh I live by the faith of the Son of God, who loved me, and gave himself for me.

48:002:021 I do not frustrate the grace of God: for if righteousness come by the law, then Christ is dead in vain.

48:003:001 O foolish Galatians, who hath bewitched you, that ye should not obey the truth, before whose eyes Jesus Christ hath been evidently set forth, crucified among you?

48:003:002 This only would I learn of you, Received ye the Spirit by the works of the law, or by the hearing of faith?

48:003:003 Are ye so foolish? having begun in the Spirit, are ye now made perfect by the flesh?

48:003:004 Have ye suffered so many things in vain? if it be yet in vain.

48:003:005 He therefore that ministereth to you the Spirit, and worketh miracles among you, doeth he it by the works of the law, or by the hearing of faith?

48:003:006 Even as Abraham believed God, and it was accounted to him for righteousness.

48:003:007 Know ye therefore that they which are of faith, the same are the children of Abraham.

48:003:008 And the scripture, foreseeing that God would justify the heathen through faith, preached before the gospel unto Abraham, saying, In thee shall all nations be blessed.

48:003:009 So then they which be of faith are blessed with faithful Abraham.

48:003:010 For as many as are of the works of the law are under the curse: for it is written, Cursed is every one that continueth not in all things which are written in the book of the law to do them.

48:003:011 But that no man is justified by the law in the sight of God, it is evident: for, The just shall live by faith.

48:003:012 And the law is not of faith: but, The man that doeth them shall live in them.

48:003:013 Christ hath redeemed us from the curse of the law, being made a curse for us: for it is written, Cursed is every one that hangeth on a tree:

48:003:014 That the blessing of Abraham might come on the Gentiles through Jesus Christ; that we might receive the promise of the Spirit through faith.

48:003:015 Brethren, I speak after the manner of men; Though it be but a man's covenant, yet if it be confirmed, no man disannulleth, or addeth thereto.

48:003:016 Now to Abraham and his seed were the promises made. He saith not, And to seeds, as of many; but as of one, And to thy seed, which is Christ.

48:003:017 And this I say, that the covenant, that was confirmed before of God in Christ, the law, which was four hundred and thirty years after, cannot disannul, that it should make the promise of none effect.

48:003:018 For if the inheritance be of the law, it is no more of promise: but God gave it to Abraham by promise.

48:003:019 Wherefore then serveth the law? It was added because of transgressions, till the seed should come to whom the promise was made; and it was ordained by angels in the hand of a mediator.

48:003:020 Now a mediator is not a mediator of one, but God is one.

48:003:021 Is the law then against the promises of God? God forbid: for if there had been a law given which could have given life, verily righteousness should have been by the law.

48:003:022 But the scripture hath concluded all under sin, that the promise by faith of Jesus Christ might be given to them that believe.

48:003:023 But before faith came, we were kept under the law, shut up unto the faith which should afterwards be revealed.

48:003:024 Wherefore the law was our schoolmaster to bring us unto Christ, that we might be justified by faith.

48:003:025 But after that faith is come, we are no longer under a schoolmaster.

48:003:026 For ye are all the children of God by faith in Christ Jesus.

48:003:027 For as many of you as have been baptized into Christ have put on Christ.

48:003:028 There is neither Jew nor Greek, there is neither bond nor free, there is neither male nor female: for ye are all one in Christ Jesus.

48:003:029 And if ye be Christ's, then are ye Abraham's seed, and heirs according to the promise.

48:004:001 Now I say, That the heir, as long as he is a child, differeth nothing from a servant, though he be lord of all;

48:004:002 But is under tutors and governors until the time appointed of the father.

48:004:003 Even so we, when we were children, were in bondage under the elements of the world:

48:004:004 But when the fulness of the time was come, God sent forth his Son, made of a woman, made under the law,

48:004:005 To redeem them that were under the law, that we might receive the adoption of sons.

48:004:006 And because ye are sons, God hath sent forth the Spirit of his Son into your hearts, crying, Abba, Father.

48:004:007 Wherefore thou art no more a servant, but a son; and if a son, then an heir of God through Christ.

48:004:008 Howbeit then, when ye knew not God, ye did service unto them which by nature are no gods.

48:004:009 But now, after that ye have known God, or rather are known of God, how turn ye again to the weak and beggarly elements, whereunto ye desire again to be in bondage?

48:004:010 Ye observe days, and months, and times, and years.

48:004:011 I am afraid of you, lest I have bestowed upon you labour in vain.

48:004:012 Brethren, I beseech you, be as I am; for I am as ye are: ye have not injured me at all.

48:004:013 Ye know how through infirmity of the flesh I preached the gospel unto you at the first.

48:004:014 And my temptation which was in my flesh ye despised not, nor rejected; but received me as an angel of God, even as Christ Jesus.

48:004:015 Where is then the blessedness ye spake of? for I bear you record, that, if it had been possible, ye would have plucked out your own eyes, and have given them to me.

48:004:016 Am I therefore become your enemy, because I tell you the truth?

48:004:017 They zealously affect you, but not well; yea, they would exclude you, that ye might affect them.

48:004:018 But it is good to be zealously affected always in a good thing, and not only when I am present with you.

48:004:019 My little children, of whom I travail in birth again until Christ be formed in you,

48:004:020 I desire to be present with you now, and to change my voice; for I stand in doubt of you.

48:004:021 Tell me, ye that desire to be under the law, do ye not hear the law?

48:004:022 For it is written, that Abraham had two sons, the one by a bondmaid, the other by a freewoman.

48:004:023 But he who was of the bondwoman was born after the flesh; but he of the freewoman was by promise.

48:004:024 Which things are an allegory: for these are the two covenants; the one from the mount Sinai, which gendereth to bondage, which is Agar.

48:004:025 For this Agar is mount Sinai in Arabia, and answereth to Jerusalem which now is, and is in bondage with her children.

48:004:026 But Jerusalem which is above is free, which is the mother of us all.

48:004:027 For it is written, Rejoice, thou barren that bearest not; break forth and cry, thou that travailest not: for the desolate hath many more children than she which hath an husband.

48:004:028 Now we, brethren, as Isaac was, are the children of promise.

48:004:029 But as then he that was born after the flesh persecuted him that was born after the Spirit, even so it is now.

48:004:030 Nevertheless what saith the scripture? Cast out the bondwoman and her son: for the son of the bondwoman shall not be heir with the son of the freewoman.

48:004:031 So then, brethren, we are not children of the bondwoman, but of the free.

48:005:001 Stand fast therefore in the liberty wherewith Christ hath made us free, and be not entangled again with the yoke of bondage.

48:005:002 Behold, I Paul say unto you, that if ye be circumcised, Christ shall profit you nothing.

48:005:003 For I testify again to every man that is circumcised, that he is a debtor to do the whole law.

48:005:004 Christ is become of no effect unto you, whosoever of you are justified by the law; ye are fallen from grace.

48:005:005 For we through the Spirit wait for the hope of righteousness by faith.

48:005:006 For in Jesus Christ neither circumcision availeth any thing, nor uncircumcision; but faith which worketh by love.

48:005:007 Ye did run well; who did hinder you that ye should not obey the truth?

48:005:008 This persuasion cometh not of him that calleth you.

48:005:009 A little leaven leaveneth the whole lump.

48:005:010 I have confidence in you through the Lord, that ye will be none otherwise minded: but he that troubleth you shall bear his judgment, whosoever he be.

48:005:011 And I, brethren, if I yet preach circumcision, why do I yet suffer persecution? then is the offence of the cross ceased.

48:005:012 I would they were even cut off which trouble you.

48:005:013 For, brethren, ye have been called unto liberty; only use not liberty for an occasion to the flesh, but by love serve one another.

48:005:014 For all the law is fulfilled in one word, even in this; Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself.

48:005:015 But if ye bite and devour one another, take heed that ye be not consumed one of another.

48:005:016 This I say then, Walk in the Spirit, and ye shall not fulfil the lust of the flesh.

48:005:017 For the flesh lusteth against the Spirit, and the Spirit against the flesh: and these are contrary the one to the other: so that ye cannot do the things that ye would.

48:005:018 But if ye be led of the Spirit, ye are not under the law.

48:005:019 Now the works of the flesh are manifest, which are these; Adultery, fornication, uncleanness, lasciviousness,

48:005:020 Idolatry, witchcraft, hatred, variance, emulations, wrath, strife, seditions, heresies,

48:005:021 Envyings, murders, drunkenness, revellings, and such like: of the which I tell you before, as I have also told you in time past, that they which do such things shall not inherit the kingdom of God.

48:005:022 But the fruit of the Spirit is love, joy, peace, longsuffering, gentleness, goodness, faith,

48:005:023 Meekness, temperance: against such there is no law.

48:005:024 And they that are Christ's have crucified the flesh with the affections and lusts.

48:005:025 If we live in the Spirit, let us also walk in the Spirit.

48:005:026 Let us not be desirous of vain glory, provoking one another, envying one another.

48:006:001 Brethren, if a man be overtaken in a fault, ye which are spiritual, restore such an one in the spirit of meekness; considering thyself, lest thou also be tempted.

48:006:002 Bear ye one another's burdens, and so fulfil the law of Christ.

48:006:003 For if a man think himself to be something, when he is nothing, he deceiveth himself.

48:006:004 But let every man prove his own work, and then shall he have rejoicing in himself alone, and not in another.

48:006:005 For every man shall bear his own burden.

48:006:006 Let him that is taught in the word communicate unto him that teacheth in all good things.

48:006:007 Be not deceived; God is not mocked: for whatsoever a man soweth, that shall he also reap.

48:006:008 For he that soweth to his flesh shall of the flesh reap corruption; but he that soweth to the Spirit shall of the Spirit reap life everlasting.

48:006:009 And let us not be weary in well doing: for in due season we shall reap, if we faint not.

48:006:010 As we have therefore opportunity, let us do good unto all men, especially unto them who are of the household of faith.

48:006:011 Ye see how large a letter I have written unto you with mine own hand.

48:006:012 As many as desire to make a fair shew in the flesh, they constrain you to be circumcised; only lest they should suffer persecution for the cross of Christ.

48:006:013 For neither they themselves who are circumcised keep the law; but desire to have you circumcised, that they may glory in your flesh.

48:006:014 But God forbid that I should glory, save in the cross of our Lord Jesus Christ, by whom the world is crucified unto me, and I unto the world.

48:006:015 For in Christ Jesus neither circumcision availeth any thing, nor uncircumcision, but a new creature.

48:006:016 And as many as walk according to this rule, peace be on them, and mercy, and upon the Israel of God.

48:006:017 From henceforth let no man trouble me: for I bear in my body the marks of the Lord Jesus.

48:006:018 Brethren, the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit. Amen.

Ephesians

The Epistle of Paul the Apostle to the

Ephesians

I

^1Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ by the will of God, to the saints which are at Ephesus, and to the faithful in Christ Jesus: ^2grace be to you, and peace, from God our Father, and from the Lord Jesus Christ.

^3Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, who hath blessed us with all spiritual blessings in heavenly places in Christ: ^4according as he hath chosen us in him before the foundation of the world, that we should be holy and without blame before him in love: ^5having predestinated us unto the adoption of children by Jesus Christ to himself, according to the good pleasure of his will, ^6to the praise of the glory of his grace, wherein he hath made us accepted in the beloved. ^7In whom we have redemption through his blood, the forgiveness of sins, according to the riches of his grace; ^8wherein he hath abounded toward us in all wisdom and prudence; ^9having made known unto us the mystery of his will, according to his good pleasure which he hath purposed in himself: ^10that in the dispensation of the fulness of times he might gather together in one all things in Christ, both which are in heaven, and which are on earth; even in him: ^11in whom also we have obtained an inheritance, being predestinated according to the purpose of him who worketh all things after the counsel of his own will: ^12that we should be to the praise of his glory, who first trusted in Christ. ^13In whom ye also trusted, after that ye heard the word of truth, the gospel of your salvation: in whom also after that ye believed, ye were sealed with that holy Spirit of promise, ^14which is the earnest of our inheritance until the redemption of the purchased possession, unto the praise of his glory.

^15Wherefore I also, after I heard of your faith in the Lord Jesus, and love unto all the saints, ^16cease not to give thanks for you, making mention of you in my prayers; ^17that the God of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of glory, may give unto you the spirit of wisdom and revelation in the knowledge of him: ^18the eyes of your understanding being enlightened; that ye may know what is the hope of his calling, and what the riches of the glory of his inheritance in the saints, ^19and what is the exceeding greatness of his power to us-ward who believe, according to the working of his mighty power, ^20which he wrought in Christ, when he raised him from the dead, and set him at his own right hand in the heavenly places, ^21far above all principality, and power, and might, and dominion, and every name that is named, not only in this world, but also in that which is to come: ^22and hath put all things under his feet, and gave him to be the head over all things to the church, ^23which is his body, the fulness of him that filleth all in all.

II

^1And you hath he quickened, who were dead in trespasses and sins; ^2wherein in time past ye walked according to the course of this world, according to the prince of the power of the air, the spirit that now worketh in the children of disobedience: ^3among whom also we all had our conversation in times past in the lusts of our flesh, fulfilling the desires of the flesh and of the mind; and were by nature the children of wrath, even as others. ^4But God, who is rich in mercy, for his great love wherewith he loved us, ^5even when we were dead in sins, hath quickened us together with Christ, (by grace ye are saved;) ^6and hath raised us up together, and made us sit together in heavenly places in Christ Jesus: ^7that in the ages to come he might shew the exceeding riches of his grace in his kindness toward us through Christ Jesus. ^8For by grace are ye saved through faith; and that not of yourselves: it is the gift of God: ^9not of works, lest any man should boast. ^10For we are his workmanship, created in Christ Jesus unto good works, which God hath before ordained that we should walk in them.

^11Wherefore remember, that ye being in time past Gentiles in the flesh, who are called Uncircumcision by that which is called the Circumcision in the flesh made by hands; ^12that at that time ye were without Christ, being aliens from the commonwealth of Israel, and strangers from the covenants of promise, having no hope, and without God in the world: ^13but now in Christ Jesus ye who sometimes were far off are made nigh by the blood of Christ. ^14For he is our peace, who hath made both one, and hath broken down the middle wall of partition between us; ^15having abolished in his flesh the enmity, even the law of commandments contained in ordinances; for to make in himself of twain one new man, so making peace; ^16and that he might reconcile both unto God in one body by the cross, having slain the enmity thereby: ^17and came and preached peace to you which were afar off, and to them that were nigh. ^18For through him we both have access by one Spirit unto the Father. ^19Now therefore ye are no more strangers and foreigners, but fellowcitizens with the saints, and of the household of God; ^20and are built upon the foundation of the apostles and prophets, Jesus Christ himself being the chief corner stone; ^21in whom all the building fitly framed together groweth unto an holy temple in the Lord: ^22in whom ye also are builded together for an habitation of God through the Spirit.

III

^1For this cause I Paul, the prisoner of Jesus Christ for you Gentiles, ^2if ye have heard of the dispensation of the grace of God which is given me to you-ward: ^3how that by revelation he made known unto me the mystery; (as I wrote afore in few words, ^4whereby, when ye read, ye may understand my knowledge in the mystery of Christ) ^5which in other ages was not made known unto the sons of men, as it is now revealed unto his holy apostles and prophets by the Spirit; ^6that the Gentiles should be fellowheirs, and of the same body, and partakers of his promise in Christ by the gospel: ^7whereof I was made a minister, according to the gift of the grace of God given unto me by the effectual working of his power. ^8Unto me, who am less than the least of all saints, is this grace given, that I should preach among the Gentiles the unsearchable riches of Christ; ^9and to make all men see what is the fellowship of the mystery, which from the beginning of the world hath been hid in God, who created all things by Jesus Christ: ^10to the intent that now unto the principalities and powers in heavenly places might be known by the church the manifold wisdom of God, ^11according to the eternal purpose which he purposed in Christ Jesus our Lord: ^12in whom we have boldness and access with confidence by the faith of him. ^13Wherefore I desire that ye faint not at my tribulations for you, which is your glory.

^14For this cause I bow my knees unto the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, ^15of whom the whole family in heaven and earth is named, ^16that he would grant you, according to the riches of his glory, to be strengthened with might by his Spirit in the inner man; ^17that Christ may dwell in your hearts by faith; that ye, being rooted and grounded in love, ^18may be able to comprehend with all saints what is the breadth, and length, and depth, and height; ^19and to know the love of Christ, which passeth knowledge, that ye might be filled with all the fulness of God. ^20Now unto him that is able to do exceeding abundantly above all that we ask or think, according to the power that worketh in us, ^21unto him be glory in the church by Christ Jesus throughout all ages, world without end. Amen.

IV

^1I therefore, the prisoner of the Lord, beseech you that ye walk worthy of the vocation wherewith ye are called, ^2with all lowliness and meekness, with longsuffering, forbearing one another in love; ^3endeavouring to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace. ^4There is one body, and one Spirit, even as ye are called in one hope of your calling; ^5one Lord, one faith, one baptism, ^6one God and Father of all, who is above all, and through all, and in you all. ^7But unto every one of us is given grace according to the measure of the gift of Christ. ^8Wherefore he saith,

When he ascended up on high, he led captivity captive,
And gave gifts unto men.

^9(Now that he ascended, what is it but that he also descended first into the lower parts of the earth? ^10He that descended is the same also that ascended up far above all heavens, that he might fill all things.) ^11And he gave some, apostles; and some, prophets; and some, evangelists; and some, pastors and teachers; ^12for the perfecting of the saints, for the work of the ministry, for the edifying of the body of Christ: ^13till we all come in the unity of the faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God, unto a perfect man, unto the measure of the stature of the fulness of Christ: ^14that we henceforth be no more children, tossed to and fro, and carried about with every wind of doctrine, by the sleight of men, and cunning craftiness, whereby they lie in wait to deceive; ^15but speaking the truth in love, may grow up into him in all things, which is the head, even Christ: ^16from whom the whole body fitly joined together and compacted by that which every joint supplieth, according to the effectual working in the measure of every part, maketh increase of the body unto the edifying of itself in love.

^17This I say therefore, and testify in the Lord, that ye henceforth walk not as other Gentiles walk, in the vanity of their mind, ^18having the understanding darkened, being alienated from the life of God through the ignorance that is in them, because of the blindness of their heart: ^19who being past feeling have given themselves over unto lasciviousness, to work all uncleanness with greediness. ^20But ye have not so learned Christ; ^21if so be that ye have heard him, and have been taught by him, as the truth is in Jesus: ^22that ye put off concerning the former conversation the old man, which is corrupt according to the deceitful lusts; ^23and be renewed in the spirit of your mind; ^24and that ye put on the new man, which after God is created in righteousness and true holiness.

^25Wherefore putting away lying, speak every man truth with his neighbour: for we are members one of another. ^26Be ye angry, and sin not: let not the sun go down upon your wrath: ^27neither give place to the devil. ^28Let him that stole steal no more: but rather let him labour, working with his hands the thing which is good, that he may have to give to him that needeth. ^29Let no corrupt communication proceed out of your mouth, but that which is good to the use of edifying, that it may minister grace unto the hearers. ^30And grieve not the holy Spirit of God, whereby ye are sealed unto the day of redemption. ^31Let all bitterness, and wrath, and anger, and clamour, and evil speaking, be put away from you, with all malice: ^32and be ye kind one to another, tenderhearted, forgiving one another, even as God for Christ’s sake hath forgiven you.

V

^1Be ye therefore followers of God, as dear children; ^2and walk in love, as Christ also hath loved us, and hath given himself for us an offering and a sacrifice to God for a sweetsmelling savour.

^3But fornication, and all uncleanness, or covetousness, let it not be once named among you, as becometh saints; ^4neither filthiness, nor foolish talking, nor jesting, which are not convenient: but rather giving of thanks. ^5For this ye know, that no whoremonger, nor unclean person, nor covetous man, who is an idolater, hath any inheritance in the kingdom of Christ and of God.

^6Let no man deceive you with vain words: for because of these things cometh the wrath of God upon the children of disobedience. ^7Be not ye therefore partakers with them. ^8For ye were sometimes darkness, but now are ye light in the Lord: walk as children of light: ^9(for the fruit of the Spirit is in all goodness and righteousness and truth;) ^10proving what is acceptable unto the Lord. ^11And have no fellowship with the unfruitful works of darkness, but rather reprove them. ^12For it is a shame even to speak of those things which are done of them in secret. ^13But all things that are reproved are made manifest by the light: for whatsoever doth make manifest is light. ^14Wherefore he saith, Awake thou that sleepest, and arise from the dead, and Christ shall give thee light.

^15See then that ye walk circumspectly, not as fools, but as wise, ^16redeeming the time, because the days are evil. ^17Wherefore be ye not unwise, but understanding what the will of the Lord is. ^18And be not drunk with wine, wherein is excess; but be filled with the Spirit; ^19speaking to yourselves in psalms and hymns and spiritual songs, singing and making melody in your heart to the Lord; ^20giving thanks always for all things unto God and the Father in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ; ^21submitting yourselves one to another in the fear of God.

^22Wives, submit yourselves unto your own husbands, as unto the Lord. ^23For the husband is the head of the wife, even as Christ is the head of the church: and he is the saviour of the body. ^24Therefore as the church is subject unto Christ, so let the wives be to their own husbands in every thing. ^25Husbands, love your wives, even as Christ also loved the church, and gave himself for it; ^26that he might sanctify and cleanse it with the washing of water by the word, ^27that he might present it to himself a glorious church, not having spot, or wrinkle, or any such thing; but that it should be holy and without blemish. ^28So ought men to love their wives as their own bodies. He that loveth his wife loveth himself. ^29For no man ever yet hated his own flesh; but nourisheth and cherisheth it, even as the Lord the church: ^30for we are members of his body, of his flesh, and of his bones. ^31For this cause shall a man leave his father and mother, and shall be joined unto his wife, and they two shall be one flesh. ^32This is a great mystery: but I speak concerning Christ and the church. ^33Nevertheless let every one of you in particular so love his wife even as himself; and the wife see that she reverence her husband.

VI

^1Children, obey your parents in the Lord: for this is right. ^2Honour thy father and mother; which is the first commandment with promise; ^3that it may be well with thee, and thou mayest live long on the earth. ^4And, ye fathers, provoke not your children to wrath: but bring them up in the nurture and admonition of the Lord.

^5Servants, be obedient to them that are your masters according to the flesh, with fear and trembling, in singleness of your heart, as unto Christ; ^6not with eyeservice, as menpleasers; but as the servants of Christ, doing the will of God from the heart; ^7with good will doing service, as to the Lord, and not to men: ^8knowing that whatsoever good thing any man doeth, the same shall he receive of the Lord, whether he be bond or free. ^9And, ye masters, do the same things unto them, forbearing threatening: knowing that your Master also is in heaven; neither is there respect of persons with him.

^10Finally, my brethren, be strong in the Lord, and in the power of his might. ^11Put on the whole armour of God, that ye may be able to stand against the wiles of the devil. ^12For we wrestle not against flesh and blood, but against principalities, against powers, against the rulers of the darkness of this world, against spiritual wickedness in high places. ^13Wherefore take unto you the whole armour of God, that ye may be able to withstand in the evil day, and having done all, to stand. ^14Stand therefore, having your loins girt about with truth, and having on the breastplate of righteousness; ^15and your feet shod with the preparation of the gospel of peace; ^16above all, taking the shield of faith, wherewith ye shall be able to quench all the fiery darts of the wicked. ^17And take the helmet of salvation, and the sword of the Spirit, which is the word of God: ^18praying always with all prayer and supplication in the Spirit, and watching thereunto with all perseverance and supplication for all saints; ^19and for me, that utterance may be given unto me, that I may open my mouth boldly, to make known the mystery of the gospel, ^20for which I am an ambassador in bonds: that therein I may speak boldly, as I ought to speak.

^21But that ye also may know my affairs, and how I do, Tychicus, a beloved brother and faithful minister in the Lord, shall make known to you all things: ^22whom I have sent unto you for the same purpose, that ye might know our affairs, and that he might comfort your hearts.

^23Peace be to the brethren, and love with faith, from God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ. ^24Grace be with all them that love our Lord Jesus Christ in sincerity. Amen.

Philippians

The Epistle of Paul the Apostle to the

Philippians

I

1^1Paul and Timotheus, the servants of Jesus Christ, to all the saints in Christ Jesus which are at Philippi, with the bishops and deacons:

^2Grace be unto you, and peace, from God our Father, and from the Lord Jesus Christ.

^3I thank my God upon every remembrance of you,

^4Always in every prayer of mine for you all making request with joy,

^5For your fellowship in the gospel from the first day until now;

^6Being confident of this very thing, that he which hath begun a good work in you will perform it until the day of Jesus Christ:

^7Even as it is meet for me to think this of you all, because I have you in my heart; inasmuch as both in my bonds, and in the defence and confirmation of the gospel, ye all are partakers of my grace.

^8For God is my record, how greatly I long after you all in the bowels of Jesus Christ.

^9And this I pray, that your love may abound yet more and more in knowledge and in all judgment;

^10That ye may approve things that are excellent; that ye may be sincere and without offence till the day of Christ.

^11Being filled with the fruits of righteousness, which are by Jesus Christ, unto the glory and praise of God.

^12But I would ye should understand, brethren, that the things which happened unto me have fallen out rather unto the furtherance of the gospel;

^13So that my bonds in Christ are manifest in all the palace, and in all other places;

^14And many of the brethren in the Lord, waxing confident by my bonds, are much more bold to speak the word without fear.

^15Some indeed preach Christ even of envy and strife; and some also of good will:

^16The one preach Christ of contention, not sincerely, supposing to add affliction to my bonds:

^17But the other of love, knowing that I am set for the defence of the gospel.

^18What then? notwithstanding, every way, whether in pretence, or in truth, Christ is preached; and I therein do rejoice, yea, and will rejoice.

^19For I know that this shall turn to my salvation through your prayer, and the supply of the Spirit of Jesus Christ,

^20According to my earnest expectation and my hope, that in nothing I shall be ashamed, but that with all boldness, as always, so now also Christ shall be magnified in my body, whether it be by life, or by death.

^21For to me to live is Christ, and to die is gain.

^22But if I live in the flesh, this is the fruit of my labour: yet what I shall choose I wot not.

^23For I am in a strait betwixt two, having a desire to depart, and to be with Christ; which is far better:

^24Nevertheless to abide in the flesh is more needful for you.

^25And having this confidence, I know that I shall abide and continue with you all for your furtherance and joy of faith;

^26That your rejoicing may be more abundant in Jesus Christ for me by my coming to you again.

^27Only let your conversation be as it becometh the gospel of Christ: that whether I come and see you, or else be absent, I may hear of your affairs, that ye stand fast in one spirit, with one mind striving together for the faith of the gospel;

^28And in nothing terrified by your adversaries: which is to them an evident token of perdition, but to you of salvation, and that of God.

^29For unto you it is given in the behalf of Christ, not only to believe on him, but also to suffer for his sake;

^30Having the same conflict which ye saw in me, and now hear to be in me.

II

2^1If there be therefore any consolation in Christ, if any comfort of love, if any fellowship of the Spirit, if any bowels and mercies,

^2Fulfil ye my joy, that ye be likeminded, having the same love, being of one accord, of one mind.

^3Let nothing be done through strife or vainglory; but in lowliness of mind let each esteem other better than themselves.

^4Look not every man on his own things, but every man also on the things of others.

^5Let this mind be in you, which was also in Christ Jesus:

^6Who, being in the form of God, thought it not robbery to be equal with God:

^7But made himself of no reputation, and took upon him the form of a servant, and was made in the likeness of men:

^8And being found in fashion as a man, he humbled himself, and became obedient unto death, even the death of the cross.

^9Wherefore God also hath highly exalted him, and given him a name which is above every name:

^10That at the name of Jesus every knee should bow, of things in heaven, and things in earth, and things under the earth;

^11And that every tongue should confess that Jesus Christ is Lord, to the glory of God the Father.

^12Wherefore, my beloved, as ye have always obeyed, not as in my presence only, but now much more in my absence, work out your own salvation with fear and trembling.

^13For it is God which worketh in you both to will and to do of his good pleasure.

^14Do all things without murmurings and disputings:

^15That ye may be blameless and harmless, the sons of God, without rebuke, in the midst of a crooked and perverse nation, among whom ye shine as lights in the world;

^16Holding forth the word of life; that I may rejoice in the day of Christ, that I have not run in vain, neither laboured in vain.

^17Yea, and if I be offered upon the sacrifice and service of your faith, I joy, and rejoice with you all.

^18For the same cause also do ye joy, and rejoice with me.

^19But I trust in the Lord Jesus to send Timotheus shortly unto you, that I also may be of good comfort, when I know your state.

^20For I have no man likeminded, who will naturally care for your state.

^21For all seek their own, not the things which are Jesus Christ’s.

^22But ye know the proof of him, that, as a son with the father, he hath served with me in the gospel.

^23Him therefore I hope to send presently, so soon as I shall see how it will go with me.

^24But I trust in the Lord that I also myself shall come shortly.

^25Yet I supposed it necessary to send to you Epaphroditus, my brother, and companion in labour, and fellowsoldier, but your messenger, and he that ministered to my wants.

^26For he longed after you all, and was full of heaviness, because that ye had heard that he had been sick.

^27For indeed he was sick nigh unto death: but God had mercy on him; and not on him only, but on me also, lest I should have sorrow upon sorrow.

^28I sent him therefore the more carefully, that, when ye see him again, ye may rejoice, and that I may be the less sorrowful.

^29Receive him therefore in the Lord with all gladness; and hold such in reputation:

^30Because for the work of Christ he was nigh unto death, not regarding his life, to supply your lack of service toward me.

III

3^1Finally, my brethren, rejoice in the Lord. To write the same things to you, to me indeed is not grievous, but for you it is safe.

^2Beware of dogs, beware of evil workers, beware of the concision.

^3For we are the circumcision, which worship God in the spirit, and rejoice in Christ Jesus, and have no confidence in the flesh.

^4Though I might also have confidence in the flesh. If any other man thinketh that he hath whereof he might trust in the flesh, I more:

^5Circumcised the eighth day, of the stock of Israel, of the tribe of Benjamin, an Hebrew of the Hebrews; as touching the law, a Pharisee;

^6Concerning zeal, persecuting the church; touching the righteousness which is in the law, blameless.

^7But what things were gain to me, those I counted loss for Christ.

^8Yea doubtless, and I count all things but loss for the excellency of the knowledge of Christ Jesus my Lord: for whom I have suffered the loss of all things, and do count them but dung, that I may win Christ,

^9And be found in him, not having mine own righteousness, which is of the law, but that which is through the faith of Christ, the righteousness which is of God by faith:

^10That I may know him, and the power of his resurrection, and the fellowship of his sufferings, being made conformable unto his death;

^11If by any means I might attain unto the resurrection of the dead.

^12Not as though I had already attained, either were already perfect: but I follow after, if that I may apprehend that for which also I am apprehended of Christ Jesus.

^13Brethren, I count not myself to have apprehended: but this one thing I do, forgetting those things which are behind, and reaching forth unto those things which are before,

^14I press toward the mark for the prize of the high calling of God in Christ Jesus.

^15Let us therefore, as many as be perfect, be thus minded: and if in any thing ye be otherwise minded, God shall reveal even this unto you.

^16Nevertheless, whereto we have already attained, let us walk by the same rule, let us mind the same thing.

^17Brethren, be followers together of me, and mark them which walk so as ye have us for an ensample.

^18(For many walk, of whom I have told you often, and now tell you even weeping, that they are the enemies of the cross of Christ:

^19Whose end is destruction, whose God is their belly, and whose glory is in their shame, who mind earthly things.)

^20For our conversation is in heaven; from whence also we look for the Saviour, the Lord Jesus Christ:

^21Who shall change our vile body, that it may be fashioned like unto his glorious body, according to the working whereby he is able even to subdue all things unto himself.

IV

4^1Therefore, my brethren dearly beloved and longed for, my joy and crown, so stand fast in the Lord, my dearly beloved.

^2I beseech Euodias, and beseech Syntyche, that they be of the same mind in the Lord.

^3And I intreat thee also, true yokefellow, help those women which laboured with me in the gospel, with Clement also, and with other my fellowlabourers, whose names are in the book of life.

^4Rejoice in the Lord alway: and again I say, Rejoice.

^5Let your moderation be known unto all men. The Lord is at hand.

^6Be careful for nothing; but in every thing by prayer and supplication with thanksgiving let your requests be made known unto God.

^7And the peace of God, which passeth all understanding, shall keep your hearts and minds through Christ Jesus.

^8Finally, brethren, whatsoever things are true, whatsoever things are honest, whatsoever things are just, whatsoever things are pure, whatsoever things are lovely, whatsoever things are of good report; if there be any virtue, and if there be any praise, think on these things.

^9Those things, which ye have both learned, and received, and heard, and seen in me, do: and the God of peace shall be with you.

^10But I rejoiced in the Lord greatly, that now at the last your care of me hath flourished again; wherein ye were also careful, but ye lacked opportunity.

^11Not that I speak in respect of want: for I have learned, in whatsoever state I am, therewith to be content.

^12I know both how to be abased, and I know how to abound: every where and in all things I am instructed both to be full and to be hungry, both to abound and to suffer need.

^13I can do all things through Christ which strengtheneth me.

^14Notwithstanding ye have well done, that ye did communicate with my affliction.

^15Now ye Philippians know also, that in the beginning of the gospel, when I departed from Macedonia, no church communicated with me as concerning giving and receiving, but ye only.

^16For even in Thessalonica ye sent once and again unto my necessity.

^17Not because I desire a gift: but I desire fruit that may abound to your account.

^18But I have all, and abound: I am full, having received of Epaphroditus the things which were sent from you, an odour of a sweet smell, a sacrifice acceptable, wellpleasing to God.

^19But my God shall supply all your need according to his riches in glory by Christ Jesus.

^20Now unto God and our Father be glory for ever and ever. Amen.

^21Salute every saint in Christ Jesus. The brethren which are with me greet you.

^22All the saints salute you, chiefly they that are of Caesar’s household.

^23The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you all. Amen.

Colossians 1

1^1Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ by the will of God, and Timotheus our brother,

^2To the saints and faithful brethren in Christ which are at Colosse: Grace be unto you, and peace, from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.

^3We give thanks to God and the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, praying always for you,

^4Since we heard of your faith in Christ Jesus, and of the love which ye have to all the saints,

^5For the hope which is laid up for you in heaven, whereof ye heard before in the word of the truth of the gospel;

^6Which is come unto you, as it is in all the world; and bringeth forth fruit, as it doth also in you, since the day ye heard of it, and knew the grace of God in truth:

^7As ye also learned of Epaphras our dear fellowservant, who is for you a faithful minister of Christ;

^8Who also declared unto us your love in the Spirit.

^9For this cause we also, since the day we heard it, do not cease to pray for you, and to desire that ye might be filled with the knowledge of his will in all wisdom and spiritual understanding;

^10That ye might walk worthy of the Lord unto all pleasing, being fruitful in every good work, and increasing in the knowledge of God;

^11Strengthened with all might, according to his glorious power, unto all patience and longsuffering with joyfulness;

^12Giving thanks unto the Father, which hath made us meet to be partakers of the inheritance of the saints in light:

^13Who hath delivered us from the power of darkness, and hath translated us into the kingdom of his dear Son:

^14In whom we have redemption through his blood, even the forgiveness of sins:

^15Who is the image of the invisible God, the firstborn of every creature:

^16For by him were all things created, that are in heaven, and that are in earth, visible and invisible, whether they be thrones, or dominions, or principalities, or powers: all things were created by him, and for him:

^17And he is before all things, and by him all things consist.

^18And he is the head of the body, the church: who is the beginning, the firstborn from the dead; that in all things he might have the preeminence.

^19For it pleased the Father that in him should all fulness dwell;

^20And, having made peace through the blood of his cross, by him to reconcile all things unto himself; by him, I say, whether they be things in earth, or things in heaven.

^21And you, that were sometime alienated and enemies in your mind by wicked works, yet now hath he reconciled

^22In the body of his flesh through death, to present you holy and unblameable and unreproveable in his sight:

^23If ye continue in the faith grounded and settled, and be not moved away from the hope of the gospel, which ye have heard, and which was preached to every creature which is under heaven; whereof I Paul am made a minister;

^24Who now rejoice in my sufferings for you, and fill up that which is behind of the afflictions of Christ in my flesh for his body’s sake, which is the church:

^25Whereof I am made a minister, according to the dispensation of God which is given to me for you, to fulfil the word of God;

^26Even the mystery which hath been hid from ages and from generations, but now is made manifest to his saints:

^27To whom God would make known what is the riches of the glory of this mystery among the Gentiles; which is Christ in you, the hope of glory:

^28Whom we preach, warning every man, and teaching every man in all wisdom; that we may present every man perfect in Christ Jesus:

^29Whereunto I also labour, striving according to his working, which worketh in me mightily.

Colossians 2

2^1For I would that ye knew what great conflict I have for you, and for them at Laodicea, and for as many as have not seen my face in the flesh;

^2That their hearts might be comforted, being knit together in love, and unto all riches of the full assurance of understanding, to the acknowledgement of the mystery of God, and of the Father, and of Christ;

^3In whom are hid all the treasures of wisdom and knowledge.

^4And this I say, lest any man should beguile you with enticing words.

^5For though I be absent in the flesh, yet am I with you in the spirit, joying and beholding your order, and the stedfastness of your faith in Christ.

^6As ye have therefore received Christ Jesus the Lord, so walk ye in him:

^7Rooted and built up in him, and stablished in the faith, as ye have been taught, abounding therein with thanksgiving.

^8Beware lest any man spoil you through philosophy and vain deceit, after the tradition of men, after the rudiments of the world, and not after Christ.

^9For in him dwelleth all the fulness of the Godhead bodily.

^10And ye are complete in him, which is the head of all principality and power:

^11In whom also ye are circumcised with the circumcision made without hands, in putting off the body of the sins of the flesh by the circumcision of Christ:

^12Buried with him in baptism, wherein also ye are risen with him through the faith of the operation of God, who hath raised him from the dead.

^13And you, being dead in your sins and the uncircumcision of your flesh, hath he quickened together with him, having forgiven you all trespasses;

^14Blotting out the handwriting of ordinances that was against us, which was contrary to us, and took it out of the way, nailing it to his cross;

^15And having spoiled principalities and powers, he made a shew of them openly, triumphing over them in it.

^16Let no man therefore judge you in meat, or in drink, or in respect of an holyday, or of the new moon, or of the sabbath days:

^17Which are a shadow of things to come; but the body is of Christ.

^18Let no man beguile you of your reward in a voluntary humility and worshipping of angels, intruding into those things which he hath not seen, vainly puffed up by his fleshly mind,

^19And not holding the Head, from which all the body by joints and bands having nourishment ministered, and knit together, increaseth with the increase of God.

^20Wherefore if ye be dead with Christ from the rudiments of the world, why, as though living in the world, are ye subject to ordinances,

^21(Touch not; taste not; handle not;

^22Which all are to perish with the using;) after the commandments and doctrines of men?

^23Which things have indeed a shew of wisdom in will worship, and humility, and neglecting of the body: not in any honour to the satisfying of the flesh.

Colossians 3

3^1If ye then be risen with Christ, seek those things which are above, where Christ sitteth on the right hand of God.

^2Set your affection on things above, not on things on the earth.

^3For ye are dead, and your life is hid with Christ in God.

^4When Christ, who is our life, shall appear, then shall ye also appear with him in glory.

^5Mortify therefore your members which are upon the earth; fornication, uncleanness, inordinate affection, evil concupiscence, and covetousness, which is idolatry:

^6For which things’ sake the wrath of God cometh on the children of disobedience:

^7In the which ye also walked some time, when ye lived in them.

^8But now ye also put off all these; anger, wrath, malice, blasphemy, filthy communication out of your mouth.

^9Lie not one to another, seeing that ye have put off the old man with his deeds;

^10And have put on the new man, which is renewed in knowledge after the image of him that created him:

^11Where there is neither Greek nor Jew, circumcision nor uncircumcision, Barbarian, Scythian, bond nor free: but Christ is all, and in all.

^12Put on therefore, as the elect of God, holy and beloved, bowels of mercies, kindness, humbleness of mind, meekness, longsuffering;

^13Forbearing one another, and forgiving one another, if any man have a quarrel against any: even as Christ forgave you, so also do ye.

^14And above all these things put on charity, which is the bond of perfectness.

^15And let the peace of God rule in your hearts, to the which also ye are called in one body; and be ye thankful.

^16Let the word of Christ dwell in you richly in all wisdom; teaching and admonishing one another in psalms and hymns and spiritual songs, singing with grace in your hearts to the Lord.

^17And whatsoever ye do in word or deed, do all in the name of the Lord Jesus, giving thanks to God and the Father by him.

^18Wives, submit yourselves unto your own husbands, as it is fit in the Lord.

^19Husbands, love your wives, and be not bitter against them.

^20Children, obey your parents in all things: for this is well pleasing unto the Lord.

^21Fathers, provoke not your children to anger, lest they be discouraged.

^22Servants, obey in all things your masters according to the flesh; not with eyeservice, as menpleasers; but in singleness of heart, fearing God;

^23And whatsoever ye do, do it heartily, as to the Lord, and not unto men;

^24Knowing that of the Lord ye shall receive the reward of the inheritance: for ye serve the Lord Christ.

^25But he that doeth wrong shall receive for the wrong which he hath done: and there is no respect of persons.

Colossians 4

4^1Masters, give unto your servants that which is just and equal; knowing that ye also have a Master in heaven.

^2Continue in prayer, and watch in the same with thanksgiving;

^3Withal praying also for us, that God would open unto us a door of utterance, to speak the mystery of Christ, for which I am also in bonds:

^4That I may make it manifest, as I ought to speak.

^5Walk in wisdom toward them that are without, redeeming the time.

^6Let your speech be alway with grace, seasoned with salt, that ye may know how ye ought to answer every man.

^7All my state shall Tychicus declare unto you, who is a beloved brother, and a faithful minister and fellowservant in the Lord:

^8Whom I have sent unto you for the same purpose, that he might know your estate, and comfort your hearts;

^9With Onesimus, a faithful and beloved brother, who is one of you. They shall make known unto you all things which are done here.

^10Aristarchus my fellowprisoner saluteth you, and Marcus, sister’s son to Barnabas, (touching whom ye received commandments: if he come unto you, receive him;)

^11And Jesus, which is called Justus, who are of the circumcision. These only are my fellowworkers unto the kingdom of God, which have been a comfort unto me.

^12Epaphras, who is one of you, a servant of Christ, saluteth you, always labouring fervently for you in prayers, that ye may stand perfect and complete in all the will of God.

^13For I bear him record, that he hath a great zeal for you, and them that are in Laodicea, and them in Hierapolis.

^14Luke, the beloved physician, and Demas, greet you.

^15Salute the brethren which are in Laodicea, and Nymphas, and the church which is in his house.

^16And when this epistle is read among you, cause that it be read also in the church of the Laodiceans; and that ye likewise read the epistle from Laodicea.

^17And say to Archippus, Take heed to the ministry which thou hast received in the Lord, that thou fulfil it.

^18The salutation by the hand of me Paul. Remember my bonds. Grace be with you. Amen.

II Thessalonians

The Second Epistle of Paul the Apostle to the

Thessalonians

I

1^1Paul, and Silvanus, and Timotheus, unto the church of the Thessalonians in God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ:

^2Grace unto you, and peace, from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.

^3We are bound to thank God always for you, brethren, as it is meet, because that your faith groweth exceedingly, and the charity of every one of you all toward each other aboundeth;

^4So that we ourselves glory in you in the churches of God for your patience and faith in all your persecutions and tribulations that ye endure:

^5Which is a manifest token of the righteous judgment of God, that ye may be counted worthy of the kingdom of God, for which ye also suffer:

^6Seeing it is a righteous thing with God to recompense tribulation to them that trouble you;

^7And to you who are troubled rest with us, when the Lord Jesus shall be revealed from heaven with his mighty angels,

^8In flaming fire taking vengeance on them that know not God, and that obey not the gospel of our Lord Jesus Christ:

^9Who shall be punished with everlasting destruction from the presence of the Lord, and from the glory of his power;

^10When he shall come to be glorified in his saints, and to be admired in all them that believe (because our testimony among you was believed) in that day.

^11Wherefore also we pray always for you, that our God would count you worthy of this calling, and fulfil all the good pleasure of his goodness, and the work of faith with power:

^12That the name of our Lord Jesus Christ may be glorified in you, and ye in him, according to the grace of our God and the Lord Jesus Christ.

II

2^1Now we beseech you, brethren, by the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ, and by our gathering together unto him,

^2That ye be not soon shaken in mind, or be troubled, neither by spirit, nor by word, nor by letter as from us, as that the day of Christ is at hand.

^3Let no man deceive you by any means: for that day shall not come, except there come a falling away first, and that man of sin be revealed, the son of perdition;

^4Who opposeth and exalteth himself above all that is called God, or that is worshipped; so that he as God sitteth in the temple of God, shewing himself that he is God.

^5Remember ye not, that, when I was yet with you, I told you these things?

^6And now ye know what withholdeth that he might be revealed in his time.

^7For the mystery of iniquity doth already work: only he who now letteth will let, until he be taken out of the way.

^8And then shall that Wicked be revealed, whom the Lord shall consume with the spirit of his mouth, and shall destroy with the brightness of his coming:

^9Even him, whose coming is after the working of Satan with all power and signs and lying wonders,

^10And with all deceivableness of unrighteousness in them that perish; because they received not the love of the truth, that they might be saved.

^11And for this cause God shall send them strong delusion, that they should believe a lie:

^12That they all might be damned who believed not the truth, but had pleasure in unrighteousness.

^13But we are bound to give thanks alway to God for you, brethren beloved of the Lord, because God hath from the beginning chosen you to salvation through sanctification of the Spirit and belief of the truth:

^14Whereunto he called you by our gospel, to the obtaining of the glory of our Lord Jesus Christ.

^15Therefore, brethren, stand fast, and hold the traditions which ye have been taught, whether by word, or our epistle.

^16Now our Lord Jesus Christ himself, and God, even our Father, which hath loved us, and hath given us everlasting consolation and good hope through grace,

^17Comfort your hearts, and stablish you in every good word and work.

III

3^1Finally, brethren, pray for us, that the word of the Lord may have free course, and be glorified, even as it is with you:

^2And that we may be delivered from unreasonable and wicked men: for all men have not faith.

^3But the Lord is faithful, who shall stablish you, and keep you from evil.

^4And we have confidence in the Lord touching you, that ye both do and will do the things which we command you.

^5And the Lord direct your hearts into the love of God, and into the patient waiting for Christ.

^6Now we command you, brethren, in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, that ye withdraw yourselves from every brother that walketh disorderly, and not after the tradition which he received of us.

^7For yourselves know how ye ought to follow us: for we behaved not ourselves disorderly among you;

^8Neither did we eat any man’s bread for nought; but wrought with labour and travail night and day, that we might not be chargeable to any of you:

^9Not because we have not power, but to make ourselves an ensample unto you to follow us.

^10For even when we were with you, this we commanded you, that if any would not work, neither should he eat.

^11For we hear that there are some which walk among you disorderly, working not at all, but are busybodies.

^12Now them that are such we command and exhort by our Lord Jesus Christ, that with quietness they work, and eat their own bread.

^13But ye, brethren, be not weary in well doing.

^14And if any man obey not our word by this epistle, note that man, and have no company with him, that he may be ashamed.

^15Yet count him not as an enemy, but admonish him as a brother.

^16Now the Lord of peace himself give you peace always by all means. The Lord be with you all.

^17The salutation of Paul with mine own hand, which is the token in every epistle: so I write.

^18The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you all. Amen.

I Timothy 1

1^1Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ by the commandment of God our Saviour, and Lord Jesus Christ, which is our hope;

^2Unto Timothy, my own son in the faith: Grace, mercy, and peace, from God our Father and Jesus Christ our Lord.

^3As I besought thee to abide still at Ephesus, when I went into Macedonia, that thou mightest charge some that they teach no other doctrine,

^4Neither give heed to fables and endless genealogies, which minister questions, rather than godly edifying which is in faith: so do.

^5Now the end of the commandment is charity out of a pure heart, and of a good conscience, and of faith unfeigned:

^6From which some having swerved have turned aside unto vain jangling;

^7Desiring to be teachers of the law; understanding neither what they say, nor whereof they affirm.

^8But we know that the law is good, if a man use it lawfully;

^9Knowing this, that the law is not made for a righteous man, but for the lawless and disobedient, for the ungodly and for sinners, for unholy and profane, for murderers of fathers and murderers of mothers, for manslayers,

^10For whoremongers, for them that defile themselves with mankind, for menstealers, for liars, for perjured persons, and if there be any other thing that is contrary to sound doctrine;

^11According to the glorious gospel of the blessed God, which was committed to my trust.

^12And I thank Christ Jesus our Lord, who hath enabled me, for that he counted me faithful, putting me into the ministry;

^13Who was before a blasphemer, and a persecutor, and injurious: but I obtained mercy, because I did it ignorantly in unbelief.

^14And the grace of our Lord was exceeding abundant with faith and love which is in Christ Jesus.

^15This is a faithful saying, and worthy of all acceptation, that Christ Jesus came into the world to save sinners; of whom I am chief.

^16Howbeit for this cause I obtained mercy, that in me first Jesus Christ might shew forth all longsuffering, for a pattern to them which should hereafter believe on him to life everlasting.

^17Now unto the King eternal, immortal, invisible, the only wise God, be honour and glory for ever and ever. Amen.

^18This charge I commit unto thee, son Timothy, according to the prophecies which went before on thee, that thou by them mightest war a good warfare;

^19Holding faith, and a good conscience; which some having put away concerning faith have made shipwreck:

^20Of whom is Hymenaeus and Alexander; whom I have delivered unto Satan, that they may learn not to blaspheme.

I Timothy 2

2^1I exhort therefore, that, first of all, supplications, prayers, intercessions, and giving of thanks, be made for all men;

^2For kings, and for all that are in authority; that we may lead a quiet and peaceable life in all godliness and honesty.

^3For this is good and acceptable in the sight of God our Saviour;

^4Who will have all men to be saved, and to come unto the knowledge of the truth.

^5For there is one God, and one mediator between God and men, the man Christ Jesus;

^6Who gave himself a ransom for all, to be testified in due time.

^7Whereunto I am ordained a preacher, and an apostle, (I speak the truth in Christ, and lie not;) a teacher of the Gentiles in faith and verity.

^8I will therefore that men pray every where, lifting up holy hands, without wrath and doubting.

^9In like manner also, that women adorn themselves in modest apparel, with shamefacedness and sobriety; not with broided hair, or gold, or pearls, or costly array;

^10But (which becometh women professing godliness) with good works.

^11Let the woman learn in silence with all subjection.

^12But I suffer not a woman to teach, nor to usurp authority over the man, but to be in silence.

^13For Adam was first formed, then Eve.

^14And Adam was not deceived, but the woman being deceived was in the transgression.

^15Notwithstanding she shall be saved in childbearing, if they continue in faith and charity and holiness with sobriety.

I Timothy 3

3^1This is a true saying, If a man desire the office of a bishop, he desireth a good work.

^2A bishop then must be blameless, the husband of one wife, vigilant, sober, of good behaviour, given to hospitality, apt to teach;

^3Not given to wine, no striker, not greedy of filthy lucre; but patient, not a brawler, not covetous;

^4One that ruleth well his own house, having his children in subjection with all gravity;

^5(For if a man know not how to rule his own house, how shall he take care of the church of God?)

^6Not a novice, lest being lifted up with pride he fall into the condemnation of the devil.

^7Moreover he must have a good report of them which are without; lest he fall into reproach and the snare of the devil.

^8Likewise must the deacons be grave, not doubletongued, not given to much wine, not greedy of filthy lucre;

^9Holding the mystery of the faith in a pure conscience.

^10And let these also first be proved; then let them use the office of a deacon, being found blameless.

^11Even so must their wives be grave, not slanderers, sober, faithful in all things.

^12Let the deacons be the husbands of one wife, ruling their children and their own houses well.

^13For they that have used the office of a deacon well purchase to themselves a good degree, and great boldness in the faith which is in Christ Jesus.

^14These things write I unto thee, hoping to come unto thee shortly:

^15But if I tarry long, that thou mayest know how thou oughtest to behave thyself in the house of God, which is the church of the living God, the pillar and ground of the truth.

^16And without controversy great is the mystery of godliness: God was manifest in the flesh, justified in the Spirit, seen of angels, preached unto the Gentiles, believed on in the world, received up into glory.

I Timothy 4

4^1Now the Spirit speaketh expressly, that in the latter times some shall depart from the faith, giving heed to seducing spirits, and doctrines of devils;

^2Speaking lies in hypocrisy; having their conscience seared with a hot iron;

^3Forbidding to marry, and commanding to abstain from meats, which God hath created to be received with thanksgiving of them which believe and know the truth.

^4For every creature of God is good, and nothing to be refused, if it be received with thanksgiving:

^5For it is sanctified by the word of God and prayer.

^6If thou put the brethren in remembrance of these things, thou shalt be a good minister of Jesus Christ, nourished up in the words of faith and of good doctrine, whereunto thou hast attained.

^7But refuse profane and old wives’ fables, and exercise thyself rather unto godliness.

^8For bodily exercise profiteth little: but godliness is profitable unto all things, having promise of the life that now is, and of that which is to come.

^9This is a faithful saying and worthy of all acceptation.

^10For therefore we both labour and suffer reproach, because we trust in the living God, who is the Saviour of all men, specially of those that believe.

^11These things command and teach.

^12Let no man despise thy youth; but be thou an example of the believers, in word, in conversation, in charity, in spirit, in faith, in purity.

^13Till I come, give attendance to reading, to exhortation, to doctrine.

^14Neglect not the gift that is in thee, which was given thee by prophecy, with the laying on of the hands of the presbytery.

^15Meditate upon these things; give thyself wholly to them; that thy profiting may appear to all.

^16Take heed unto thyself, and unto the doctrine; continue in them: for in doing this thou shalt both save thyself, and them that hear thee.

I Timothy 5

5^1Rebuke not an elder, but intreat him as a father; and the younger men as brethren;

^2The elder women as mothers; the younger as sisters, with all purity.

^3Honour widows that are widows indeed.

^4But if any widow have children or nephews, let them learn first to shew piety at home, and to requite their parents: for that is good and acceptable before God.

^5Now she that is a widow indeed, and desolate, trusteth in God, and continueth in supplications and prayers night and day.

^6But she that liveth in pleasure is dead while she liveth.

^7And these things give in charge, that they may be blameless.

^8But if any provide not for his own, and specially for those of his own house, he hath denied the faith, and is worse than an infidel.

^9Let not a widow be taken into the number under threescore years old, having been the wife of one man.

^10Well reported of for good works; if she have brought up children, if she have lodged strangers, if she have washed the saints’ feet, if she have relieved the afflicted, if she have diligently followed every good work.

^11But the younger widows refuse: for when they have begun to wax wanton against Christ, they will marry;

^12Having damnation, because they have cast off their first faith.

^13And withal they learn to be idle, wandering about from house to house; and not only idle, but tattlers also and busybodies, speaking things which they ought not.

^14I will therefore that the younger women marry, bear children, guide the house, give none occasion to the adversary to speak reproachfully.

^15For some are already turned aside after Satan.

^16If any man or woman that believeth have widows, let them relieve them, and let not the church be charged; that it may relieve them that are widows indeed.

^17Let the elders that rule well be counted worthy of double honour, especially they who labour in the word and doctrine.

^18For the scripture saith, Thou shalt not muzzle the ox that treadeth out the corn. And, The labourer is worthy of his reward.

^19Against an elder receive not an accusation, but before two or three witnesses.

^20Them that sin rebuke before all, that others also may fear.

^21I charge thee before God, and the Lord Jesus Christ, and the elect angels, that thou observe these things without preferring one before another, doing nothing by partiality.

^22Lay hands suddenly on no man, neither be partaker of other men’s sins: keep thyself pure.

^23Drink no longer water, but use a little wine for thy stomach’s sake and thine often infirmities.

^24Some men’s sins are open beforehand, going before to judgment; and some men they follow after.

^25Likewise also the good works of some are manifest beforehand; and they that are otherwise cannot be hid.

I Timothy 6

6^1Let as many servants as are under the yoke count their own masters worthy of all honour, that the name of God and his doctrine be not blasphemed.

^2And they that have believing masters, let them not despise them, because they are brethren; but rather do them service, because they are faithful and beloved, partakers of the benefit. These things teach and exhort.

^3If any man teach otherwise, and consent not to wholesome words, even the words of our Lord Jesus Christ, and to the doctrine which is according to godliness;

^4He is proud, knowing nothing, but doting about questions and strifes of words, whereof cometh envy, strife, railings, evil surmisings,

^5Perverse disputings of men of corrupt minds, and destitute of the truth, supposing that gain is godliness: from such withdraw thyself.

^6But godliness with contentment is great gain.

^7For we brought nothing into this world, and it is certain we can carry nothing out.

^8And having food and raiment let us be therewith content.

^9But they that will be rich fall into temptation and a snare, and into many foolish and hurtful lusts, which drown men in destruction and perdition.

^10For the love of money is the root of all evil: which while some coveted after, they have erred from the faith, and pierced themselves through with many sorrows.

^11But thou, O man of God, flee these things; and follow after righteousness, godliness, faith, love, patience, meekness.

^12Fight the good fight of faith, lay hold on eternal life, whereunto thou art also called, and hast professed a good profession before many witnesses.

^13I give thee charge in the sight of God, who quickeneth all things, and before Christ Jesus, who before Pontius Pilate witnessed a good confession;

^14That thou keep this commandment without spot, unrebukable, until the appearing of our Lord Jesus Christ:

^15Which in his times he shall shew, who is the blessed and only Potentate, the King of kings, and Lord of lords;

^16Who only hath immortality, dwelling in the light which no man can approach unto; whom no man hath seen, nor can see: to whom be honour and power everlasting. Amen.

^17Charge them that are rich in this world, that they be not highminded, nor trust in uncertain riches, but in the living God, who giveth us richly all things to enjoy;

^18That they do good, that they be rich in good works, ready to distribute, willing to communicate;

^19Laying up in store for themselves a good foundation against the time to come, that they may lay hold on eternal life.

^20O Timothy, keep that which is committed to thy trust, avoiding profane and vain babblings, and oppositions of science falsely so called:

^21Which some professing have erred concerning the faith. Grace be with thee. Amen.

II Timothy

The Second Epistle of Paul the Apostle to

Timothy

I

^1Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ by the will of God, according to the promise of life which is in Christ Jesus,

^2To Timothy, my dearly beloved son: Grace, mercy, and peace, from God the Father and Christ Jesus our Lord.

^3I thank God, whom I serve from my forefathers with pure conscience, that without ceasing I have remembrance of thee in my prayers night and day;

^4Greatly desiring to see thee, being mindful of thy tears, that I may be filled with joy;

^5When I call to remembrance the unfeigned faith that is in thee, which dwelt first in thy grandmother Lois, and thy mother Eunice; and I am persuaded that in thee also.

^6Wherefore I put thee in remembrance that thou stir up the gift of God, which is in thee by the putting on of my hands.

^7For God hath not given us the spirit of fear; but of power, and of love, and of a sound mind.

^8Be not thou therefore ashamed of the testimony of our Lord, nor of me his prisoner: but be thou partaker of the afflictions of the gospel according to the power of God;

^9Who hath saved us, and called us with an holy calling, not according to our works, but according to his own purpose and grace, which was given us in Christ Jesus before the world began,

^10But is now made manifest by the appearing of our Saviour Jesus Christ, who hath abolished death, and hath brought life and immortality to light through the gospel:

^11Whereunto I am appointed a preacher, and an apostle, and a teacher of the Gentiles.

^12For the which cause I also suffer these things: nevertheless I am not ashamed: for I know whom I have believed, and am persuaded that he is able to keep that which I have committed unto him against that day.

^13Hold fast the form of sound words, which thou hast heard of me, in faith and love which is in Christ Jesus.

^14That good thing which was committed unto thee keep by the Holy Ghost which dwelleth in us.

^15This thou knowest, that all they which are in Asia be turned away from me; of whom are Phygellus and Hermogenes.

^16The Lord give mercy unto the house of Onesiphorus; for he oft refreshed me, and was not ashamed of my chain:

^17But, when he was in Rome, he sought me out very diligently, and found me.

^18The Lord grant unto him that he may find mercy of the Lord in that day: and in how many things he ministered unto me at Ephesus, thou knowest very well.

II

^1Thou therefore, my son, be strong in the grace that is in Christ Jesus.

^2And the things that thou hast heard of me among many witnesses, the same commit thou to faithful men, who shall be able to teach others also.

^3Thou therefore endure hardness, as a good soldier of Jesus Christ.

^4No man that warreth entangleth himself with the affairs of this life; that he may please him who hath chosen him to be a soldier.

^5And if a man also strive for masteries, yet is he not crowned, except he strive lawfully.

^6The husbandman that laboureth must be first partaker of the fruits.

^7Consider what I say; and the Lord give thee understanding in all things.

^8Remember that Jesus Christ of the seed of David was raised from the dead according to my gospel:

^9Wherein I suffer trouble, as an evil doer, even unto bonds; but the word of God is not bound.

^10Therefore I endure all things for the elect’s sakes, that they may also obtain the salvation which is in Christ Jesus with eternal glory.

^11It is a faithful saying: For if we be dead with him, we shall also live with him:

^12If we suffer, we shall also reign with him: if we deny him, he also will deny us:

^13If we believe not, yet he abideth faithful: he cannot deny himself.

^14Of these things put them in remembrance, charging them before the Lord that they strive not about words to no profit, but to the subverting of the hearers.

^15Study to shew thyself approved unto God, a workman that needeth not to be ashamed, rightly dividing the word of truth.

^16But shun profane and vain babblings: for they will increase unto more ungodliness.

^17And their word will eat as doth a canker: of whom is Hymenaeus and Philetus;

^18Who concerning the truth have erred, saying that the resurrection is past already; and overthrow the faith of some.

^19Nevertheless the foundation of God standeth sure, having this seal, The Lord knoweth them that are his. And, Let every one that nameth the name of Christ depart from iniquity.

^20But in a great house there are not only vessels of gold and of silver, but also of wood and of earth; and some to honour, and some to dishonour.

^21If a man therefore purge himself from these, he shall be a vessel unto honour, sanctified, and meet for the master’s use, and prepared unto every good work.

^22Flee also youthful lusts: but follow righteousness, faith, charity, peace, with them that call on the Lord out of a pure heart.

^23But foolish and unlearned questions avoid, knowing that they do gender strifes.

^24And the servant of the Lord must not strive; but be gentle unto all men, apt to teach, patient,

^25In meekness instructing those that oppose themselves; if God peradventure will give them repentance to the acknowledging of the truth;

^26And that they may recover themselves out of the snare of the devil, who are taken captive by him at his will.

III

^1This know also, that in the last days perilous times shall come.

^2For men shall be lovers of their own selves, covetous, boasters, proud, blasphemers, disobedient to parents, unthankful, unholy,

^3Without natural affection, trucebreakers, false accusers, incontinent, fierce, despisers of those that are good,

^4Traitors, heady, highminded, lovers of pleasures more than lovers of God;

^5Having a form of godliness, but denying the power thereof: from such turn away.

^6For of this sort are they which creep into houses, and lead captive silly women laden with sins, led away with divers lusts,

^7Ever learning, and never able to come to the knowledge of the truth.

^8Now as Jannes and Jambres withstood Moses, so do these also resist the truth: men of corrupt minds, reprobate concerning the faith.

^9But they shall proceed no further: for their folly shall be manifest unto all men, as their’s also was.

^10But thou hast fully known my doctrine, manner of life, purpose, faith, longsuffering, charity, patience,

^11Persecutions, afflictions, which came unto me at Antioch, at Iconium, at Lystra; what persecutions I endured: but out of them all the Lord delivered me.

^12Yea, and all that will live godly in Christ Jesus shall suffer persecution.

^13But evil men and seducers shall wax worse and worse, deceiving, and being deceived.

^14But continue thou in the things which thou hast learned and hast been assured of, knowing of whom thou hast learned them;

^15And that from a child thou hast known the holy scriptures, which are able to make thee wise unto salvation through faith which is in Christ Jesus.

^16All scripture is given by inspiration of God, and is profitable for doctrine, for reproof, for correction, for instruction in righteousness:

^17That the man of God may be perfect, throughly furnished unto all good works.

IV

^1I charge thee therefore before God, and the Lord Jesus Christ, who shall judge the quick and the dead at his appearing and his kingdom;

^2Preach the word; be instant in season, out of season; reprove, rebuke, exhort with all longsuffering and doctrine.

^3For the time will come when they will not endure sound doctrine; but after their own lusts shall they heap to themselves teachers, having itching ears;

^4And they shall turn away their ears from the truth, and shall be turned unto fables.

^5But watch thou in all things, endure afflictions, do the work of an evangelist, make full proof of thy ministry.

^6For I am now ready to be offered, and the time of my departure is at hand.

^7I have fought a good fight, I have finished my course, I have kept the faith:

^8Henceforth there is laid up for me a crown of righteousness, which the Lord, the righteous judge, shall give me at that day: and not to me only, but unto all them also that love his appearing.

^9Do thy diligence to come shortly unto me:

^10For Demas hath forsaken me, having loved this present world, and is departed unto Thessalonica; Crescens to Galatia, Titus unto Dalmatia.

^11Only Luke is with me. Take Mark, and bring him with thee: for he is profitable to me for the ministry.

^12And Tychicus have I sent to Ephesus.

^13The cloke that I left at Troas with Carpus, when thou comest, bring with thee, and the books, but especially the parchments.

^14Alexander the coppersmith did me much evil: the Lord reward him according to his works:

^15Of whom be thou ware also; for he hath greatly withstood our words.

^16At my first answer no man stood with me, but all men forsook me: I pray God that it may not be laid to their charge.

^17Notwithstanding the Lord stood with me, and strengthened me; that by me the preaching might be fully known, and that all the Gentiles might hear: and I was delivered out of the mouth of the lion.

^18And the Lord shall deliver me from every evil work, and will preserve me unto his heavenly kingdom: to whom be glory for ever and ever. Amen.

^19Salute Prisca and Aquila, and the household of Onesiphorus.

^20Erastus abode at Corinth: but Trophimus have I left at Miletum sick.

^21Do thy diligence to come before winter. Eubulus greeteth thee, and Pudens, and Linus, and Claudia, and all the brethren.

^22The Lord Jesus Christ be with thy spirit. Grace be with you. Amen.

Titus

The Epistle of Paul the Apostle to

Titus

I

1^1Paul, a servant of God, and an apostle of Jesus Christ, according to the faith of God’s elect, and the acknowledging of the truth which is after godliness;

^2In hope of eternal life, which God, that cannot lie, promised before the world began;

^3But hath in due times manifested his word through preaching, which is committed unto me according to the commandment of God our Saviour;

^4To Titus, mine own son after the common faith: Grace, mercy, and peace, from God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ our Saviour.

^5For this cause left I thee in Crete, that thou shouldest set in order the things that are wanting, and ordain elders in every city, as I had appointed thee:

^6If any be blameless, the husband of one wife, having faithful children not accused of riot or unruly.

^7For a bishop must be blameless, as the steward of God; not selfwilled, not soon angry, not given to wine, no striker, not given to filthy lucre;

^8But a lover of hospitality, a lover of good men, sober, just, holy, temperate;

^9Holding fast the faithful word as he hath been taught, that he may be able by sound doctrine both to exhort and to convince the gainsayers.

^10For there are many unruly and vain talkers and deceivers, specially they of the circumcision:

^11Whose mouths must be stopped, who subvert whole houses, teaching things which they ought not, for filthy lucre’s sake.

^12One of themselves, even a prophet of their own, said, The Cretians are alway liars, evil beasts, slow bellies.

^13This witness is true. Wherefore rebuke them sharply, that they may be sound in the faith;

^14Not giving heed to Jewish fables, and commandments of men, that turn from the truth.

^15Unto the pure all things are pure: but unto them that are defiled and unbelieving is nothing pure; but even their mind and conscience is defiled.

^16They profess that they know God; but in works they deny him, being abominable, and disobedient, and unto every good work reprobate.

II

2^1But speak thou the things which become sound doctrine:

^2That the aged men be sober, grave, temperate, sound in faith, in charity, in patience.

^3The aged women likewise, that they be in behaviour as becometh holiness, not false accusers, not given to much wine, teachers of good things;

^4That they may teach the young women to be sober, to love their husbands, to love their children,

^5To be discreet, chaste, keepers at home, good, obedient to their own husbands, that the word of God be not blasphemed.

^6Young men likewise exhort to be sober minded.

^7In all things shewing thyself a pattern of good works: in doctrine shewing uncorruptness, gravity, sincerity,

^8Sound speech, that cannot be condemned; that he that is of the contrary part may be ashamed, having no evil thing to say of you.

^9Exhort servants to be obedient unto their own masters, and to please them well in all things; not answering again;

^10Not purloining, but shewing all good fidelity; that they may adorn the doctrine of God our Saviour in all things.

^11For the grace of God that bringeth salvation hath appeared to all men,

^12Teaching us that, denying ungodliness and worldly lusts, we should live soberly, righteously, and godly, in this present world;

^13Looking for that blessed hope, and the glorious appearing of the great God and our Saviour Jesus Christ;

^14Who gave himself for us, that he might redeem us from all iniquity, and purify unto himself a peculiar people, zealous of good works.

^15These things speak, and exhort, and rebuke with all authority. Let no man despise thee.

III

3^1Put them in mind to be subject to principalities and powers, to obey magistrates, to be ready to every good work,

^2To speak evil of no man, to be no brawlers, but gentle, shewing all meekness unto all men.

^3For we ourselves also were sometimes foolish, disobedient, deceived, serving divers lusts and pleasures, living in malice and envy, hateful, and hating one another.

^4But after that the kindness and love of God our Saviour toward man appeared,

^5Not by works of righteousness which we have done, but according to his mercy he saved us, by the washing of regeneration, and renewing of the Holy Ghost;

^6Which he shed on us abundantly through Jesus Christ our Saviour;

^7That being justified by his grace, we should be made heirs according to the hope of eternal life.

^8This is a faithful saying, and these things I will that thou affirm constantly, that they which have believed in God might be careful to maintain good works. These things are good and profitable unto men.

^9But avoid foolish questions, and genealogies, and contentions, and strivings about the law; for they are unprofitable and vain.

^10A man that is an heretick after the first and second admonition reject;

^11Knowing that he that is such is subverted, and sinneth, being condemned of himself.

^12When I shall send Artemas unto thee, or Tychicus, be diligent to come unto me to Nicopolis: for I have determined there to winter.

^13Bring Zenas the lawyer and Apollos on their journey diligently, that nothing be wanting unto them.

^14And let our’s also learn to maintain good works for necessary uses, that they be not unfruitful.

^15All that are with me salute thee. Greet them that love us in the faith. Grace be with you all. Amen.

Philemon

The Epistle of Paul the Apostle to

Philemon

I

1^1Paul, a prisoner of Jesus Christ, and Timothy our brother, unto Philemon our dearly beloved, and fellowlabourer,

^2And to our beloved Apphia, and Archippus our fellowsoldier, and to the church in thy house:

^3Grace to you, and peace, from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.

^4I thank my God, making mention of thee always in my prayers,

^5Hearing of thy love and faith, which thou hast toward the Lord Jesus, and toward all saints;

^6That the communication of thy faith may become effectual by the acknowledging of every good thing which is in you in Christ Jesus.

^7For we have great joy and consolation in thy love, because the bowels of the saints are refreshed by thee, brother.

^8Wherefore, though I might be much bold in Christ to enjoin thee that which is convenient,

^9Yet for love’s sake I rather beseech thee, being such an one as Paul the aged, and now also a prisoner of Jesus Christ.

^10I beseech thee for my son Onesimus, whom I have begotten in my bonds:

^11Which in time past was to thee unprofitable, but now profitable to thee and to me:

^12Whom I have sent again: thou therefore receive him, that is, mine own bowels:

^13Whom I would have retained with me, that in thy stead he might have ministered unto me in the bonds of the gospel:

^14But without thy mind would I do nothing; that thy benefit should not be as it were of necessity, but willingly.

^15For perhaps he therefore departed for a season, that thou shouldest receive him for ever;

^16Not now as a servant, but above a servant, a brother beloved, specially to me, but how much more unto thee, both in the flesh, and in the Lord?

^17If thou count me therefore a partner, receive him as myself.

^18If he hath wronged thee, or oweth thee ought, put that on mine account;

^19I Paul have written it with mine own hand, I will repay it: albeit I do not say to thee how thou owest unto me even thine own self besides.

^20Yea, brother, let me have joy of thee in the Lord: refresh my bowels in the Lord.

^21Having confidence in thy obedience I wrote unto thee, knowing that thou wilt also do more than I say.

^22But withal prepare me also a lodging: for I trust that through your prayers I shall be given unto you.

^23There salute thee Epaphras, my fellowprisoner in Christ Jesus;

^24Marcus, Aristarchus, Demas, Lucas, my fellowlabourers.

^25The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit. Amen.

Hebrews

The Epistle to the

Hebrews

I

^1God, who at sundry times and in divers manners spake in time past unto the fathers by the prophets,

^2Hath in these last days spoken unto us by his Son, whom he hath appointed heir of all things, by whom also he made the worlds;

^3Who being the brightness of his glory, and the express image of his person, and upholding all things by the word of his power, when he had by himself purged our sins, sat down on the right hand of the Majesty on high:

^4Being made so much better than the angels, as he hath by inheritance obtained a more excellent name than they.

^5For unto which of the angels said he at any time, Thou art my Son, this day have I begotten thee? And again, I will be to him a Father, and he shall be to me a Son?

^6And again, when he bringeth in the firstbegotten into the world, he saith, And let all the angels of God worship him.

^7And of the angels he saith, Who maketh his angels spirits, and his ministers a flame of fire.

^8But unto the Son he saith, Thy throne, O God, is for ever and ever: a sceptre of righteousness is the sceptre of thy kingdom.

^9Thou hast loved righteousness, and hated iniquity; therefore God, even thy God, hath anointed thee with the oil of gladness above thy fellows.

^10And, Thou, Lord, in the beginning hast laid the foundation of the earth; and the heavens are the works of thine hands:

^11They shall perish; but thou remainest; and they all shall wax old as doth a garment;

^12And as a vesture shalt thou fold them up, and they shall be changed: but thou art the same, and thy years shall not fail.

^13But to which of the angels said he at any time, Sit on my right hand, until I make thine enemies thy footstool?

^14Are they not all ministering spirits, sent forth to minister for them who shall be heirs of salvation?

II

^1Therefore we ought to give the more earnest heed to the things which we have heard, lest at any time we should let them slip.

^2For if the word spoken by angels was stedfast, and every transgression and disobedience received a just recompence of reward;

^3How shall we escape, if we neglect so great salvation; which at the first began to be spoken by the Lord, and was confirmed unto us by them that heard him;

^4God also bearing them witness, both with signs and wonders, and with divers miracles, and gifts of the Holy Ghost, according to his own will?

^5For unto the angels hath he not put in subjection the world to come, whereof we speak.

^6But one in a certain place testified, saying, What is man, that thou art mindful of him? or the son of man that thou visitest him?

^7Thou madest him a little lower than the angels; thou crownedst him with glory and honour, and didst set him over the works of thy hands:

^8Thou hast put all things in subjection under his feet. For in that he put all in subjection under him, he left nothing that is not put under him. But now we see not yet all things put under him.

^9But we see Jesus, who was made a little lower than the angels for the suffering of death, crowned with glory and honour; that he by the grace of God should taste death for every man.

^10For it became him, for whom are all things, and by whom are all things, in bringing many sons unto glory, to make the captain of their salvation perfect through sufferings.

^11For both he that sanctifieth and they who are sanctified are all of one: for which cause he is not ashamed to call them brethren,

^12Saying, I will declare thy name unto my brethren, in the midst of the church will I sing praise unto thee.

^13And again, I will put my trust in him. And again, Behold I and the children which God hath given me.

^14Forasmuch then as the children are partakers of flesh and blood, he also himself likewise took part of the same; that through death he might destroy him that had the power of death, that is, the devil;

^15And deliver them who through fear of death were all their lifetime subject to bondage.

^16For verily he took not on him the nature of angels; but he took on him the seed of Abraham.

^17Wherefore in all things it behoved him to be made like unto his brethren, that he might be a merciful and faithful high priest in things pertaining to God, to make reconciliation for the sins of the people.

^18For in that he himself hath suffered being tempted, he is able to succour them that are tempted.

III

^1Wherefore, holy brethren, partakers of the heavenly calling, consider the Apostle and High Priest of our profession, Christ Jesus;

^2Who was faithful to him that appointed him, as also Moses was faithful in all his house.

^3For this man was counted worthy of more glory than Moses, inasmuch as he who hath builded the house hath more honour than the house.

^4For every house is builded by some man; but he that built all things is God.

^5And Moses verily was faithful in all his house, as a servant, for a testimony of those things which were to be spoken after;

^6But Christ as a son over his own house; whose house are we, if we hold fast the confidence and the rejoicing of the hope firm unto the end.

^7Wherefore (as the Holy Ghost saith, To day if ye will hear his voice,

^8Harden not your hearts, as in the provocation, in the day of temptation in the wilderness:

^9When your fathers tempted me, proved me, and saw my works forty years.

^10Wherefore I was grieved with that generation, and said, They do alway err in their heart; and they have not known my ways.

^11So I sware in my wrath, They shall not enter into my rest.)

^12Take heed, brethren, lest there be in any of you an evil heart of unbelief, in departing from the living God.

^13But exhort one another daily, while it is called To day; lest any of you be hardened through the deceitfulness of sin.

^14For we are made partakers of Christ, if we hold the beginning of our confidence stedfast unto the end;

^15While it is said, To day if ye will hear his voice, harden not your hearts, as in the provocation.

^16For some, when they had heard, did provoke: howbeit not all that came out of Egypt by Moses.

^17But with whom was he grieved forty years? was it not with them that had sinned, whose carcases fell in the wilderness?

^18And to whom sware he that they should not enter into his rest, but to them that believed not?

^19So we see that they could not enter in because of unbelief.

IV

^1Let us therefore fear, lest, a promise being left us of entering into his rest, any of you should seem to come short of it.

^2For unto us was the gospel preached, as well as unto them: but the word preached did not profit them, not being mixed with faith in them that heard it.

^3For we which have believed do enter into rest, as he said, As I have sworn in my wrath, if they shall enter into my rest: although the works were finished from the foundation of the world.

^4For he spake in a certain place of the seventh day on this wise, And God did rest the seventh day from all his works.

^5And in this place again, If they shall enter into my rest.

^6Seeing therefore it remaineth that some must enter therein, and they to whom it was first preached entered not in because of unbelief:

^7Again, he limiteth a certain day, saying in David, To day, after so long a time; as it is said, To day if ye will hear his voice, harden not your hearts.

^8For if Jesus had given them rest, then would he not afterward have spoken of another day.

^9There remaineth therefore a rest to the people of God.

^10For he that is entered into his rest, he also hath ceased from his own works, as God did from his.

^11Let us labour therefore to enter into that rest, lest any man fall after the same example of unbelief.

^12For the word of God is quick, and powerful, and sharper than any twoedged sword, piercing even to the dividing asunder of soul and spirit, and of the joints and marrow, and is a discerner of the thoughts and intents of the heart.

^13Neither is there any creature that is not manifest in his sight: but all things are naked and opened unto the eyes of him with whom we have to do.

^14Seeing then that we have a great high priest, that is passed into the heavens, Jesus the Son of God, let us hold fast our profession.

^15For we have not an high priest which cannot be touched with the feeling of our infirmities; but was in all points tempted like as we are, yet without sin.

^16Let us therefore come boldly unto the throne of grace, that we may obtain mercy, and find grace to help in time of need.

V

^1For every high priest taken from among men is ordained for men in things pertaining to God, that he may offer both gifts and sacrifices for sins:

^2Who can have compassion on the ignorant, and on them that are out of the way; for that he himself also is compassed with infirmity.

^3And by reason hereof he ought, as for the people, so also for himself, to offer for sins.

^4And no man taketh this honour unto himself, but he that is called of God, as was Aaron.

^5So also Christ glorified not himself to be made an high priest; but he that said unto him, Thou art my Son, to day have I begotten thee.

^6As he saith also in another place, Thou art a priest for ever after the order of Melchisedec.

^7Who in the days of his flesh, when he had offered up prayers and supplications with strong crying and tears unto him that was able to save him from death, and was heard in that he feared;

^8Though he were a Son, yet learned he obedience by the things which he suffered;

^9And being made perfect, he became the author of eternal salvation unto all them that obey him;

^10Called of God an high priest after the order of Melchisedec.

^11Of whom we have many things to say, and hard to be uttered, seeing ye are dull of hearing.

^12For when for the time ye ought to be teachers, ye have need that one teach you again which be the first principles of the oracles of God; and are become such as have need of milk, and not of strong meat.

^13For every one that useth milk is unskilful in the word of righteousness: for he is a babe.

^14But strong meat belongeth to them that are of full age, even those who by reason of use have their senses exercised to discern both good and evil.

VI

^1Therefore leaving the principles of the doctrine of Christ, let us go on unto perfection; not laying again the foundation of repentance from dead works, and of faith toward God,

^2Of the doctrine of baptisms, and of laying on of hands, and of resurrection of the dead, and of eternal judgment.

^3And this will we do, if God permit.

^4For it is impossible for those who were once enlightened, and have tasted of the heavenly gift, and were made partakers of the Holy Ghost,

^5And have tasted the good word of God, and the powers of the world to come,

^6If they shall fall away, to renew them again unto repentance; seeing they crucify to themselves the Son of God afresh, and put him to an open shame.

^7For the earth which drinketh in the rain that cometh oft upon it, and bringeth forth herbs meet for them by whom it is dressed, receiveth blessing from God:

^8But that which beareth thorns and briers is rejected, and is nigh unto cursing; whose end is to be burned.

^9But, beloved, we are persuaded better things of you, and things that accompany salvation, though we thus speak.

^10For God is not unrighteous to forget your work and labour of love, which ye have shewed toward his name, in that ye have ministered to the saints, and do minister.

^11And we desire that every one of you do shew the same diligence to the full assurance of hope unto the end:

^12That ye be not slothful, but followers of them who through faith and patience inherit the promises.

^13For when God made promise to Abraham, because he could swear by no greater, he sware by himself,

^14Saying, Surely blessing I will bless thee, and multiplying I will multiply thee.

^15And so, after he had patiently endured, he obtained the promise.

^16For men verily swear by the greater: and an oath for confirmation is to them an end of all strife.

^17Wherein God, willing more abundantly to shew unto the heirs of promise the immutability of his counsel, confirmed it by an oath:

^18That by two immutable things, in which it was impossible for God to lie, we might have a strong consolation, who have fled for refuge to lay hold upon the hope set before us:

^19Which hope we have as an anchor of the soul, both sure and stedfast, and which entereth into that within the veil;

^20Whither the forerunner is for us entered, even Jesus, made an high priest for ever after the order of Melchisedec.

VII

^1For this Melchisedec, king of Salem, priest of the most high God, who met Abraham returning from the slaughter of the kings, and blessed him;

^2To whom also Abraham gave a tenth part of all; first being by interpretation King of righteousness, and after that also King of Salem, which is, King of peace;

^3Without father, without mother, without descent, having neither beginning of days, nor end of life; but made like unto the Son of God; abideth a priest continually.

^4Now consider how great this man was, unto whom even the patriarch Abraham gave the tenth of the spoils.

^5And verily they that are of the sons of Levi, who receive the office of the priesthood, have a commandment to take tithes of the people according to the law, that is, of their brethren, though they come out of the loins of Abraham:

^6But he whose descent is not counted from them received tithes of Abraham, and blessed him that had the promises.

^7And without all contradiction the less is blessed of the better.

^8And here men that die receive tithes; but there he receiveth them, of whom it is witnessed that he liveth.

^9And as I may so say, Levi also, who receiveth tithes, payed tithes in Abraham.

^10For he was yet in the loins of his father, when Melchisedec met him.

^11If therefore perfection were by the Levitical priesthood, (for under it the people received the law,) what further need was there that another priest should rise after the order of Melchisedec, and not be called after the order of Aaron?

^12For the priesthood being changed, there is made of necessity a change also of the law.

^13For he of whom these things are spoken pertaineth to another tribe, of which no man gave attendance at the altar.

^14For it is evident that our Lord sprang out of Juda; of which tribe Moses spake nothing concerning priesthood.

^15And it is yet far more evident: for that after the similitude of Melchisedec there ariseth another priest,

^16Who is made, not after the law of a carnal commandment, but after the power of an endless life.

^17For he testifieth, Thou art a priest for ever after the order of Melchisedec.

^18For there is verily a disannulling of the commandment going before for the weakness and unprofitableness thereof.

^19For the law made nothing perfect, but the bringing in of a better hope did; by the which we draw nigh unto God.

^20And inasmuch as not without an oath he was made priest:

^21(For those priests were made without an oath; but this with an oath by him that said unto him, The Lord sware and will not repent, Thou art a priest for ever after the order of Melchisedec:)

^22By so much was Jesus made a surety of a better testament.

^23And they truly were many priests, because they were not suffered to continue by reason of death:

^24But this man, because he continueth ever, hath an unchangeable priesthood.

^25Wherefore he is able also to save them to the uttermost that come unto God by him, seeing he ever liveth to make intercession for them.

^26For such an high priest became us, who is holy, harmless, undefiled, separate from sinners, and made higher than the heavens;

^27Who needeth not daily, as those high priests, to offer up sacrifice, first for his own sins, and then for the people’s: for this he did once, when he offered up himself.

^28For the law maketh men high priests which have infirmity; but the word of the oath, which was since the law, maketh the Son, who is consecrated for evermore.

VIII

^1Now of the things which we have spoken this is the sum: We have such an high priest, who is set on the right hand of the throne of the Majesty in the heavens;

^2A minister of the sanctuary, and of the true tabernacle, which the Lord pitched, and not man.

^3For every high priest is ordained to offer gifts and sacrifices: wherefore it is of necessity that this man have somewhat also to offer.

^4For if he were on earth, he should not be a priest, seeing that there are priests that offer gifts according to the law:

^5Who serve unto the example and shadow of heavenly things, as Moses was admonished of God when he was about to make the tabernacle: for, See, saith he, that thou make all things according to the pattern shewed to thee in the mount.

^6But now hath he obtained a more excellent ministry, by how much also he is the mediator of a better covenant, which was established upon better promises.

^7For if that first covenant had been faultless, then should no place have been sought for the second.

^8For finding fault with them, he saith, Behold, the days come, saith the Lord, when I will make a new covenant with the house of Israel and with the house of Judah:

^9Not according to the covenant that I made with their fathers in the day when I took them by the hand to lead them out of the land of Egypt; because they continued not in my covenant, and I regarded them not, saith the Lord.

^10For this is the covenant that I will make with the house of Israel after those days, saith the Lord; I will put my laws into their mind, and write them in their hearts: and I will be to them a God, and they shall be to me a people:

^11And they shall not teach every man his neighbour, and every man his brother, saying, Know the Lord: for all shall know me, from the least to the greatest.

^12For I will be merciful to their unrighteousness, and their sins and their iniquities will I remember no more.

^13In that he saith, A new covenant, he hath made the first old. Now that which decayeth and waxeth old is ready to vanish away.

IX

^1Then verily the first covenant had also ordinances of divine service, and a worldly sanctuary.

^2For there was a tabernacle made; the first, wherein was the candlestick, and the table, and the shewbread; which is called the sanctuary.

^3And after the second veil, the tabernacle which is called the Holiest of all;

^4Which had the golden censer, and the ark of the covenant overlaid round about with gold, wherein was the golden pot that had manna, and Aaron’s rod that budded, and the tables of the covenant;

^5And over it the cherubims of glory shadowing the mercyseat; of which we cannot now speak particularly.

^6Now when these things were thus ordained, the priests went always into the first tabernacle, accomplishing the service of God.

^7But into the second went the high priest alone once every year, not without blood, which he offered for himself, and for the errors of the people:

^8The Holy Ghost this signifying, that the way into the holiest of all was not yet made manifest, while as the first tabernacle was yet standing:

^9Which was a figure for the time then present, in which were offered both gifts and sacrifices, that could not make him that did the service perfect, as pertaining to the conscience;

^10Which stood only in meats and drinks, and divers washings, and carnal ordinances, imposed on them until the time of reformation.

^11But Christ being come an high priest of good things to come, by a greater and more perfect tabernacle, not made with hands, that is to say, not of this building;

^12Neither by the blood of goats and calves, but by his own blood he entered in once into the holy place, having obtained eternal redemption for us.

^13For if the blood of bulls and of goats, and the ashes of an heifer sprinkling the unclean, sanctifieth to the purifying of the flesh:

^14How much more shall the blood of Christ, who through the eternal Spirit offered himself without spot to God, purge your conscience from dead works to serve the living God?

^15And for this cause he is the mediator of the new testament, that by means of death, for the redemption of the transgressions that were under the first testament, they which are called might receive the promise of eternal inheritance.

^16For where a testament is, there must also of necessity be the death of the testator.

^17For a testament is of force after men are dead: otherwise it is of no strength at all while the testator liveth.

^18Whereupon neither the first testament was dedicated without blood.

^19For when Moses had spoken every precept to all the people according to the law, he took the blood of calves and of goats, with water, and scarlet wool, and hyssop, and sprinkled both the book, and all the people,

^20Saying, This is the blood of the testament which God hath enjoined unto you.

^21Moreover he sprinkled with blood both the tabernacle, and all the vessels of the ministry.

^22And almost all things are by the law purged with blood; and without shedding of blood is no remission.

^23It was therefore necessary that the patterns of things in the heavens should be purified with these; but the heavenly things themselves with better sacrifices than these.

^24For Christ is not entered into the holy places made with hands, which are the figures of the true; but into heaven itself, now to appear in the presence of God for us:

^25Nor yet that he should offer himself often, as the high priest entereth into the holy place every year with blood of others;

^26For then must he often have suffered since the foundation of the world: but now once in the end of the world hath he appeared to put away sin by the sacrifice of himself.

^27And as it is appointed unto men once to die, but after this the judgment:

^28So Christ was once offered to bear the sins of many; and unto them that look for him shall he appear the second time without sin unto salvation.

X

^1For the law having a shadow of good things to come, and not the very image of the things, can never with those sacrifices which they offered year by year continually make the comers thereunto perfect.

^2For then would they not have ceased to be offered? because that the worshippers once purged should have had no more conscience of sins.

^3But in those sacrifices there is a remembrance again made of sins every year.

^4For it is not possible that the blood of bulls and of goats should take away sins.

^5Wherefore when he cometh into the world, he saith, Sacrifice and offering thou wouldest not, but a body hast thou prepared me:

^6In burnt offerings and sacrifices for sin thou hast had no pleasure.

^7Then said I, Lo, I come (in the volume of the book it is written of me,) to do thy will, O God.

^8Above when he said, Sacrifice and offering and burnt offerings and offering for sin thou wouldest not, neither hadst pleasure therein; which are offered by the law;

^9Then said he, Lo, I come to do thy will, O God. He taketh away the first, that he may establish the second.

^10By the which will we are sanctified through the offering of the body of Jesus Christ once for all.

^11And every priest standeth daily ministering and offering oftentimes the same sacrifices, which can never take away sins:

^12But this man, after he had offered one sacrifice for sins for ever, sat down on the right hand of God;

^13From henceforth expecting till his enemies be made his footstool.

^14For by one offering he hath perfected for ever them that are sanctified.

^15Whereof the Holy Ghost also is a witness to us: for after that he had said before,

^16This is the covenant that I will make with them after those days, saith the Lord, I will put my laws into their hearts, and in their minds will I write them;

^17And their sins and iniquities will I remember no more.

^18Now where remission of these is, there is no more offering for sin.

^19Having therefore, brethren, boldness to enter into the holiest by the blood of Jesus,

^20By a new and living way, which he hath consecrated for us, through the veil, that is to say, his flesh;

^21And having an high priest over the house of God;

^22Let us draw near with a true heart in full assurance of faith, having our hearts sprinkled from an evil conscience, and our bodies washed with pure water.

^23Let us hold fast the profession of our faith without wavering; (for he is faithful that promised;)

^24And let us consider one another to provoke unto love and to good works:

^25Not forsaking the assembling of ourselves together, as the manner of some is; but exhorting one another: and so much the more, as ye see the day approaching.

^26For if we sin wilfully after that we have received the knowledge of the truth, there remaineth no more sacrifice for sins,

^27But a certain fearful looking for of judgment and fiery indignation, which shall devour the adversaries.

^28He that despised Moses’ law died without mercy under two or three witnesses:

^29Of how much sorer punishment, suppose ye, shall he be thought worthy, who hath trodden under foot the Son of God, and hath counted the blood of the covenant, wherewith he was sanctified, an unholy thing, and hath done despite unto the Spirit of grace?

^30For we know him that hath said, Vengeance belongeth unto me, I will recompense, saith the Lord. And again, The Lord shall judge his people.

^31It is a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God.

^32But call to remembrance the former days, in which, after ye were illuminated, ye endured a great fight of afflictions;

^33Partly, whilst ye were made a gazingstock both by reproaches and afflictions; and partly, whilst ye became companions of them that were so used.

^34For ye had compassion of me in my bonds, and took joyfully the spoiling of your goods, knowing in yourselves that ye have in heaven a better and an enduring substance.

^35Cast not away therefore your confidence, which hath great recompence of reward.

^36For ye have need of patience, that, after ye have done the will of God, ye might receive the promise.

^37For yet a little while, and he that shall come will come, and will not tarry.

^38Now the just shall live by faith: but if any man draw back, my soul shall have no pleasure in him.

^39But we are not of them who draw back unto perdition; but of them that believe to the saving of the soul.

XI

^1Now faith is the substance of things hoped for, the evidence of things not seen.

^2For by it the elders obtained a good report.

^3Through faith we understand that the worlds were framed by the word of God, so that things which are seen were not made of things which do appear.

^4By faith Abel offered unto God a more excellent sacrifice than Cain, by which he obtained witness that he was righteous, God testifying of his gifts: and by it he being dead yet speaketh.

^5By faith Enoch was translated that he should not see death; and was not found, because God had translated him: for before his translation he had this testimony, that he pleased God.

^6But without faith it is impossible to please him: for he that cometh to God must believe that he is, and that he is a rewarder of them that diligently seek him.

^7By faith Noah, being warned of God of things not seen as yet, moved with fear, prepared an ark to the saving of his house; by the which he condemned the world, and became heir of the righteousness which is by faith.

^8By faith Abraham, when he was called to go out into a place which he should after receive for an inheritance, obeyed; and he went out, not knowing whither he went.

^9By faith he sojourned in the land of promise, as in a strange country, dwelling in tabernacles with Isaac and Jacob, the heirs with him of the same promise:

^10For he looked for a city which hath foundations, whose builder and maker is God.

^11Through faith also Sara herself received strength to conceive seed, and was delivered of a child when she was past age, because she judged him faithful who had promised.

^12Therefore sprang there even of one, and him as good as dead, so many as the stars of the sky in multitude, and as the sand which is by the sea shore innumerable.

^13These all died in faith, not having received the promises, but having seen them afar off, and were persuaded of them, and embraced them, and confessed that they were strangers and pilgrims on the earth.

^14For they that say such things declare plainly that they seek a country.

^15And truly, if they had been mindful of that country from whence they came out, they might have had opportunity to have returned.

^16But now they desire a better country, that is, an heavenly: wherefore God is not ashamed to be called their God: for he hath prepared for them a city.

^17By faith Abraham, when he was tried, offered up Isaac: and he that had received the promises offered up his only begotten son,

^18Of whom it was said, That in Isaac shall thy seed be called:

^19Accounting that God was able to raise him up, even from the dead; from whence also he received him in a figure.

^20By faith Isaac blessed Jacob and Esau concerning things to come.

^21By faith Jacob, when he was a dying, blessed both the sons of Joseph; and worshipped, leaning upon the top of his staff.

^22By faith Joseph, when he died, made mention of the departing of the children of Israel; and gave commandment concerning his bones.

^23By faith Moses, when he was born, was hid three months of his parents, because they saw he was a proper child; and they were not afraid of the king’s commandment.

^24By faith Moses, when he was come to years, refused to be called the son of Pharaoh’s daughter;

^25Choosing rather to suffer affliction with the people of God, than to enjoy the pleasures of sin for a season;

^26Esteeming the reproach of Christ greater riches than the treasures in Egypt: for he had respect unto the recompence of the reward.

^27By faith he forsook Egypt, not fearing the wrath of the king: for he endured, as seeing him who is invisible.

^28Through faith he kept the passover, and the sprinkling of blood, lest he that destroyed the firstborn should touch them.

^29By faith they passed through the Red sea as by dry land: which the Egyptians assaying to do were drowned.

^30By faith the walls of Jericho fell down, after they were compassed about seven days.

^31By faith the harlot Rahab perished not with them that believed not, when she had received the spies with peace.

^32And what shall I more say? for the time would fail me to tell of Gedeon, and of Barak, and of Samson, and of Jephthae; of David also, and Samuel, and of the prophets:

^33Who through faith subdued kingdoms, wrought righteousness, obtained promises, stopped the mouths of lions.

^34Quenched the violence of fire, escaped the edge of the sword, out of weakness were made strong, waxed valiant in fight, turned to flight the armies of the aliens.

^35Women received their dead raised to life again: and others were tortured, not accepting deliverance; that they might obtain a better resurrection:

^36And others had trial of cruel mockings and scourgings, yea, moreover of bonds and imprisonment:

^37They were stoned, they were sawn asunder, were tempted, were slain with the sword: they wandered about in sheepskins and goatskins; being destitute, afflicted, tormented;

^38(Of whom the world was not worthy:) they wandered in deserts, and in mountains, and in dens and caves of the earth.

^39And these all, having obtained a good report through faith, received not the promise:

^40God having provided some better thing for us, that they without us should not be made perfect.

XII

^1Wherefore seeing we also are compassed about with so great a cloud of witnesses, let us lay aside every weight, and the sin which doth so easily beset us, and let us run with patience the race that is set before us,

^2Looking unto Jesus the author and finisher of our faith; who for the joy that was set before him endured the cross, despising the shame, and is set down at the right hand of the throne of God.

^3For consider him that endured such contradiction of sinners against himself, lest ye be wearied and faint in your minds.

^4Ye have not yet resisted unto blood, striving against sin.

^5And ye have forgotten the exhortation which speaketh unto you as unto children, My son, despise not thou the chastening of the Lord, nor faint when thou art rebuked of him:

^6For whom the Lord loveth he chasteneth, and scourgeth every son whom he receiveth.

^7If ye endure chastening, God dealeth with you as with sons; for what son is he whom the father chasteneth not?

^8But if ye be without chastisement, whereof all are partakers, then are ye bastards, and not sons.

^9Furthermore we have had fathers of our flesh which corrected us, and we gave them reverence: shall we not much rather be in subjection unto the Father of spirits, and live?

^10For they verily for a few days chastened us after their own pleasure; but he for our profit, that we might be partakers of his holiness.

^11Now no chastening for the present seemeth to be joyous, but grievous: nevertheless afterward it yieldeth the peaceable fruit of righteousness unto them which are exercised thereby.

^12Wherefore lift up the hands which hang down, and the feeble knees;

^13And make straight paths for your feet, lest that which is lame be turned out of the way; but let it rather be healed.

^14Follow peace with all men, and holiness, without which no man shall see the Lord:

^15Looking diligently lest any man fail of the grace of God; lest any root of bitterness springing up trouble you, and thereby many be defiled;

^16Lest there be any fornicator, or profane person, as Esau, who for one morsel of meat sold his birthright.

^17For ye know how that afterward, when he would have inherited the blessing, he was rejected: for he found no place of repentance, though he sought it carefully with tears.

^18For ye are not come unto the mount that might be touched, and that burned with fire, nor unto blackness, and darkness, and tempest,

^19And the sound of a trumpet, and the voice of words; which voice they that heard intreated that the word should not be spoken to them any more:

^20(For they could not endure that which was commanded, And if so much as a beast touch the mountain, it shall be stoned, or thrust through with a dart:

^21And so terrible was the sight, that Moses said, I exceedingly fear and quake:)

^22But ye are come unto mount Sion, and unto the city of the living God, the heavenly Jerusalem, and to an innumerable company of angels,

^23To the general assembly and church of the firstborn, which are written in heaven, and to God the Judge of all, and to the spirits of just men made perfect,

^24And to Jesus the mediator of the new covenant, and to the blood of sprinkling, that speaketh better things than that of Abel.

^25See that ye refuse not him that speaketh. For if they escaped not who refused him that spake on earth, much more shall not we escape, if we turn away from him that speaketh from heaven:

^26Whose voice then shook the earth: but now he hath promised, saying, Yet once more I shake not the earth only, but also heaven.

^27And this word, Yet once more, signifieth the removing of those things that are shaken, as of things that are made, that those things which cannot be shaken may remain.

^28Wherefore we receiving a kingdom which cannot be moved, let us have grace, whereby we may serve God acceptably with reverence and godly fear:

^29For our God is a consuming fire.

XIII

^1Let brotherly love continue.

^2Be not forgetful to entertain strangers: for thereby some have entertained angels unawares.

^3Remember them that are in bonds, as bound with them; and them which suffer adversity, as being yourselves also in the body.

^4Marriage is honourable in all, and the bed undefiled: but whoremongers and adulterers God will judge.

^5Let your conversation be without covetousness; and be content with such things as ye have: for he hath said, I will never leave thee, nor forsake thee.

^6So that we may boldly say, The Lord is my helper, and I will not fear what man shall do unto me.

^7Remember them which have the rule over you, who have spoken unto you the word of God: whose faith follow, considering the end of their conversation.

^8Jesus Christ the same yesterday, and to day, and for ever.

^9Be not carried about with divers and strange doctrines. For it is a good thing that the heart be established with grace; not with meats, which have not profited them that have been occupied therein.

^10We have an altar, whereof they have no right to eat which serve the tabernacle.

^11For the bodies of those beasts, whose blood is brought into the sanctuary by the high priest for sin, are burned without the camp.

^12Wherefore Jesus also, that he might sanctify the people with his own blood, suffered without the gate.

^13Let us go forth therefore unto him without the camp, bearing his reproach.

^14For here have we no continuing city, but we seek one to come.

^15By him therefore let us offer the sacrifice of praise to God continually, that is, the fruit of our lips giving thanks to his name.

^16But to do good and to communicate forget not: for with such sacrifices God is well pleased.

^17Obey them that have the rule over you, and submit yourselves: for they watch for your souls, as they that must give account, that they may do it with joy, and not with grief: for that is unprofitable for you.

^18Pray for us: for we trust we have a good conscience, in all things willing to live honestly.

^19But I beseech you the rather to do this, that I may be restored to you the sooner.

^20Now the God of peace, that brought again from the dead our Lord Jesus, that great shepherd of the sheep, through the blood of the everlasting covenant,

^21Make you perfect in every good work to do his will, working in you that which is wellpleasing in his sight, through Jesus Christ; to whom be glory for ever and ever. Amen.

^22And I beseech you, brethren, suffer the word of exhortation: for I have written a letter unto you in few words.

^23Know ye that our brother Timothy is set at liberty; with whom, if he come shortly, I will see you.

^24Salute all them that have the rule over you, and all the saints. They of Italy salute you.

^25Grace be with you all. Amen.

James 1

1^1James, a servant of God and of the Lord Jesus Christ, to the twelve tribes which are scattered abroad, greeting.

^2My brethren, count it all joy when ye fall into divers temptations;

^3Knowing this, that the trying of your faith worketh patience.

^4But let patience have her perfect work, that ye may be perfect and entire, wanting nothing.

^5If any of you lack wisdom, let him ask of God, that giveth to all men liberally, and upbraideth not; and it shall be given him.

^6But let him ask in faith, nothing wavering. For he that wavereth is like a wave of the sea driven with the wind and tossed.

^7For let not that man think that he shall receive any thing of the Lord.

^8A double minded man is unstable in all his ways.

^9Let the brother of low degree rejoice in that he is exalted:

^10But the rich, in that he is made low: because as the flower of the grass he shall pass away.

^11For the sun is no sooner risen with a burning heat, but it withereth the grass, and the flower thereof falleth, and the grace of the fashion of it perisheth: so also shall the rich man fade away in his ways.

^12Blessed is the man that endureth temptation: for when he is tried, he shall receive the crown of life, which the Lord hath promised to them that love him.

^13Let no man say when he is tempted, I am tempted of God: for God cannot be tempted with evil, neither tempteth he any man:

^14But every man is tempted, when he is drawn away of his own lust, and enticed.

^15Then when lust hath conceived, it bringeth forth sin: and sin, when it is finished, bringeth forth death.

^16Do not err, my beloved brethren.

^17Every good gift and every perfect gift is from above, and cometh down from the Father of lights, with whom is no variableness, neither shadow of turning.

^18Of his own will begat he us with the word of truth, that we should be a kind of firstfruits of his creatures.

^19Wherefore, my beloved brethren, let every man be swift to hear, slow to speak, slow to wrath:

^20For the wrath of man worketh not the righteousness of God.

^21Wherefore lay apart all filthiness and superfluity of naughtiness, and receive with meekness the engrafted word, which is able to save your souls.

^22But be ye doers of the word, and not hearers only, deceiving your own selves.

^23For if any be a hearer of the word, and not a doer, he is like unto a man beholding his natural face in a glass:

^24For he beholdeth himself, and goeth his way, and straightway forgetteth what manner of man he was.

^25But whoso looketh into the perfect law of liberty, and continueth therein, he being not a forgetful hearer, but a doer of the work, this man shall be blessed in his deed.

^26If any man among you seem to be religious, and bridleth not his tongue, but deceiveth his own heart, this man’s religion is vain.

^27Pure religion and undefiled before God and the Father is this, To visit the fatherless and widows in their affliction, and to keep himself unspotted from the world.

James 2

2^1My brethren, have not the faith of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Lord of glory, with respect of persons.

^2For if there come unto your assembly a man with a gold ring, in goodly apparel, and there come in also a poor man in vile raiment;

^3And ye have respect to him that weareth the gay clothing, and say unto him, Sit thou here in a good place; and say to the poor, Stand thou there, or sit here under my footstool:

^4Are ye not then partial in yourselves, and are become judges of evil thoughts?

^5Hearken, my beloved brethren, Hath not God chosen the poor of this world rich in faith, and heirs of the kingdom which he hath promised to them that love him?

^6But ye have despised the poor. Do not rich men oppress you, and draw you before the judgment seats?

^7Do not they blaspheme that worthy name by the which ye are called?

^8If ye fulfil the royal law according to the scripture, Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself, ye do well:

^9But if ye have respect to persons, ye commit sin, and are convinced of the law as transgressors.

^10For whosoever shall keep the whole law, and yet offend in one point, he is guilty of all.

^11For he that said, Do not commit adultery, said also, Do not kill. Now if thou commit no adultery, yet if thou kill, thou art become a transgressor of the law.

^12So speak ye, and so do, as they that shall be judged by the law of liberty.

^13For he shall have judgment without mercy, that hath shewed no mercy; and mercy rejoiceth against judgment.

^14What doth it profit, my brethren, though a man say he hath faith, and have not works? can faith save him?

^15If a brother or sister be naked, and destitute of daily food,

^16And one of you say unto them, Depart in peace, be ye warmed and filled; notwithstanding ye give them not those things which are needful to the body; what doth it profit?

^17Even so faith, if it hath not works, is dead, being alone.

^18Yea, a man may say, Thou hast faith, and I have works: shew me thy faith without thy works, and I will shew thee my faith by my works.

^19Thou believest that there is one God; thou doest well: the devils also believe, and tremble.

^20But wilt thou know, O vain man, that faith without works is dead?

^21Was not Abraham our father justified by works, when he had offered Isaac his son upon the altar?

^22Seest thou how faith wrought with his works, and by works was faith made perfect?

^23And the scripture was fulfilled which saith, Abraham believed God, and it was imputed unto him for righteousness: and he was called the Friend of God.

^24Ye see then how that by works a man is justified, and not by faith only.

^25Likewise also was not Rahab the harlot justified by works, when she had received the messengers, and had sent them out another way?

^26For as the body without the spirit is dead, so faith without works is dead also.

James 3

3^1My brethren, be not many masters, knowing that we shall receive the greater condemnation.

^2For in many things we offend all. If any man offend not in word, the same is a perfect man, and able also to bridle the whole body.

^3Behold, we put bits in the horses’ mouths, that they may obey us; and we turn about their whole body.

^4Behold also the ships, which though they be so great, and are driven of fierce winds, yet are they turned about with a very small helm, whithersoever the governor listeth.

^5Even so the tongue is a little member, and boasteth great things. Behold, how great a matter a little fire kindleth!

^6And the tongue is a fire, a world of iniquity: so is the tongue among our members, that it defileth the whole body, and setteth on fire the course of nature; and it is set on fire of hell.

^7For every kind of beasts, and of birds, and of serpents, and of things in the sea, is tamed, and hath been tamed of mankind:

^8But the tongue can no man tame; it is an unruly evil, full of deadly poison.

^9Therewith bless we God, even the Father; and therewith curse we men, which are made after the similitude of God.

^10Out of the same mouth proceedeth blessing and cursing. My brethren, these things ought not so to be.

^11Doth a fountain send forth at the same place sweet water and bitter?

^12Can the fig tree, my brethren, bear olive berries? either a vine, figs? so can no fountain both yield salt water and fresh.

^13Who is a wise man and endued with knowledge among you? let him shew out of a good conversation his works with meekness of wisdom.

^14But if ye have bitter envying and strife in your hearts, glory not, and lie not against the truth.

^15This wisdom descendeth not from above, but is earthly, sensual, devilish.

^16For where envying and strife is, there is confusion and every evil work.

^17But the wisdom that is from above is first pure, then peaceable, gentle, and easy to be intreated, full of mercy and good fruits, without partiality, and without hypocrisy.

^18And the fruit of righteousness is sown in peace of them that make peace.

James 4

4^1From whence come wars and fightings among you? come they not hence, even of your lusts that war in your members?

^2Ye lust, and have not: ye kill, and desire to have, and cannot obtain: ye fight and war, yet ye have not, because ye ask not.

^3Ye ask, and receive not, because ye ask amiss, that ye may consume it upon your lusts.

^4Ye adulterers and adulteresses, know ye not that the friendship of the world is enmity with God? whosoever therefore will be a friend of the world is the enemy of God.

^5Do ye think that the scripture saith in vain, The spirit that dwelleth in us lusteth to envy?

^6But he giveth more grace. Wherefore he saith, God resisteth the proud, but giveth grace unto the humble.

^7Submit yourselves therefore to God. Resist the devil, and he will flee from you.

^8Draw nigh to God, and he will draw nigh to you. Cleanse your hands, ye sinners; and purify your hearts, ye double minded.

^9Be afflicted, and mourn, and weep: let your laughter be turned to mourning, and your joy to heaviness.

^10Humble yourselves in the sight of the Lord, and he shall lift you up.

^11Speak not evil one of another, brethren. He that speaketh evil of his brother, and judgeth his brother, speaketh evil of the law, and judgeth the law: but if thou judge the law, thou art not a doer of the law, but a judge.

^12There is one lawgiver, who is able to save and to destroy: who art thou that judgest another?

^13Go to now, ye that say, To day or to morrow we will go into such a city, and continue there a year, and buy and sell, and get gain:

^14Whereas ye know not what shall be on the morrow. For what is your life? It is even a vapour, that appeareth for a little time, and then vanisheth away.

^15For that ye ought to say, If the Lord will, we shall live, and do this, or that.

^16But now ye rejoice in your boastings: all such rejoicing is evil.

^17Therefore to him that knoweth to do good, and doeth it not, to him it is sin.

James 5

5^1Go to now, ye rich men, weep and howl for your miseries that shall come upon you.

^2Your riches are corrupted, and your garments are motheaten.

^3Your gold and silver is cankered; and the rust of them shall be a witness against you, and shall eat your flesh as it were fire. Ye have heaped treasure together for the last days.

^4Behold, the hire of the labourers who have reaped down your fields, which is of you kept back by fraud, crieth: and the cries of them which have reaped are entered into the ears of the Lord of sabaoth.

^5Ye have lived in pleasure on the earth, and been wanton; ye have nourished your hearts, as in a day of slaughter.

^6Ye have condemned and killed the just; and he doth not resist you.

^7Be patient therefore, brethren, unto the coming of the Lord. Behold, the husbandman waiteth for the precious fruit of the earth, and hath long patience for it, until he receive the early and latter rain.

^8Be ye also patient; stablish your hearts: for the coming of the Lord draweth nigh.

^9Grudge not one against another, brethren, lest ye be condemned: behold, the judge standeth before the door.

^10Take, my brethren, the prophets, who have spoken in the name of the Lord, for an example of suffering affliction, and of patience.

^11Behold, we count them happy which endure. Ye have heard of the patience of Job, and have seen the end of the Lord; that the Lord is very pitiful, and of tender mercy.

^12But above all things, my brethren, swear not, neither by heaven, neither by the earth, neither by any other oath: but let your yea be yea; and your nay, nay; lest ye fall into condemnation.

^13Is any among you afflicted? let him pray. Is any merry? let him sing psalms.

^14Is any sick among you? let him call for the elders of the church; and let them pray over him, anointing him with oil in the name of the Lord:

^15And the prayer of faith shall save the sick, and the Lord shall raise him up; and if he have committed sins, they shall be forgiven him.

^16Confess your faults one to another, and pray one for another, that ye may be healed. The effectual fervent prayer of a righteous man availeth much.

^17Elias was a man subject to like passions as we are, and he prayed earnestly that it might not rain: and it rained not on the earth by the space of three years and six months.

^18And he prayed again, and the heaven gave rain, and the earth brought forth her fruit.

^19Brethren, if any of you do err from the truth, and one convert him;

^20Let him know, that he which converteth the sinner from the error of his way shall save a soul from death, and shall hide a multitude of sins.

Book 60 1 Peter

60:001:001 Peter, an apostle of Jesus Christ, to the strangers scattered throughout Pontus, Galatia, Cappadocia, Asia, and Bithynia,

60:001:002 Elect according to the foreknowledge of God the Father, through sanctification of the Spirit, unto obedience and sprinkling of the blood of Jesus Christ: Grace unto you, and peace, be multiplied.

60:001:003 Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, which according to his abundant mercy hath begotten us again unto a lively hope by the resurrection of Jesus Christ from the dead,

60:001:004 To an inheritance incorruptible, and undefiled, and that fadeth not away, reserved in heaven for you,

60:001:005 Who are kept by the power of God through faith unto salvation ready to be revealed in the last time.

60:001:006 Wherein ye greatly rejoice, though now for a season, if need be, ye are in heaviness through manifold temptations:

60:001:007 That the trial of your faith, being much more precious than of gold that perisheth, though it be tried with fire, might be found unto praise and honour and glory at the appearing of Jesus Christ:

60:001:008 Whom having not seen, ye love; in whom, though now ye see him not, yet believing, ye rejoice with joy unspeakable and full of glory:

60:001:009 Receiving the end of your faith, even the salvation of your souls.

60:001:010 Of which salvation the prophets have enquired and searched diligently, who prophesied of the grace that should come unto you:

60:001:011 Searching what, or what manner of time the Spirit of Christ which was in them did signify, when it testified beforehand the sufferings of Christ, and the glory that should follow.

60:001:012 Unto whom it was revealed, that not unto themselves, but unto us they did minister the things, which are now reported unto you by them that have preached the gospel unto you with the Holy Ghost sent down from heaven; which things the angels desire to look into.

60:001:013 Wherefore gird up the loins of your mind, be sober, and hope to the end for the grace that is to be brought unto you at the revelation of Jesus Christ;

60:001:014 As obedient children, not fashioning yourselves according to the former lusts in your ignorance:

60:001:015 But as he which hath called you is holy, so be ye holy in all manner of conversation;

60:001:016 Because it is written, Be ye holy; for I am holy.

60:001:017 And if ye call on the Father, who without respect of persons judgeth according to every man's work, pass the time of your sojourning here in fear:

60:001:018 Forasmuch as ye know that ye were not redeemed with corruptible things, as silver and gold, from your vain conversation received by tradition from your fathers;

60:001:019 But with the precious blood of Christ, as of a lamb without blemish and without spot:

60:001:020 Who verily was foreordained before the foundation of the world, but was manifest in these last times for you,

60:001:021 Who by him do believe in God, that raised him up from the dead, and gave him glory; that your faith and hope might be in God.

60:001:022 Seeing ye have purified your souls in obeying the truth through the Spirit unto unfeigned love of the brethren, see that ye love one another with a pure heart fervently:

60:001:023 Being born again, not of corruptible seed, but of incorruptible, by the word of God, which liveth and abideth for ever.

60:001:024 For all flesh is as grass, and all the glory of man as the flower of grass. The grass withereth, and the flower thereof falleth away:

60:001:025 But the word of the Lord endureth for ever. And this is the word which by the gospel is preached unto you.

60:002:001 Wherefore laying aside all malice, and all guile, and hypocrisies, and envies, all evil speakings,

60:002:002 As newborn babes, desire the sincere milk of the word, that ye may grow thereby:

60:002:003 If so be ye have tasted that the Lord is gracious.

60:002:004 To whom coming, as unto a living stone, disallowed indeed of men, but chosen of God, and precious,

60:002:005 Ye also, as lively stones, are built up a spiritual house, an holy priesthood, to offer up spiritual sacrifices, acceptable to God by Jesus Christ.

60:002:006 Wherefore also it is contained in the scripture, Behold, I lay in Sion a chief corner stone, elect, precious: and he that believeth on him shall not be confounded.

60:002:007 Unto you therefore which believe he is precious: but unto them which be disobedient, the stone which the builders disallowed, the same is made the head of the corner,

60:002:008 And a stone of stumbling, and a rock of offence, even to them which stumble at the word, being disobedient: whereunto also they were appointed.

60:002:009 But ye are a chosen generation, a royal priesthood, an holy nation, a peculiar people; that ye should shew forth the praises of him who hath called you out of darkness into his marvellous light;

60:002:010 Which in time past were not a people, but are now the people of God: which had not obtained mercy, but now have obtained mercy.

60:002:011 Dearly beloved, I beseech you as strangers and pilgrims, abstain from fleshly lusts, which war against the soul;

60:002:012 Having your conversation honest among the Gentiles: that, whereas they speak against you as evildoers, they may by your good works, which they shall behold, glorify God in the day of visitation.

60:002:013 Submit yourselves to every ordinance of man for the Lord's sake: whether it be to the king, as supreme;

60:002:014 Or unto governors, as unto them that are sent by him for the punishment of evildoers, and for the praise of them that do well.

60:002:015 For so is the will of God, that with well doing ye may put to silence the ignorance of foolish men:

60:002:016 As free, and not using your liberty for a cloke of maliciousness, but as the servants of God.

60:002:017 Honour all men. Love the brotherhood. Fear God. Honour the king.

60:002:018 Servants, be subject to your masters with all fear; not only to the good and gentle, but also to the froward.

60:002:019 For this is thankworthy, if a man for conscience toward God endure grief, suffering wrongfully.

60:002:020 For what glory is it, if, when ye be buffeted for your faults, ye shall take it patiently? but if, when ye do well, and suffer for it, ye take it patiently, this is acceptable with God.

60:002:021 For even hereunto were ye called: because Christ also suffered for us, leaving us an example, that ye should follow his steps:

60:002:022 Who did no sin, neither was guile found in his mouth:

60:002:023 Who, when he was reviled, reviled not again; when he suffered, he threatened not; but committed himself to him that judgeth righteously:

60:002:024 Who his own self bare our sins in his own body on the tree, that we, being dead to sins, should live unto righteousness: by whose stripes ye were healed.

60:002:025 For ye were as sheep going astray; but are now returned unto the Shepherd and Bishop of your souls.

60:003:001 Likewise, ye wives, be in subjection to your own husbands; that, if any obey not the word, they also may without the word be won by the conversation of the wives;

60:003:002 While they behold your chaste conversation coupled with fear.

60:003:003 Whose adorning let it not be that outward adorning of plaiting the hair, and of wearing of gold, or of putting on of apparel;

60:003:004 But let it be the hidden man of the heart, in that which is not corruptible, even the ornament of a meek and quiet spirit, which is in the sight of God of great price.

60:003:005 For after this manner in the old time the holy women also, who trusted in God, adorned themselves, being in subjection unto their own husbands:

60:003:006 Even as Sara obeyed Abraham, calling him lord: whose daughters ye are, as long as ye do well, and are not afraid with any amazement.

60:003:007 Likewise, ye husbands, dwell with them according to knowledge, giving honour unto the wife, as unto the weaker vessel, and as being heirs together of the grace of life; that your prayers be not hindered.

60:003:008 Finally, be ye all of one mind, having compassion one of another, love as brethren, be pitiful, be courteous:

60:003:009 Not rendering evil for evil, or railing for railing: but contrariwise blessing; knowing that ye are thereunto called, that ye should inherit a blessing.

60:003:010 For he that will love life, and see good days, let him refrain his tongue from evil, and his lips that they speak no guile:

60:003:011 Let him eschew evil, and do good; let him seek peace, and ensue it.

60:003:012 For the eyes of the Lord are over the righteous, and his ears are open unto their prayers: but the face of the Lord is against them that do evil.

60:003:013 And who is he that will harm you, if ye be followers of that which is good?

60:003:014 But and if ye suffer for righteousness' sake, happy are ye: and be not afraid of their terror, neither be troubled;

60:003:015 But sanctify the Lord God in your hearts: and be ready always to give an answer to every man that asketh you a reason of the hope that is in you with meekness and fear:

60:003:016 Having a good conscience; that, whereas they speak evil of you, as of evildoers, they may be ashamed that falsely accuse your good conversation in Christ.

60:003:017 For it is better, if the will of God be so, that ye suffer for well doing, than for evil doing.

60:003:018 For Christ also hath once suffered for sins, the just for the unjust, that he might bring us to God, being put to death in the flesh, but quickened by the Spirit:

60:003:019 By which also he went and preached unto the spirits in prison;

60:003:020 Which sometime were disobedient, when once the longsuffering of God waited in the days of Noah, while the ark was a preparing, wherein few, that is, eight souls were saved by water.

60:003:021 The like figure whereunto even baptism doth also now save us (not the putting away of the filth of the flesh, but the answer of a good conscience toward God,) by the resurrection of Jesus Christ:

60:003:022 Who is gone into heaven, and is on the right hand of God; angels and authorities and powers being made subject unto him.

60:004:001 Forasmuch then as Christ hath suffered for us in the flesh, arm yourselves likewise with the same mind: for he that hath suffered in the flesh hath ceased from sin;

60:004:002 That he no longer should live the rest of his time in the flesh to the lusts of men, but to the will of God.

60:004:003 For the time past of our life may suffice us to have wrought the will of the Gentiles, when we walked in lasciviousness, lusts, excess of wine, revellings, banquetings, and abominable idolatries:

60:004:004 Wherein they think it strange that ye run not with them to the same excess of riot, speaking evil of you:

60:004:005 Who shall give account to him that is ready to judge the quick and the dead.

60:004:006 For for this cause was the gospel preached also to them that are dead, that they might be judged according to men in the flesh, but live according to God in the spirit.

60:004:007 But the end of all things is at hand: be ye therefore sober, and watch unto prayer.

60:004:008 And above all things have fervent charity among yourselves: for charity shall cover the multitude of sins.

60:004:009 Use hospitality one to another without grudging.

60:004:010 As every man hath received the gift, even so minister the same one to another, as good stewards of the manifold grace of God.

60:004:011 If any man speak, let him speak as the oracles of God; if any man minister, let him do it as of the ability which God giveth: that God in all things may be glorified through Jesus Christ, to whom be praise and dominion for ever and ever. Amen.

60:004:012 Beloved, think it not strange concerning the fiery trial which is to try you, as though some strange thing happened unto you:

60:004:013 But rejoice, inasmuch as ye are partakers of Christ's sufferings; that, when his glory shall be revealed, ye may be glad also with exceeding joy.

60:004:014 If ye be reproached for the name of Christ, happy are ye; for the spirit of glory and of God resteth upon you: on their part he is evil spoken of, but on your part he is glorified.

60:004:015 But let none of you suffer as a murderer, or as a thief, or as an evildoer, or as a busybody in other men's matters.

60:004:016 Yet if any man suffer as a Christian, let him not be ashamed; but let him glorify God on this behalf.

60:004:017 For the time is come that judgment must begin at the house of God: and if it first begin at us, what shall the end be of them that obey not the gospel of God?

60:004:018 And if the righteous scarcely be saved, where shall the ungodly and the sinner appear?

60:004:019 Wherefore let them that suffer according to the will of God commit the keeping of their souls to him in well doing, as unto a faithful Creator.

60:005:001 The elders which are among you I exhort, who am also an elder, and a witness of the sufferings of Christ, and also a partaker of the glory that shall be revealed:

60:005:002 Feed the flock of God which is among you, taking the oversight thereof, not by constraint, but willingly; not for filthy lucre, but of a ready mind;

60:005:003 Neither as being lords over God's heritage, but being ensamples to the flock.

60:005:004 And when the chief Shepherd shall appear, ye shall receive a crown of glory that fadeth not away.

60:005:005 Likewise, ye younger, submit yourselves unto the elder. Yea, all of you be subject one to another, and be clothed with humility: for God resisteth the proud, and giveth grace to the humble.

60:005:006 Humble yourselves therefore under the mighty hand of God, that he may exalt you in due time:

60:005:007 Casting all your care upon him; for he careth for you.

60:005:008 Be sober, be vigilant; because your adversary the devil, as a roaring lion, walketh about, seeking whom he may devour:

60:005:009 Whom resist stedfast in the faith, knowing that the same afflictions are accomplished in your brethren that are in the world.

60:005:010 But the God of all grace, who hath called us unto his eternal glory by Christ Jesus, after that ye have suffered a while, make you perfect, stablish, strengthen, settle you.

60:005:011 To him be glory and dominion for ever and ever. Amen.

60:005:012 By Silvanus, a faithful brother unto you, as I suppose, I have written briefly, exhorting, and testifying that this is the true grace of God wherein ye stand.

60:005:013 The church that is at Babylon, elected together with you, saluteth you; and so doth Marcus my son.

60:005:014 Greet ye one another with a kiss of charity. Peace be with you all that are in Christ Jesus. Amen.

II Peter 1

1^1Simon Peter, a servant and an apostle of Jesus Christ, to them that have obtained like precious faith with us through the righteousness of God and our Saviour Jesus Christ:

^2Grace and peace be multiplied unto you through the knowledge of God, and of Jesus our Lord,

^3According as his divine power hath given unto us all things that pertain unto life and godliness, through the knowledge of him that hath called us to glory and virtue:

^4Whereby are given unto us exceeding great and precious promises: that by these ye might be partakers of the divine nature, having escaped the corruption that is in the world through lust.

^5And beside this, giving all diligence, add to your faith virtue; and to virtue knowledge;

^6And to knowledge temperance; and to temperance patience; and to patience godliness;

^7And to godliness brotherly kindness; and to brotherly kindness charity.

^8For if these things be in you, and abound, they make you that ye shall neither be barren nor unfruitful in the knowledge of our Lord Jesus Christ.

^9But he that lacketh these things is blind, and cannot see afar off, and hath forgotten that he was purged from his old sins.

^10Wherefore the rather, brethren, give diligence to make your calling and election sure: for if ye do these things, ye shall never fall:

^11For so an entrance shall be ministered unto you abundantly into the everlasting kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ.

^12Wherefore I will not be negligent to put you always in remembrance of these things, though ye know them, and be established in the present truth.

^13Yea, I think it meet, as long as I am in this tabernacle, to stir you up by putting you in remembrance;

^14Knowing that shortly I must put off this my tabernacle, even as our Lord Jesus Christ hath shewed me.

^15Moreover I will endeavour that ye may be able after my decease to have these things always in remembrance.

^16For we have not followed cunningly devised fables, when we made known unto you the power and coming of our Lord Jesus Christ, but were eyewitnesses of his majesty.

^17For he received from God the Father honour and glory, when there came such a voice to him from the excellent glory, This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased.

^18And this voice which came from heaven we heard, when we were with him in the holy mount.

^19We have also a more sure word of prophecy; whereunto ye do well that ye take heed, as unto a light that shineth in a dark place, until the day dawn, and the day star arise in your hearts:

^20Knowing this first, that no prophecy of the scripture is of any private interpretation.

^21For the prophecy came not in old time by the will of man: but holy men of God spake as they were moved by the Holy Ghost.

II Peter 2

2^1But there were false prophets also among the people, even as there shall be false teachers among you, who privily shall bring in damnable heresies, even denying the Lord that bought them, and bring upon themselves swift destruction.

^2And many shall follow their pernicious ways; by reason of whom the way of truth shall be evil spoken of.

^3And through covetousness shall they with feigned words make merchandise of you: whose judgment now of a long time lingereth not, and their damnation slumbereth not.

^4For if God spared not the angels that sinned, but cast them down to hell, and delivered them into chains of darkness, to be reserved unto judgment;

^5And spared not the old world, but saved Noah the eighth person, a preacher of righteousness, bringing in the flood upon the world of the ungodly;

^6And turning the cities of Sodom and Gomorrha into ashes condemned them with an overthrow, making them an ensample unto those that after should live ungodly;

^7And delivered just Lot, vexed with the filthy conversation of the wicked:

^8(For that righteous man dwelling among them, in seeing and hearing, vexed his righteous soul from day to day with their unlawful deeds;)

^9The Lord knoweth how to deliver the godly out of temptations, and to reserve the unjust unto the day of judgment to be punished:

^10But chiefly them that walk after the flesh in the lust of uncleanness, and despise government. Presumptuous are they, selfwilled, they are not afraid to speak evil of dignities.

^11Whereas angels, which are greater in power and might, bring not railing accusation against them before the Lord.

^12But these, as natural brute beasts, made to be taken and destroyed, speak evil of the things that they understand not; and shall utterly perish in their own corruption;

^13And shall receive the reward of unrighteousness, as they that count it pleasure to riot in the day time. Spots they are and blemishes, sporting themselves with their own deceivings while they feast with you;

^14Having eyes full of adultery, and that cannot cease from sin; beguiling unstable souls: an heart they have exercised with covetous practices; cursed children:

^15Which have forsaken the right way, and are gone astray, following the way of Balaam the son of Bosor, who loved the wages of unrighteousness;

^16But was rebuked for his iniquity: the dumb ass speaking with man’s voice forbad the madness of the prophet.

^17These are wells without water, clouds that are carried with a tempest; to whom the mist of darkness is reserved for ever.

^18For when they speak great swelling words of vanity, they allure through the lusts of the flesh, through much wantonness, those that were clean escaped from them who live in error.

^19While they promise them liberty, they themselves are the servants of corruption: for of whom a man is overcome, of the same is he brought in bondage.

^20For if after they have escaped the pollutions of the world through the knowledge of the Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ, they are again entangled therein, and overcome, the latter end is worse with them than the beginning.

^21For it had been better for them not to have known the way of righteousness, than, after they have known it, to turn from the holy commandment delivered unto them.

^22But it is happened unto them according to the true proverb, The dog is turned to his own vomit again; and the sow that was washed to her wallowing in the mire.

II Peter 3

3^1This second epistle, beloved, I now write unto you; in both which I stir up your pure minds by way of remembrance:

^2That ye may be mindful of the words which were spoken before by the holy prophets, and of the commandment of us the apostles of the Lord and Saviour:

^3Knowing this first, that there shall come in the last days scoffers, walking after their own lusts,

^4And saying, Where is the promise of his coming? for since the fathers fell asleep, all things continue as they were from the beginning of the creation.

^5For this they willingly are ignorant of, that by the word of God the heavens were of old, and the earth standing out of the water and in the water:

^6Whereby the world that then was, being overflowed with water, perished:

^7But the heavens and the earth, which are now, by the same word are kept in store, reserved unto fire against the day of judgment and perdition of ungodly men.

^8But, beloved, be not ignorant of this one thing, that one day is with the Lord as a thousand years, and a thousand years as one day.

^9The Lord is not slack concerning his promise, as some men count slackness; but is longsuffering to us-ward, not willing that any should perish, but that all should come to repentance.

^10But the day of the Lord will come as a thief in the night; in the which the heavens shall pass away with a great noise, and the elements shall melt with fervent heat, the earth also and the works that are therein shall be burned up.

^11Seeing then that all these things shall be dissolved, what manner of persons ought ye to be in all holy conversation and godliness,

^12Looking for and hasting unto the coming of the day of God, wherein the heavens being on fire shall be dissolved, and the elements shall melt with fervent heat?

^13Nevertheless we, according to his promise, look for new heavens and a new earth, wherein dwelleth righteousness.

^14Wherefore, beloved, seeing that ye look for such things, be diligent that ye may be found of him in peace, without spot, and blameless.

^15And account that the longsuffering of our Lord is salvation; even as our beloved brother Paul also according to the wisdom given unto him hath written unto you;

^16As also in all his epistles, speaking in them of these things; in which are some things hard to be understood, which they that are unlearned and unstable wrest, as they do also the other scriptures, unto their own destruction.

^17Ye therefore, beloved, seeing ye know these things before, beware lest ye also, being led away with the error of the wicked, fall from your own stedfastness.

^18But grow in grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ. To him be glory both now and for ever. Amen.

I John

The First Epistle of

John

I

^1That which was from the beginning, which we have heard, which we have seen with our eyes, which we have looked upon, and our hands have handled, of the Word of life;

^2(For the life was manifested, and we have seen it, and bear witness, and shew unto you that eternal life, which was with the Father, and was manifested unto us;)

^3That which we have seen and heard declare we unto you, that ye also may have fellowship with us: and truly our fellowship is with the Father, and with his Son Jesus Christ.

^4And these things write we unto you, that your joy may be full.

^5This then is the message which we have heard of him, and declare unto you, that God is light, and in him is no darkness at all.

^6If we say that we have fellowship with him, and walk in darkness, we lie, and do not the truth:

^7But if we walk in the light, as he is in the light, we have fellowship one with another, and the blood of Jesus Christ his Son cleanseth us from all sin.

^8If we say that we have no sin, we deceive ourselves, and the truth is not in us.

^9If we confess our sins, he is faithful and just to forgive us our sins, and to cleanse us from all unrighteousness.

^10If we say that we have not sinned, we make him a liar, and his word is not in us.

II

^1My little children, these things write I unto you, that ye sin not. And if any man sin, we have an advocate with the Father, Jesus Christ the righteous:

^2And he is the propitiation for our sins: and not for our’s only, but also for the sins of the whole world.

^3And hereby we do know that we know him, if we keep his commandments.

^4He that saith, I know him, and keepeth not his commandments, is a liar, and the truth is not in him.

^5But whoso keepeth his word, in him verily is the love of God perfected: hereby know we that we are in him.

^6He that saith he abideth in him ought himself also so to walk, even as he walked.

^7Brethren, I write no new commandment unto you, but an old commandment which ye had from the beginning. The old commandment is the word which ye have heard from the beginning.

^8Again, a new commandment I write unto you, which thing is true in him and in you: because the darkness is past, and the true light now shineth.

^9He that saith he is in the light, and hateth his brother, is in darkness even until now.

^10He that loveth his brother abideth in the light, and there is none occasion of stumbling in him.

^11But he that hateth his brother is in darkness, and walketh in darkness, and knoweth not whither he goeth, because that darkness hath blinded his eyes.

^12I write unto you, little children, because your sins are forgiven you for his name’s sake.

^13I write unto you, fathers, because ye have known him that is from the beginning. I write unto you, young men, because ye have overcome the wicked one. I write unto you, little children, because ye have known the Father.

^14I have written unto you, fathers, because ye have known him that is from the beginning. I have written unto you, young men, because ye are strong, and the word of God abideth in you, and ye have overcome the wicked one.

^15Love not the world, neither the things that are in the world. If any man love the world, the love of the Father is not in him.

^16For all that is in the world, the lust of the flesh, and the lust of the eyes, and the pride of life, is not of the Father, but is of the world.

^17And the world passeth away, and the lust thereof: but he that doeth the will of God abideth for ever.

^18Little children, it is the last time: and as ye have heard that antichrist shall come, even now are there many antichrists; whereby we know that it is the last time.

^19They went out from us, but they were not of us; for if they had been of us, they would no doubt have continued with us: but they went out, that they might be made manifest that they were not all of us.

^20But ye have an unction from the Holy One, and ye know all things.

^21I have not written unto you because ye know not the truth, but because ye know it, and that no lie is of the truth.

^22Who is a liar but he that denieth that Jesus is the Christ? He is antichrist, that denieth the Father and the Son.

^23Whosoever denieth the Son, the same hath not the Father: he that acknowledgeth the Son hath the Father also.

^24Let that therefore abide in you, which ye have heard from the beginning. If that which ye have heard from the beginning shall remain in you, ye also shall continue in the Son, and in the Father.

^25And this is the promise that he hath promised us, even eternal life.

^26These things have I written unto you concerning them that seduce you.

^27But the anointing which ye have received of him abideth in you, and ye need not that any man teach you: but as the same anointing teacheth you of all things, and is truth, and is no lie, and even as it hath taught you, ye shall abide in him.

^28And now, little children, abide in him; that, when he shall appear, we may have confidence, and not be ashamed before him at his coming.

^29If ye know that he is righteous, ye know that every one that doeth righteousness is born of him.

III

^1Behold, what manner of love the Father hath bestowed upon us, that we should be called the sons of God: therefore the world knoweth us not, because it knew him not.

^2Beloved, now are we the sons of God, and it doth not yet appear what we shall be: but we know that, when he shall appear, we shall be like him; for we shall see him as he is.

^3And every man that hath this hope in him purifieth himself, even as he is pure.

^4Whosoever committeth sin transgresseth also the law: for sin is the transgression of the law.

^5And ye know that he was manifested to take away our sins; and in him is no sin.

^6Whosoever abideth in him sinneth not: whosoever sinneth hath not seen him, neither known him.

^7Little children, let no man deceive you: he that doeth righteousness is righteous, even as he is righteous.

^8He that committeth sin is of the devil; for the devil sinneth from the beginning. For this purpose the Son of God was manifested, that he might destroy the works of the devil.

^9Whosoever is born of God doth not commit sin; for his seed remaineth in him: and he cannot sin, because he is born of God.

^10In this the children of God are manifest, and the children of the devil: whosoever doeth not righteousness is not of God, neither he that loveth not his brother.

^11For this is the message that ye heard from the beginning, that we should love one another.

^12Not as Cain, who was of that wicked one, and slew his brother. And wherefore slew he him? Because his own works were evil, and his brother’s righteous.

^13Marvel not, my brethren, if the world hate you.

^14We know that we have passed from death unto life, because we love the brethren. He that loveth not his brother abideth in death.

^15Whosoever hateth his brother is a murderer: and ye know that no murderer hath eternal life abiding in him.

^16Hereby perceive we the love of God, because he laid down his life for us: and we ought to lay down our lives for the brethren.

^17But whoso hath this world’s good, and seeth his brother have need, and shutteth up his bowels of compassion from him, how dwelleth the love of God in him?

^18My little children, let us not love in word, neither in tongue; but in deed and in truth.

^19And hereby we know that we are of the truth, and shall assure our hearts before him.

^20For if our heart condemn us, God is greater than our heart, and knoweth all things.

^21Beloved, if our heart condemn us not, then have we confidence toward God.

^22And whatsoever we ask, we receive of him, because we keep his commandments, and do those things that are pleasing in his sight.

^23And this is his commandment, That we should believe on the name of his Son Jesus Christ, and love one another, as he gave us commandment.

^24And he that keepeth his commandments dwelleth in him, and he in him. And hereby we know that he abideth in us, by the Spirit which he hath given us.

IV

^1Beloved, believe not every spirit, but try the spirits whether they are of God: because many false prophets are gone out into the world.

^2Hereby know ye the Spirit of God: Every spirit that confesseth that Jesus Christ is come in the flesh is of God:

^3And every spirit that confesseth not that Jesus Christ is come in the flesh is not of God: and this is that spirit of antichrist, whereof ye have heard that it should come; and even now already is it in the world.

^4Ye are of God, little children, and have overcome them: because greater is he that is in you, than he that is in the world.

^5They are of the world: therefore speak they of the world, and the world heareth them.

^6We are of God: he that knoweth God heareth us; he that is not of God heareth not us. Hereby know we the spirit of truth, and the spirit of error.

^7Beloved, let us love one another: for love is of God; and every one that loveth is born of God, and knoweth God.

^8He that loveth not knoweth not God; for God is love.

^9In this was manifested the love of God toward us, because that God sent his only begotten Son into the world, that we might live through him.

^10Herein is love, not that we loved God, but that he loved us, and sent his Son to be the propitiation for our sins.

^11Beloved, if God so loved us, we ought also to love one another.

^12No man hath seen God at any time. If we love one another, God dwelleth in us, and his love is perfected in us.

^13Hereby know we that we dwell in him, and he in us, because he hath given us of his Spirit.

^14And we have seen and do testify that the Father sent the Son to be the Saviour of the world.

^15Whosoever shall confess that Jesus is the Son of God, God dwelleth in him, and he in God.

^16And we have known and believed the love that God hath to us. God is love; and he that dwelleth in love dwelleth in God, and God in him.

^17Herein is our love made perfect, that we may have boldness in the day of judgment: because as he is, so are we in this world.

^18There is no fear in love; but perfect love casteth out fear: because fear hath torment. He that feareth is not made perfect in love.

^19We love him, because he first loved us.

^20If a man say, I love God, and hateth his brother, he is a liar: for he that loveth not his brother whom he hath seen, how can he love God whom he hath not seen?

^21And this commandment have we from him, That he who loveth God love his brother also.

V

^1Whosoever believeth that Jesus is the Christ is born of God: and every one that loveth him that begat loveth him also that is begotten of him.

^2By this we know that we love the children of God, when we love God, and keep his commandments.

^3For this is the love of God, that we keep his commandments: and his commandments are not grievous.

^4For whatsoever is born of God overcometh the world: and this is the victory that overcometh the world, even our faith.

^5Who is he that overcometh the world, but he that believeth that Jesus is the Son of God?

^6This is he that came by water and blood, even Jesus Christ; not by water only, but by water and blood. And it is the Spirit that beareth witness, because the Spirit is truth.

^7For there are three that bear record in heaven, the Father, the Word, and the Holy Ghost: and these three are one.

^8And there are three that bear witness in earth, the Spirit, and the water, and the blood: and these three agree in one.

^9If we receive the witness of men, the witness of God is greater: for this is the witness of God which he hath testified of his Son.

^10He that believeth on the Son of God hath the witness in himself: he that believeth not God hath made him a liar; because he believeth not the record that God gave of his Son.

^11And this is the record, that God hath given to us eternal life, and this life is in his Son.

^12He that hath the Son hath life; and he that hath not the Son of God hath not life.

^13These things have I written unto you that believe on the name of the Son of God; that ye may know that ye have eternal life, and that ye may believe on the name of the Son of God.

^14And this is the confidence that we have in him, that, if we ask any thing according to his will, he heareth us:

^15And if we know that he hear us, whatsoever we ask, we know that we have the petitions that we desired of him.

^16If any man see his brother sin a sin which is not unto death, he shall ask, and he shall give him life for them that sin not unto death. There is a sin unto death: I do not say that he shall pray for it.

^17All unrighteousness is sin: and there is a sin not unto death.

^18We know that whosoever is born of God sinneth not; but he that is begotten of God keepeth himself, and that wicked one toucheth him not.

^19And we know that we are of God, and the whole world lieth in wickedness.

^20And we know that the Son of God is come, and hath given us an understanding, that we may know him that is true, and we are in him that is true, even in his Son Jesus Christ. This is the true God, and eternal life.

^21Little children, keep yourselves from idols. Amen.

III John

The Third Epistle of

John

I

1^1The elder unto the wellbeloved Gaius, whom I love in the truth.

^2Beloved, I wish above all things that thou mayest prosper and be in health, even as thy soul prospereth.

^3For I rejoiced greatly, when the brethren came and testified of the truth that is in thee, even as thou walkest in the truth.

^4I have no greater joy than to hear that my children walk in truth.

^5Beloved, thou doest faithfully whatsoever thou doest to the brethren, and to strangers;

^6Which have borne witness of thy charity before the church: whom if thou bring forward on their journey after a godly sort, thou shalt do well:

^7Because that for his name’s sake they went forth, taking nothing of the Gentiles.

^8We therefore ought to receive such, that we might be fellowhelpers to the truth.

^9I wrote unto the church: but Diotrephes, who loveth to have the preeminence among them, receiveth us not.

^10Wherefore, if I come, I will remember his deeds which he doeth, prating against us with malicious words: and not content therewith, neither doth he himself receive the brethren, and forbiddeth them that would, and casteth them out of the church.

^11Beloved, follow not that which is evil, but that which is good. He that doeth good is of God: but he that doeth evil hath not seen God.

^12Demetrius hath good report of all men, and of the truth itself: yea, and we also bear record; and ye know that our record is true.

^13I had many things to write, but I will not with ink and pen write unto thee:

^14But I trust I shall shortly see thee, and we shall speak face to face. Peace be to thee. Our friends salute thee. Greet the friends by name.